Harry had chosen to assume a rather relaxed posture, as he sat in a low chair before the mighty desk of the Headmaster of Hogwarts: one leg cocked over his knee, and his arms sprawling casually to either side. Harry was doing his best to disregard the noise from the surrounding devices, although the one directly behind him that sounded like an owl hooting desperately as it was put through a wood-chipper was pretty difficult to ignore.

‘Harry,’ the old wizard said from behind the desk, the aged voice level as the blue eyes stared out at him from beneath the shining half-moon spectacles. Headmaster Dumbledore had garbed himself in robes of midnight purple; not true formal black, but dark enough to come close indeed to deadly seriousness, as the wizarding world counted the meaning of fashions. ‘Were you … responsible for this?’

‘I cannot deny that my influence was at work,’ Harry said.

The old wizard took off his glasses, leaned forward to stare at Harry directly, blue eyes to green. ‘I will ask you one question,’ the Headmaster said in a quiet voice. ‘Do you think that what you did today was – appropriate?’

‘They were bullies and they came to that hallway with the direct intent of hurting Hermione Granger and seven other first-year children,’ Harry said levelly. ‘If I am not too young for moral judgement, then neither are they. No, Headmaster, they didn’t deserve to die. But they did deserve to be stripped naked and glued to the ceiling.’

The old wizard put his glasses back on. For the first time that Harry had seen of him, the Headmaster seemed to be at a loss for words. ‘As Merlin himself is my witness,’ said Dumbledore, ‘I haven’t the faintest notion of how I ought to react to this.’

‘That’s pretty much the effect I was aiming for,’ said Harry. He felt like he ought to be whistling a merry tune, but unfortunately he had never learned how to whistle reliably.

‘I need not ask you who is directly responsible,’ said the Headmaster. ‘Only three wizards within Hogwarts might be powerful enough. I myself did not do it. Severus has assured me he was not involved. And the third …’ The Headmaster shook his head in some dismay. ‘You loaned the Defence Professor your Cloak, Harry. I do not think that was wise. For now that he has escaped detection by simple Charms, he surely knows that it is a Deathly Hallow – if, indeed, he did not know from its first touch upon his flesh.’

‘Professor Quirrell had already deduced my possession of an invisibility cloak,’ Harry said. ‘And knowing him, he has probably guessed that it is a Deathly Hallow. But in this case, Headmaster, it so happens that Professor Quirrell was under one of those face-concealing white robes.’

There was another pause.

‘How very cunning,’ said the Headmaster. He leaned back in his throne and sighed. ‘I have spoken to the Defence Professor. Just before you, indeed. I did not quite know what to say. I told him that this was not the approved Hogwarts policy for dealing with infractions of hallway discipline, and that I did not feel it was appropriate for a Hogwarts professor to do what he had done.’

‘And what did Professor Quirrell say to that?’ said Harry, who was not impressed with Hogwarts’s current policies for enforcing hallway discipline.

The Headmaster wore a look of resignation. ‘He said: Fire me.’

Somehow Harry managed not to cheer out loud.

The Headmaster frowned. ‘But why did he do it, Harry?’

‘Because Professor Quirrell doesn’t like school bullies and I asked very politely,’ said Harry. And he was feeling bored and I thought this might cheer him up. ‘Either that or it’s part of some incredibly deep plot.’

The Headmaster rose up from behind the desk, began to pace back and forth before the hat stand that held the Sorting Hat and the red slippers. ‘Harry, do you not feel that all of this has got a bit …’

‘Awesome?’ offered Harry.

‘Utterly and completely out of hand would say it better,’ said Dumbledore. ‘I am not sure there has ever been a time in the whole history of this school when things have become so, so … I don’t have a word for this, Harry, because things have never been like this before, and so no one has ever needed to invent a word for it.’

Harry would have tried to invent words to express how deeply complimented he felt, if he hadn’t been snorting with laughter too hard to speak.

The Headmaster was regarding him with increasing graveness. ‘Harry, do you understand at all why I find these events concerning?’

‘Honestly?’ said Harry. ‘No, not really. I mean, of course Professor McGonagall would object to anything that breaks up the dull monotony of the Hogwarts school experience. But then Professor McGonagall wouldn’t set a chicken on fire.’

The frown lines deepened on Dumbledore’s wrinkled face. ‘That, Harry, is not what disturbs me,’ the Headmaster said quietly. ‘There was a full battle fought in these halls!’

‘Headmaster,’ Harry said, trying to keep his voice carefully respectful, ‘Professor Quirrell and I did not choose for that battle to happen. The bullies did that. We just decided to have the Light side win. I know there are times where the boundaries of morality are uncertain, but in this case the line separating the villains and the heroines was twenty metres tall and drawn in white fire. Our intervention may have been weird, but it certainly wasn’t wrong –’

Dumbledore had gone back to his desk, sat down in his padded throne with a dull thump, and was now covering his face with both his hands.

‘Am I missing something here?’ Harry said. ‘I thought you’d be secretly on our side, Headmaster. It was the Gryffindor thing to do. The Weasley twins would approve, Fawkes would approve –’ Harry glanced at the golden perch, but it was empty; either the phoenix had more important things to do, or the Headmaster hadn’t invited him to today’s meeting.

‘That,’ said the Headmaster in an old and tired and somewhat muffled voice, ‘is precisely the problem, Harry. There is a reason why courageous young heroes are not put in charge of schools.’

‘All right,’ Harry said. He couldn’t quite keep the skepticism out of his voice. ‘What am I missing this time?’

The old wizard lifted his head, his face now solemn, and calmer. ‘Listen, Harry,’ said Dumbledore, ‘hear me well; for all who wield power must learn this in time. Some things in this world are, indeed, truly simple. If you pick up a stone and drop it again, the earth will be no heavier for it, the stars will not move from their paths. I say this, Harry, so that you know I am not pretending to be wise, when I tell you that even as some things are simple, others are complex. There are greater wizardries which leave marks upon the world, and marks upon those who wield them, as a simple Charm would not. Those wizardries demand hesitation, consideration of consequence, a moment to weigh the meaning of their marks. And yet the most intricate magics known to me are simpler than the simplest soul. People, Harry, people are always marked, by what they do and by what is done to them. Do you, then, understand how to say, “Here is the line between hero and villain!” is not enough to say that what you did was right?’

‘Headmaster,’ Harry said evenly, ‘this is not a decision I made at random. No, I don’t know what exact effect this will have on every single one of the bullies present. But if I always waited for perfect information before I acted, I would never do anything. When it comes to the future psychological development of, say, Peregrine Derrick, beating up eight first-year girls probably wouldn’t have been good for him. And it wasn’t enough to just stop them quietly and quickly, since then they would just try again later; they had to see that there was a protective power worth fearing.’ Harry’s voice stayed level. ‘But of course, since I am a good guy, I didn’t want to permanently injure them or even cause them any pain; and yet the penalty had to be enough to weigh on the minds of anyone thinking about trying it again. So, after weighing the expected outcomes as best I could with my boundedly rational intellect, I thought it would be wisest to strip the bullies naked and glue them to the ceiling.’

The young hero stared directly into the old wizard’s gaze, unflinching green eyes locked with the blue behind the spectacles.

And since I wasn’t there and didn’t do anything personally, there’s no lawful way to punish me under the Hogwarts school rules; the only one who acted was Professor Quirrell, and he’s fireproof. And just breaking the rules to get at me wouldn’t be a wise thing to do to the hero you’re grooming to fight Lord Voldemort … This time Harry actually had tried to think through all the ramifications in advance, before he’d made the suggestion to Professor Quirrell; and for once the Defence Professor hadn’t called him a fool, just slowly smiled and then begun to laugh.

‘I understand your intentions, Harry,’ the old wizard said. ‘You think you have taught the bullies of Hogwarts a lesson. But if Peregrine Derrick could learn that lesson, he would not be Peregrine Derrick. He will only be provoked more by what you do – it is not fair, it is not right, but that is the way it is.’ The old wizard closed his eyes, as though in brief pain, and then opened them again. ‘Harry, the most painful truth any hero must learn is that the right cannot, should not, must not win every battle. All of this began when Miss Granger fought three older enemies and won. If she had been content with this, the echoes of her deed would have died away in time. Yet instead she banded together with her classmates and raised her wand in open challenge to Peregrine Derrick and all his kind; and his kind cannot but raise their own wands in answer. So Jaime Astorga went hunting her, and in the natural course he would have beaten her; it would have been a sad day, but it would have ended there. There is not enough magic in eight first-year witches all together to defeat such a foe. But you could not accept that, Harry, could not let Miss Granger learn her own lessons; and so you sent the Defence Professor to watch over them invisibly, and pierce Astorga’s shields when Daphne Greengrass struck at him –’

What? thought Harry.

The old wizard went on speaking. ‘Each time you intervened, Harry, it escalated matters further and yet further. Soon Miss Granger was facing Robert Jugson himself, the son of a Death Eater, with two strong allies at his side. Painful indeed it would have been for her, if Miss Granger had lost that battle. And yet again by your will and Quirinus’s hand, this time shown more openly, she won.’

Harry was still struggling with the notion of the Defence Professor watching invisibly over S.P.H.E.W., guarding the heroines from harm.

‘And so,’ the old wizard finished, ‘that is how we came to today, Harry, to forty-four students attacking eight first-year witches. A full battle in these halls! I know it was not your intent, but you must accept some measure of responsibility. Such things did not happen before you came to this school, not through all my decades in Hogwarts; neither when I was a student nor when I was a Professor.’

‘Thank you very much,’ Harry said evenly. ‘Though I think Professor Quirrell deserves more credit than me.’

The blue eyes widened. ‘Harry …’

‘Those bullies were attacking victims long before this year,’ Harry said. Despite his best efforts, his voice was starting to rise. ‘But nobody seems to have taught the students that they’re allowed to fight back. I know it’s much harder to ignore a two-sided fight than some helpless victims getting hexed or almost pushed out of windows, but it’s not exactly worse, is it? I wish I’d read more of Godric Gryffindor’s writings so I could quote him, there’s got to be something in there about this. Open battle may be louder than the victims suffering in silence, it may be harder to pretend that nothing is happening, but the final result is better –’

‘No, it is not,’ Dumbledore said. ‘It is not, Harry. To always fight the darkness, to never let evil pass unchallenged – that is not heroism, but simple pride. Even Godric Gryffindor did not think that every war was worth fighting, though he went his whole life from one battle to another.’ The old wizard’s voice went quieter. ‘In truth, Harry, the words you speak – they are not evil. No, not evil, and yet they have frightened me. You are one who might someday wield great power, over wizardry, over your fellow wizards. And if, come that day, you still think that evil must never pass unchallenged –’ Now a note of real worry had entered the Headmaster’s voice. ‘The world has grown more fragile since the age when Hogwarts was raised; I fear it cannot bear the fury of another Godric Gryffindor. And he was slower to his wrath than you.’ The old wizard shook his head. ‘You are too ready to fight, Harry. Much too ready to fight, and Hogwarts itself is becoming a more violent place around you.’

‘Well,’ Harry said carefully, after weighing his words. ‘I don’t know if it will help to say this, but I think you’re getting the wrong impression of what I’m all about. I don’t like real fighting either. It’s scary, and violent, and somebody might get hurt. But I didn’t fight today, Headmaster.’

The Headmaster frowned. ‘You sent the Defence Professor in your place –’

‘Professor Quirrell didn’t do any fighting either,’ Harry said calmly. ‘There wasn’t anyone there strong enough to fight him. What happened today wasn’t fighting, it was winning.’

It was a while then before the old wizard spoke. ‘That may be as it may be,’ the Headmaster said, ‘but all these conflicts must end. I can hear the strain in the air, and with each of these clashes, it rises. All this must end, decisively and soon; you must not stand in the way of its ending.’

The old wizard gestured toward the great oaken door of his office, and Harry departed through it.

It was with some surprise that Harry stepped out from between the huge grey gargoyles which had made way for him, and saw that Quirinus Quirrell was still slumped against the stone of the corridor wall, a thick thread of spittle drooling from his slack mouth onto his Professorial robes, in just the same position he’d occupied when Harry had first gone up into the Headmaster’s office.

Harry waited, but the slumped man didn’t rise up; and after long awkward seconds, Harry began to walk down the corridor again.

‘Mr Potter?’ came a soft call, after Harry had turned two corners; a quiet voice carrying unnaturally through the halls.

When Harry had returned he found Professor Quirrell still slumped against the wall, but the pale eyes now watched him with keen intelligence.

I’m sorry to have tired you out –

It was something that Harry couldn’t say. He’d noticed the correlation between the effort Professor Quirrell expended and the time he had to spend resting. But Harry had reasoned that if the effort was too painful or detrimental, surely Professor Quirrell would just say no. Now Harry was wondering if that reasoning had actually been correct, and if not, how to apologize …

The Defence Professor spoke in a quiet voice, the rest of the body unmoving. ‘How went your meeting with the Headmaster, Mr Potter?’

‘I’m not sure,’ Harry said. ‘Not the way I predicted. He seems to believe the Light should lose a lot more often than I’d consider wise. Plus I’m not sure he understands the difference between trying to fight and trying to win. It explains a lot, actually …’ Harry hadn’t read much about the Wizarding War, but he’d read enough to know that the good guys probably had acquired a pretty accurate picture of who most of the worst Death Eaters were, and hadn’t just owled them all hand grenades over the course of five minutes.

A soft, soft laugh from the pale lips. ‘Dumbledore does not comprehend the enjoyment of winning, just as he does not comprehend the enjoyment of the game. Tell me, Mr Potter. Did you suggest this little plan with the deliberate intention of relieving my tedium?’

‘That was among my many motives,’ Harry said, because some instinct had warned that he couldn’t just say Yes.

‘Do you know,’ the Defence Professor said in soft reflective tones, ‘there are those who have tried to soften my darker moods, and those who have indeed participated in brightening my day, but you are the first person ever to succeed in doing it deliberately?’ The Defence Professor seemed to straighten up from the wall with a peculiar motion which might have included magic as well as muscle; and the Defence Professor began to walk away without a look back in Harry’s direction. Only a single small gesture of one finger indicated that Harry was to follow.

‘I particularly enjoyed that chant you composed for Miss Davis,’ said Professor Quirrell after they had walked a short distance. ‘Though you might have been wiser to consult me in advance, before giving it to her to memorize.’ One hand bestirred itself to within the Defence Professor’s robes and drew forth a wand, which traced a small gesture in the air, after which all the faraway sounds of the castle Hogwarts fell silent. ‘Tell me honestly, Mr Potter, have you somehow acquired a familiarity with the theory of Dark rituals? That is not the same as confessing an intent to cast them; many wizards know the principles.’

‘No …’ Harry said slowly. He had decided some time ago against trying to sneak into the Restricted Section of the Hogwarts library, for much the same reason he’d decided a year earlier not to look up how to make explosives out of common household materials. Harry prided himself on at least having more sense than people thought he did.

‘Oh?’ said Professor Quirrell. The man was walking more normally now, and the lips curved about in a peculiar smile. ‘Why, perhaps you possess a natural talent for the field, then.’

‘Yes, well,’ Harry said wearily. ‘I suppose Dr Seuss also has a natural talent for Dark rituals, because the part about shuffle, duffle, muzzle, muff came from a children’s book called Bartholomew and the Oobleck –’

‘No, not that part,’ said Professor Quirrell. His voice grew a little stronger, took on some of its normal lecturing tone. ‘An ordinary Charm, Mr Potter, can be cast merely by speaking certain words, making precise motions of the wand, expending some of your own strength. Even powerful spells may be invoked in this way, if the magic is efficient as well as efficacious. But with the greatest of magics, speech alone does not suffice to give them structure. You must perform specific actions, make significant choices. Nor is the temporary expenditure of your own strength sufficient to set them in motion; a ritual requires permanent sacrifice. The power of such a greater spell, compared to ordinary Charms, can be like day compared to night. But many rituals – indeed, most – happen to demand at least one sacrifice which might inspire squeamishness. And so the entire field of ritual magic, containing all the furthest and most interesting reaches of wizardry, is widely regarded as Dark. With a few exceptions carved out by tradition, of course.’ Professor Quirrell’s voice took on a sardonic tinge. ‘The Unbreakable Vow is too useful to certain wealthy Houses to be outlawed entirely – even though to bind a man’s will through all his days is indeed a dread and terrible act, more fearsome than many lesser rituals that wizards shun. A cynic might conclude that which rituals are prohibited is not so much a matter of morality, as habit. But I digress …’ Professor Quirrell made a brief coughing sound, a clearing of his throat. ‘The Unbreakable Vow requires three participants and three sacrifices. The one who receives the Unbreakable Vow must be one who could have come to trust the Vower, but chooses instead to demand the Vow from them, and they sacrifice that possibility of trust. The one who makes the Vow must be someone who could have chosen to do what the Vow demands of them, and they sacrifice that capacity for choice. And the third wizard, the binder, permanently sacrifices a small portion of their own magic, to sustain the Vow forever.’

‘Ah,’ Harry said. ‘I’d wondered why that spell wasn’t used all over the place, every time two people have difficulty trusting each other … although … why don’t wizards on their deathbeds charge money to bind Unbreakable Vows, and use that to leave an inheritance for their children –’

‘Because they are stupid,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘There are hundreds of useful rituals which could be performed if men had so much sense; I could name twenty without stopping to draw breath. But in any case, Mr Potter, the thing about such rituals – whether or not you choose to term them Dark – is that they are shaped to be magically efficacious, not to appear impressive when performed. I suppose there is a certain tendency for the more powerful rituals to require more dreadful sacrifices. Even so, the most terrible ritual known to me demands only a rope which has hanged a man and a sword which has slain a woman; and that for a ritual which promised to summon Death itself – though what is truly meant by that I do not know and do not care to discover, since it was also said that the counter-spell to dismiss Death had been lost. The most dread chant I have encountered does not sound even a hundredth as fearsome as the chant you composed for Miss Davis. Those among the bullies who had a passing familiarity with Dark rituals – and I am certain that there were some – must have been terrified beyond the capacity of words to describe. If there existed a true ritual which appeared that impressive, Mr Potter, it would melt the Earth.’

‘Um,’ said Harry.

Professor Quirrell’s lips twisted further. ‘Ah, but the truly amusing thing was this. You see, Mr Potter, the chant of every ritual names that which is to be sacrificed, and that which is to be gained. The chant which you gave to Miss Davis spoke, first, of a darkness beyond darkness, buried beneath the flow of time, which knows the gate, and is the gate. And the second thing spoken of, Mr Potter, was the manifestation of your own presence. And always, in each element of the ritual, first is named that which is sacrificed, and then is said the use commanded of it.’

‘I … see,’ said Harry, as he trod through the halls of Hogwarts after Professor Quirrell, following him toward the Defence Professor’s office. ‘So my chant, the way I wrote it, implies that the Outer God, Yog-Sothoth –’

‘Was permanently sacrificed in a ritual which but briefly manifested your presence,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I suppose we will discover tomorrow whether anyone took that seriously, when we read the newspapers and see whether all the magical nations of the world are banding together in a desperate effort to seal off your incursion into our reality.’

They walked on, as the Defence Professor began chuckling, odd throaty sounds.

The two of them didn’t talk after that until they came to the Defence Professor’s office, and then the man halted with his hand upon the door.

‘It is a very strange thing,’ the Defence Professor said, his voice now soft again, almost inaudible. The man was not looking at Harry, and Harry saw only his back. ‘A very strange thing … There was a time when I would have sacrificed a finger from my wand hand, to work upon the bullies of Hogwarts as we have worked upon them this day. To make them fear me as they now fear you, to have the deference of all the students and the adoration of many, I would have given my finger for that. You have everything now that I wanted then. All that I know of human nature says that I should hate you. And yet I do not. It is a very strange thing.’

It should have been a touching moment, but instead Harry felt a coldness travelling down his spine, as though he were a little fish in the sea, and some vast white shark had just looked him over and decided after a visible hesitation not to eat him.

The man opened the door to Defence Professor’s office, and passed within, and was gone.

Her fellow Slytherins were looking at Daphne like … like they didn’t have the faintest idea of how to look at her.

The Gryffindors were looking at her like they didn’t have the faintest idea of how to look at her.

Showing no fear, Daphne Greengrass strode into the Potions classroom, wrapped in the imperious dignity of a Noble and Most Ancient House. Inside she was feeling much the same way everyone else probably did.

It had been two hours since the What? when the What? had happened and Daphne’s brain was still going: What? What? What?

The classroom was quiet as they all waited for Professor Snape to arrive. Lavender and Parvati sat near a cluster of other Gryffindors, surrounded by silent stares. The two of them were looking over each other’s homework before class started, and nobody else was helping them or talking to them. Even Lavender, who Daphne would have sworn could never be fazed by anything, seemed subdued.

Daphne sat down at her desk, and took Magical Draughts and Potions out of her bag, and began looking over her own homework, doing her very best to act normal. People stared at her, and said nothing –

A gasp went through the whole classroom. Girls and boys flinched back, leaning away from the door like they were stalks of wheat touched by a gust of wind.

In the door stood Tracey Davis, wrapped in a black tattered cloak which had been draped over her Hogwarts uniform.

Tracey walked slowly into the classroom, swaying slightly with each step, looking like she was trying to drift. She sat down at her accustomed desk, which happened to be right next to Daphne’s.

Slowly Tracey’s head turned to stare at Daphne.

‘See?’ the Slytherin girl said in a low, sepulchral tone. ‘I told you I’d get him before she did.’

‘What?’ blurted Daphne, who immediately wished she hadn’t said anything.

‘I got Harry Potter before Granger did.’ Tracey’s voice was still low, but her eyes were gleaming with triumph. ‘See, Daphne, what General Potter wants in a girl isn’t a pretty face or a pretty dress. He wants a girl willing to channel his dread powers, that’s what he wants. Now I’m his – and he’s mine!’

This announcement produced a frozen silence through the whole classroom.

‘Excuse me, Miss Davis,’ said the cultured voice of Draco Malfoy, who seemed unconcerned as he shuffled through his own Potions parchments. The other scion of a Most Ancient House didn’t so much as glance up from his desk, even as everyone else turned to look at him. ‘Did Harry Potter actually tell you that? Using those words?’

‘Well, no …’ Tracey said, and then her eyes flashed angrily. ‘But he’d better take me in, now that I’ve sacrificed my soul to him and everything!’

‘You sacrificed your soul to Harry Potter?’ gasped Millicent. There was a clatter from the other side of the room as Ron Weasley dropped his inkwell.

‘Well, I’m pretty sure I did,’ said Tracey, sounding briefly uncertain before she rallied. ‘I mean, I looked at myself in a mirror and I look paler now, and I can always feel darkness surrounding me, and I was a conduit for his dread powers and everything … Daphne, you also saw my eyes go green, right? I didn’t see it myself but that’s what I heard afterwards.’

There was a pause, broken only by the sounds of Ron Weasley trying to clean up his desk.

‘Daphne?’ said Tracey.

‘I don’t believe it,’ said an angry voice. ‘There’s no way the next Dark Lord would take you to be his bride!’

Slowly, and with considerable disbelief, heads turned to stare at Pansy Parkinson.

‘Hush, you,’ said Tracey, ‘or I’ll …’ The Slytherin girl paused. Then Tracey’s voice went even lower, and she said, ‘Hush, you, or I’ll devour your soul.’

‘You can’t do that,’ said Pansy, in the confident tones of a hen which had worked out a perfectly good pecking order where she was at the top, and wasn’t about to go updating that belief based on mere evidence.

Slowly, like she was trying to float, Tracey got up from her desk. There were more gasps. Daphne felt like she’d been Petrified in place within her chair.

‘Tracey?’ said Lavender in a small voice. ‘Please don’t do all that again. Please?’

Now Pansy was showing definite nervousness as Tracey swayed toward her desk. ‘What d’you think you’re doing?’ Pansy said, not quite managing to sound indignant.

‘I told you,’ Tracey said menacingly. ‘I’m going to devour your soul.’

Tracey bent down over Pansy, who sat frozen at her desk; and, with their lips almost touching, made a loud inhaling noise.

‘There!’ said Tracey as she straightened. ‘I ate your soul.’

‘No you didn’t!’ said Pansy.

‘Did too!’ said Tracey.

There was a very slight pause –

‘Merlin, she did!’ cried Theodore Nott. ‘You look all pale now, and your eyes seem empty!’

‘What?’ screeched Pansy, turning pale. The girl leapt up from her desk and began frantically rummaging through her bookbag. After Pansy drew out a mirror and looked at herself, she turned even paler.

Daphne abandoned all pretence of aristocratic poise and let her head fall to the desk with a dull thud, as she wondered whether going to the same school as all the other important families was really worth going to the same school as the Chaos Legion.

‘Ooh, you’re in trouble now, Pansy,’ said Seamus Finnigan. ‘I don’t know exactly what happens when a Dementor Kisses you, but if Tracey Davis kisses you that’s probably even worse.’

‘I’ve heard about people without souls,’ Dean Thomas said gloomily. ‘They have to dress all in black, and they write awful poetry, and nothing ever makes them happy. They’re all angsty.’

‘I don’t want to be angsty!’ cried Pansy.

‘Too bad,’ said Dean Thomas. ‘You’ve got to be, now that your soul’s gone.’

Pansy turned, and stretched out a begging hand toward Draco Malfoy’s desk. ‘Draco!’ she said pleadingly. ‘Mr Malfoy! Please, make Tracey give me back my soul!’

‘I can’t,’ said Tracey. ‘I ate it.’

‘Make her throw it up!’ yelled Pansy.

The heir of Malfoy had slumped forward, resting his head in both hands, so that nobody could see his face. ‘Why is my life like this?’ said Draco Malfoy.

A wild babble of whispers started up as Tracey returned to her desk, now smiling in satisfaction, while Pansy stood in the midst of the classroom, wringing her hands and tears starting from her eyes –

‘Be. Quiet.’

The soft, lethal voice seemed to fill the whole classroom as Professor Snape stalked in through the door. His face was angrier than Daphne had ever seen it, sending a jolt of genuine fear down her spine. Hastily she looked down at her homework.

‘Sit down, Parkinson,’ the Potions Master hissed, ‘and you, Davis, take off that ridiculous cloak –’

‘Professor Snaaaaaape!’ wailed Pansy Parkinson in tears. ‘Tracey ate my sooouuul!’

In a shadowy clearing the Defence Professor waited, his back leant negligently against the rough grey bark of a towering beech tree as yet bare of leaves in the late March days, so that its trunk and crown seemed like a pale arm reaching up from the ground and exploding into a hand of a thousand fingers. Around the Defence Professor and above him were branches so dense that even in the earliest spring, with few trees so much as budding, you could have hardly seen the sky from the ground. The strands of the wooden net crossed and proliferated so many times that if you were on a broomstick above, searching for someone below, you would have found it easier to follow your ears than your eyes. Nor would it have helped that it was almost dark amid the prohibited woods, the unseen sun almost set, so that only a few glints of fading sunlight illuminated the tops of the tallest trees.

Then came the faintest sound of footsteps, almost inaudible even on the forest ground; the gait of a man accustomed to passing unseen. No twig snapped, nor leaf rustled –

‘Good afternoon,’ said Professor Quirrell. The Defence Professor did not trouble to move his eyes, or his hands from where they rested negligently at his side.

A figure clad in a black cloak shimmered into existence, his head turning to look left and then right. In the figure’s right hand, gripped low, was a wand of wood so grey it was almost silver.

‘I do not know why you wished to meet here of all places,’ said Severus Snape, his voice cool.

‘Oh,’ Professor Quirrell said idly, as though the whole matter was of the least importance, ‘I thought you would prefer privacy. The walls of Hogwarts have ears, and you would not wish the Headmaster to know of your role in yesterday’s affair, would you?’

The March chill seemed to grow deeper, the temperature further fall. ‘I don’t know what you’re talking about,’ the Potions Master said icily.

‘You know perfectly well what we’re talking about,’ said Professor Quirrell in an amused voice. ‘Really, my good Professor, you should not meddle in the affairs of idiots unless you are ready to defend yourself upon the instant from all their violence.’ (The Defence Professor’s hands still lay relaxed and open at his side.) ‘And yet none of those idiots seem to remember the sight of you falling, nor do the young ladies recall your presence. Which raises the fascinating question of why you would go to the extraordinary length, I dare say the desperate length, of casting fifty-two Memory Charms.’ Professor Quirrell tilted his head. ‘Would you fear so much the opinions of mere students? I think not. Would you dread the matter becoming known to your good friend, Lord Malfoy? But those fools, upon the very spot, invented a quite satisfactory excuse for your presence. No, there is only one person who holds so much power over you, and who would be most perturbed to find you executing any plot without his knowledge. Your true and hidden master, Albus Dumbledore.’

‘What?’ hissed the Potions Master, the anger plain upon his face.

‘But now, it seems, you are moving on your own; and so I find myself most intrigued as to what you could possibly be doing, and why.’ The Defence Professor regarded the black-clad silhouette of the Potions Master with the scrutiny a man might give an exceptionally interesting bug, even if it was still ultimately just a bug.

‘I am no servant of Dumbledore’s,’ the Potions Master said coldly.

‘Really? What astonishing news.’ The Defence Professor smiled slightly. ‘Do tell me all about it.’

There was a long pause. From some tree an owl hooted, the sound huge in the silence; neither man startled or flinched.

‘You don’t want me as your enemy, Quirrell,’ Severus Snape said, his voice very soft.

‘I don’t?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘How would you know?’

‘On the other hand,’ the Potions Master continued, voice still soft, ‘my friends enjoy many advantages.’

The man leaning against the grey bark raised his eyebrows. ‘Such as?’

‘There is much that I know of this school,’ said the Potions Master. ‘Things you might not think I knew.’

There was an expectant pause.

‘How incredibly fascinating,’ said Professor Quirrell. The man was examining his fingernails with a bored look. ‘Do go on.’

‘I know you have been … investigating … the third-floor corridor –’

‘You know nothing of the sort.’ The man’s back straightened against the wood. ‘Do not bluff against me, Severus Snape; I find it annoying, and you are in no position to annoy me. A single glance would tell any competent wizard that the Headmaster has laced that corridor with a ridiculous quantity of wards and webs, triggers and tripsigns. And more: there are Charms laid there of ancient power, magical constructs of which I have heard not even rumours, techniques that must have been disgorged from the hoarded lore of Flamel himself. Even He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named would have had trouble passing those without notice.’ Professor Quirrell tapped a thoughtful finger on his cheek. ‘And for the actual lock, a Colloportus laid on an ordinary doorknob, cast so weakly that it could not have kept out Miss Granger on the day she entered Hogwarts. Never before in my existence have I encountered such a blatant trap.’ Now the Defence Professor narrowed his eyes. ‘I know of no one left in the world against whom such fantastic feats of detection would serve any useful purpose. If there is some wizard possessed of ancient lore, of whom I know nothing, against whom this trap is set – you may trade that information for as much silence as you like, my dear Professor, and a good serving of my favour left over afterwards.’

You could have sworn that Professor Quirrell was watching Severus Snape with keen interest. Not the faintest trace of a smile crossed the man’s lips.

There was another long silence in the clearing.

‘I do not know who Dumbledore fears,’ Snape said. ‘But I know what bait he has set out, and somewhat of how it is truly guarded –’

‘As to that,’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding bored again, ‘I stole it months ago, and left a fake in its place. But thank you kindly for asking.’

‘You’re lying,’ said Severus Snape after a pause.

‘Yes, I am.’ Professor Quirrell leaned back against the grey wood again, his eyes drifting up to the dense net of branches, the falling night scarcely visible between the complex crossings. ‘I simply wished to learn whether you would challenge me on it, since you are pretending to know so little.’ The Defence Professor smiled to himself.

The Potions Master looked like he was about to choke on his own fury. ‘What do you want?’

‘Nothing, really,’ said the Defence Professor, continuing to gaze at the forest ceiling. ‘I was only curious. I suppose I shall just watch and see where your plotting goes, and meanwhile I will say nothing to the Headmaster – so long as you are willing to do me a favour now and then, of course.’ A dry smile crossed the face. ‘You are dismissed for now, Severus Snape. Though I wouldn’t mind having another little chat soon, if you’re willing to speak with me honestly of where your loyalties lie. And I do mean honestly, not the false faces you’ve shown today. You might find you have more allies than you thought. Take some time to think it over, my friend.’

A rainbow hemisphere, a dome of solid force with little chromaticity of its own which sent back the infringing light in splintered reflections, iridescent in many colours, as it fractured the shine of the many-splendoured chandeliers of the Slytherin common room.

Sheltered beneath the rainbow hemisphere, the terrified face of a young witch who had never fought bullies, who had not joined any of Professor Quirrell’s armies, who was getting Acceptable marks at best in her Defence class, who could not have cast a Prismatic Barrier even to save her own life.

‘Oh, stop it,’ said Draco Malfoy, making his voice sound bored despite the sweat that had broken out underneath his robes, as he kept his wand pointed at the barrier that was sheltering Millicent Bulstrode.

He couldn’t remember making the decision, there’d just been the two older boys about to hex Millicent, the common room silently staring, and then Draco’s hand had just drawn his wand and cast the barrier, leaving his heart to pump itself full of shocked adrenaline while his poor sad brain frantically racked itself for explanations –

The two older boys were straightening up from where they’d been looming over Millicent, turning to Draco, looking at him with a mixture of shock and anger. Gregory and Vincent beside him had already drawn their own wands, but weren’t pointing them. All three of them together couldn’t have won, anyway.

But the older boys wouldn’t hex him. Nobody could possibly be stupid enough to hex the next Lord Malfoy.

It wasn’t fear of being hexed that was making Draco sweat beneath his robes, as he desperately hoped the beads of water weren’t visible on his forehead.

Draco was sweating because of the dawning and sickening certainty that even if he got away with this now, if he kept down this path, there would come a time when it would all come crashing down; and then he might not be the next Lord Malfoy any more.

‘Mr Malfoy,’ said the oldest-looking boy. ‘Why are you protecting her?’

‘So you’ve located the mistress of the conspiracy,’ Draco said with a Number Two Sneer, ‘and it’s, let me get this straight now, a first-year girl named Millicent Bulstrode. She’s just a conduit, you nitwit!’

‘So?’ demanded the older boy. ‘She still helped them!’

Draco lifted his wand and the Prismatic Sphere winked out. Still talking in a bored voice, Draco said, ‘Did you know what you were doing, Miss Bulstrode?’

‘N-no,’ Millicent stammered from where she was still sitting at her desk.

‘Did you know where the Slytherin messages you were passing on were going to?’

‘No!’ said Millicent.

‘Thank you,’ Draco said. ‘All of you please leave her alone, she’s just a pawn. Miss Bulstrode, you may consider the favour you did me in February to have been repaid.’ And Draco turned back to his Potions homework, hoping to Merlin and back again that Millicent didn’t say anything incredibly stupid like What favour? –

‘Then why,’ a voice said clearly from across the room, ‘did those witches go where a note from Millicent told them to go?’

Sweating even more, Draco lifted his head again to look at where Randolph Lee had spoken. ‘What did the fake note say exactly?’ said Draco. ‘Was it, “I command you to go forth in the name of the Dark Lady Bulstrode” or “Please meet me here, sincerely Millicent?”’

Randolph Lee opened his mouth, hesitated for a fractional second –

‘I thought so,’ said Draco. ‘That wasn’t a very good test, Mr Lee, it – it can –’ A frantic, nerve-racking moment while he figured out how to say it without using Harry-words like false positive. ‘It can get the witches to go there if any of them is just friends with Millicent.’

As though the matter had been entirely settled, Draco looked down again at his Potions homework, ignoring (except for the feeling of sick dread in his stomach) the whispers from around the room.

It was only out of the corner of his eye that he caught Gregory staring at him.

Draco’s eyes rested on his Astronomy homework, but he couldn’t make his mind focus there. If you were trying not to think about things Harry Potter had said, pretty much the worst possible thing you could do was look at your textbook’s pictures of the night sky, and try to remember what you weren’t supposed to know about how the planets wandered. Astronomy, a noble and prestigious art, a sign of learning and knowledge; only Muggles possessed secret modern artifacts which could do it a million billion times better using methods that Harry had tried to explain and which Draco still couldn’t begin to understand except that apparently it didn’t even take magic to make things do Arithmancy.

Draco looked at the pictures of constellations, and wondered if it was like this in the other Houses, if people were always threatening each other in Ravenclaw.

Harry Potter had told him once that soldiers on a battlefield didn’t really fight for their country. Patriotism might get them to the battlefield in the first place, but once they were there, they fought to protect each other, the friends they’d trained with who were right in front of them. And Harry had observed, and Draco had known that it was true, that you couldn’t use loyalty to a leader to power a Patronus Charm, it wasn’t quite the right kind of warm and happy thought. But thinking of protecting someone beside you –

That, Harry Potter had said thoughtfully, was probably why the Death Eaters had fallen apart the moment the Dark Lord had departed. They hadn’t been warm enough to each other.

You could recruit a group that included Bellatrix Black and Amycus Carrow alongside Lord Malfoy and Mr Macnair, and keep them in line with the Cruciatus Curse. But the instant the master of the Dark Mark was gone, you didn’t have an army any more, you had a circle of acquaintances. That was why Father had failed. It hadn’t even really been his fault. There’d been nothing Father could have done, after inheriting Death Eaters who weren’t really friends with each other.

And even though it was Slytherin House he was supposed to defend – Slytherin House which he and Harry had formed a pact to save – sometimes Draco couldn’t help but think that it was just less wearisome when he was leading army practises. When he was working with students from the other three Houses that weren’t Slytherin. Once you saw and named the problems, you couldn’t stop seeing them, it just got more annoying every day.

‘Mr Malfoy?’ said the voice of Gregory Goyle, from where he was lying on the floor beside Draco’s desk, in the small but private bedroom; Gregory was doing his Transfiguration homework, on which he often needed help.

Any distraction was welcome at this point. ‘Yes?’ said Draco.

‘You weren’t really plotting against Granger at all,’ said Gregory. ‘Were you?’

The sensation spreading through Draco’s stomach felt just like Gregory’s voice sounded, sickened and afraid.

‘You actually were helping Granger, that day you picked her up off the floor,’ said Gregory. ‘And before, that time you kept her from falling off the roof. You helped a mudblood –’

‘Yeah, right,’ said Draco sarcastically, without the slightest hesitation or delay, looking back down at his Astronomy homework like he wasn’t the least bit nervous. It was all happening the way Draco had feared it would, but at least that meant he’d played this conversation in his head over and over, coming up with the right opening gambit. ‘Come on, Gregory, you’ve duelled General Granger, you know how strong her spells are. Like a real Muggle-spawn is going to be more powerful than you, more powerful than Theodore, more powerful than every single pureblood in our whole school year except me? Don’t you actually believe in anything Father says? She’s adopted. Her parents died in the war and someone stuck her with a couple of Muggles to hide her. No way is General Granger a real mudblood.’

A slow pulse of silence through Draco’s bedroom. Draco wanted to know, needed to know what look was on Gregory’s face. But he couldn’t look up from his desk, not yet, not until Gregory spoke first.

And then –

‘Is that what Harry Potter said to you?’ said Gregory.

The voice wavered, and broke. When Draco looked up from his homework, he saw that tears were leaking out of Gregory’s eyes.

Apparently that hadn’t worked.

‘I don’t know what to do,’ Gregory said in a whisper. ‘I don’t know what to do now, Mr Malfoy. Your father isn’t – when he finds out – he’s not going to like it, Mr Malfoy!’

It’s not your job to decide what Father will like, Goyle –

Draco could hear the words in his head; they sounded in Father’s voice, with the same sternness. It was the sort of thing Father had told him to say, if Vincent or Gregory ever questioned him; and if that didn’t work he was to hex them. They were not equal friends, Father had said, and he wasn’t ever to forget it. Draco was in charge, they were his servants, and if Draco couldn’t keep it that way then he wasn’t fit to inherit House Malfoy …

‘It’s all right, Gregory,’ Draco said, as gently as he could. ‘All you’ve got to do is worry about protecting me. Nobody’s going to blame you for following my orders, not my father, not yours.’ Putting all the warmth he could into his voice, like trying to cast a Patronus Charm. ‘And anyway, the next war isn’t going to be the same as the last one. House Malfoy was around long before the Dark Lord, and not every Lord Malfoy does the same thing. Father knows that.’

‘Does he?’ said Gregory in trembling voice. ‘Does he really?’

Draco nodded. ‘Professor Quirrell knows it too,’ said Draco. ‘That’s what the armies are about. The Defence Professor’s right, when the next war comes, Father won’t be able to unite the whole country, they’ll remember the last war. But anyone who’s fought in Professor Quirrell’s armies will remember who the strongest generals were, they’ll know who’s worthy to lead them. They’ll proclaim Harry Potter their Lord, and I’ll be his right hand, and House Malfoy will come out on top, like always. People might even turn to me, if Potter isn’t there, so long as they think I’m trustworthy. That’s what I’m setting up now. Father will understand.’

Gregory reached up and wiped his eyes, looking down again at his Transfiguration homework. ‘Okay,’ Gregory said in a shaky voice. ‘If you say so, Mr Malfoy.’

Draco nodded again, ignoring the hollow feeling inside himself at the lies he’d just told his friend, and turned back to the stars.

Being invisible should’ve been more interesting than this, the corridors of Hogwarts should have been outlined in strange colours or something. But actually, Hermione thought, being under Harry’s invisibility cloak was exactly like not being under an invisibility cloak, except for the cloak part. When you pulled the veil of soft black cloth down from the hood and over your face, you couldn’t even see it stretching in front of you, and afterwards it didn’t seem to impede your breathing. And the world looked just the same, except that when you walked past things of metal, you didn’t see any small reflections of yourself. Portraits never looked at you, only did whatever strange things they did when they were alone. Hermione hadn’t tried walking past a mirror yet, she wasn’t sure she wanted to. Most of all, there was no you any more as you walked around, no hands, no feet, just a changing point of view. It was an unnerving feeling, not so much of being invisible as of not existing.

Harry hadn’t questioned her at all, she’d just got out the word invisibility and then Harry was drawing his invisibility cloak from his pouch. She hadn’t even been given a chance to explain about her extremely secret meeting with Daphne and Millicent Bulstrode, or that she thought it would help protect the other girls, Harry had just handed over what was probably a Deathly Hallow. If you were fair, and she did try to be fair, she had to admit that sometimes Harry could be a true, true friend.

The secret meeting itself had been a total failure.

Millicent had claimed to be a seer.

Hermione had carefully explained to Millicent and Daphne at considerable length that this could not possibly be true.

She and Harry had looked up Divination early on in their research; Harry had insisted that they read everything they could find about prophecies that wasn’t in the Restricted Section. As Harry had observed, it would save a lot of effort if they could just get a seer to prophesy everything they would figure out thirty-five years later. (Or to put it in Harry’s terms, any means of obtaining information transmitted from the distant future was potentially an instant global victory condition.)

But, as Hermione had explained to Millicent, prophesying wasn’t controllable, there was no way to ask for a prophecy about anything in particular. Instead (the books had said) there was a sort of pressure that built up in Time, when some huge event was trying to happen, or stop itself from happening. And seers were like weak points that let out the pressure, when the right listener was nearby. So prophecies were only about big, important things, because only that generated enough pressure; and you almost never got more than one seer saying the same thing, because afterwards the pressure was gone. And, as Hermione had further explained to Millicent, the seers themselves didn’t remember their prophecies, because the message wasn’t for them. And the messages would come out in riddles, and only someone who heard the prophecy in the seer’s original voice would hear all the meaning that was in the riddle. There was no possible way that Millicent could just give out a prophecy any time she wanted, about school bullies, and then remember it, and if she had it would’ve come out as the skeleton is the key and not Susan Bones has to be there.

Millicent had been looking rather frightened at this point, so Hermione had relaxed her fists where they’d been jammed on her hips, calmed herself down, and stated carefully that she was glad Millicent had helped them, but they had sometimes walked into traps following what Millicent said, and so Hermione really did want to know where the messages had actually come from.

And Millicent had said in a small voice:

But, but she told me that she was a seer …

Hermione had told Daphne not to press it, after Millicent had refused to give up her source. It wasn’t just that Hermione had felt awful about the scared look on Millicent’s face. It was that Hermione had a strong feeling that if they did find the person who’d been telling Millicent things, why, they would turn out to just be finding envelopes under their pillow in the morning.

She was getting that same despairing feeling she’d had in the battle before Christmas, looking at Zabini’s charts with all the coloured lines and boxes and … and she had only just now realized what it meant that Zabini had been the one showing her that chart.

Even for a Ravenclaw, she felt, there was such a thing as having your life get overly complicated.

Hermione began ascending a short spiral of yellow marble steps protruding from a central spine, a poorly-kept ‘secret’ staircase that was actually one of the fastest ways from the Slytherin dungeons to the Ravenclaw tower, but which only witches could traverse. (Why girls in particular needed a quick way to move between Ravenclaw and Slytherin was something Hermione found a bit puzzling.) At the top of the staircase, now that she was away from Slytherin, Hermione stopped and took off Harry’s invisibility cloak.

After her pouch had swallowed the cloak, Hermione turned right and started to walk down a short passageway, now automatically keeping an eye out in all directions without really thinking about it, and her constantly-scanning eyes glanced into a shadowy alcove –

(fleeting disorientation)

– and then a rush of shock and fear hit her like a Stunning Hex over her whole body, she found that without any thought or any conscious decision her wand had leaped into her hand and was already pointed at …

… a black cloak so wide and billowing that it was impossible to determine whether the figure beneath was male or female, and atop the cloak a broad-brimmed black hat; and a black mist seemed to gather beneath it and obscure the face of whoever or whatever might lie beneath.

‘Hello again, Hermione,’ whispered a sibilant voice from beneath the black hat, from behind the black mist.

Hermione’s heart was already pounding hugely inside her chest, her witch’s robes felt already sweat-dampened against her skin, there was a taste of fear already in her mouth; she didn’t know why she was so suddenly filled up with adrenaline but her hand gripped harder on her wand. ‘Who are you?’ Hermione demanded.

The hat tilted slightly; the whispering voice, when it came forth from the black mist, sounded dry as dust. ‘The last ally,’ spoke the sibilant whisper. ‘The one who finally answers, when no other will answer you. I am perhaps the only true friend you have in all Hogwarts, Hermione. For you have now seen how the others stayed silent when you were in need –’

‘What’s your name?’

The black cloak rotated slightly, back and forth, it didn’t look like shoulders shrugging, but it conveyed a shrug. ‘That is the riddle, young Ravenclaw. Until you solve it, you may call me whatever you wish.’

She could feel her palm already sweaty and was thankful for the spiral grooves on her wand that helped her hand keep a steady grip on the wood. ‘Well, Mister Incredibly Suspicious Person,’ Hermione said, ‘what do you want with me?’

‘That is the wrong question,’ came the whisper from black mist. ‘You should ask, rather, what I can offer you.’

‘No,’ the young girl said quite steadily, ‘I don’t think I should be asking that, actually.’

A high-pitched chuckle from behind the black mist. ‘Not power,’ whispered the voice, ‘not wealth, you care little for such things, do you, young Ravenclaw? Knowledge. That is what I possess. I know what is unfolding within this school, all the hidden plans and players, the answers of the riddle. I know the true reason for the coldness you see in Harry Potter’s eyes. I know the true nature of Professor Quirrell’s mysterious illness. I know who Dumbledore truly fears.’

‘Good for you,’ said Hermione Granger. ‘But do you know how many licks it takes to get to the Tootsie Roll centre of a Tootsie Pop?’

The black mist seemed to darken slightly, the voice sounded lower when it spoke, disappointed. ‘So you are not even curious, young Ravenclaw, about the truths behind the lies?’

‘One hundred and eighty-seven,’ she said. ‘I tried it once and that’s how many it came out to.’ Her hand was almost slipping on her wand, there was a sense of fatigue in her fingers like she’d been holding the wand for hours instead of minutes –

The voice hissed, ‘Professor Snape is a hidden Death Eater.’

Hermione almost dropped her wand.

‘Ah,’ the voice whispered in satisfaction. ‘I thought that might interest you. So, Hermione. Is there anything else you would like to know about your enemies, or those you call friends?’

She stared up at the black mist that topped the towering black cloak, frantically trying to order her thoughts. Professor Snape was a Death Eater? Who would tell her something like that, why, what was going on? ‘That’s –’ Hermione said. Her voice was quavering. ‘That’s extremely serious business, if it’s really true. Why are you telling something like that to me, and not to Headmaster Dumbledore?’

‘Dumbledore did nothing to stop Snape,’ the black mist whispered. ‘You saw it, Hermione. The rot at Hogwarts begins at the top. Everything that is wrong with this school, it all begins with the mad Headmaster. You alone dared to criticise him for it – and therefore I speak to you.’

‘And have you also spoken to Harry Potter, then?’ Hermione said, keeping her voice as even as she could. If this was his helpful ghost –

The black mist darkened and lightened, like a shake of the head. ‘I am frightened of Harry Potter,’ it whispered. ‘Of the coldness in his eyes, of the darkness that grows behind them. Harry Potter is a killer, and anyone who is an obstacle to him will die. Even you, Hermione Granger, if you dare truly oppose him, the darkness behind his eyes will reach out and destroy you. This I know.’

‘Then you don’t know half of what you pretend to know,’ Hermione said, her voice a little firmer. ‘I’m scared of Harry too. But not because of what he might ever do to me. I’m scared of what he might do to protect me –’

‘Wrong.’ The whisper was flat, and hard, as if to brook no possibility of denial. ‘Harry Potter will turn against you in time, Hermione, when the darkness takes him fully. He will not shed a tear, he will not even notice, on the day his footsteps finally crush you underneath.’

‘Double wrong!’ she said back in a rising voice, even though there were chills going down her spine. One of Harry’s phrases came to her. ‘Just what do you think you know, and how do you think you know it, anyway?’

‘Time –’ The voice seemed to catch itself. ‘Time enough for that later. For now, for today, indeed Harry Potter is not your enemy. And yet you are in gravest danger.’

‘I can believe that,’ said Hermione Granger. She desperately wanted to shift her wand to her other hand, she felt like she needed to grab her right arm just to keep it up, her head ached like she’d been staring at the black mist for days; she didn’t know why she’d tired so quickly.

‘Lucius Malfoy has taken notice of you, Hermione.’ The whisper had risen, departed from its tonelessness, taken on a note of audible concern. ‘You have humiliated Slytherin House, you have defeated his son in battle. Even before then you were an embarrassment to all who stand with the Death Eaters; for you are a Muggleborn and yet you possess a power of wizardry greater than any pureblood. And now you are becoming known, the eyes of the world on you. Lucius Malfoy seeks to crush you, Hermione, to hurt you and perhaps even kill you, and he has the means to do it!’ The whisper had grown urgent.

There was a pause.

‘Is that all?’ Hermione said. If she was ex-Colonel Zabini or Harry Potter, she’d probably be asking clever questions to gather more information; but her mind felt slow and fatigued. She really needed to get out of here and go lie down for a while.

‘You don’t believe me,’ the whisper said, softer and sadder now. ‘Why not, Hermione? I am trying to help you.’

Hermione took a step backward, away from the shadowy alcove.

‘Why not, Hermione?’ demanded the voice, rising to a hiss. ‘You owe me that much! Tell me, and then –’ The voice caught, and came back quieter. ‘And then you can go, I suppose. Only tell me – why –’

Maybe she shouldn’t’ve answered; maybe she should’ve just turned and fled, or better yet, cast a Prismatic Wall first and then screamed at the top of her lungs as she ran; but it was the note of real pain in the voice that caught her, and so she answered.

‘Because you look incredibly dark and scary and suspicious,’ Hermione said, keeping her voice polite, as her wand stayed level on the towering black cloak and the faceless black mist.

‘That’s all?’ whispered the voice incredulously. Sadness seemed to infuse it. ‘I hoped for better from you, Hermione. Surely such a Ravenclaw as you, the most intelligent Ravenclaw to grace Hogwarts in a generation, knows that appearances can be misleading.’

‘Oh, I know it,’ said Hermione. She took another step back, her tired fingers tightening on the wand. ‘But the thing that people forget sometimes, is that even though appearances can be misleading, they’re usually not.’

There was a pause.

‘You are the clever one,’ said the voice, and the black mist evaporated away, no longer obscuring; she saw the face beneath, and recognition sent a jolt of terrified adrenaline bursting through her –

(fleeting disorientation)

– and then a rush of shock and fear hit her like a Stunning Hex over her whole body, she found that without any thought or any conscious decision her wand had leaped into her hand and was already pointed at …

… a shining lady, her long white dress billowing about her as though in invisible winds; neither her hands nor her feet were visible, her face hidden beneath a white veil; and she was glowing all over, not like a ghost, not transparent, just surrounded by soft white light.

Hermione stared open-mouthed at the gentle sight, wondering why her heart was already hammering, and why she felt so scared.

‘Hello again, Hermione,’ the kindly whisper emanated from the white glow behind the veil. ‘I’ve been sent to help you, so please don’t be afraid. I am your servant in all things; for you, my Lady, are the bearer of a most marvellous destiny –’

…

…

…

That night at dinnertime, Susan Bones came to Harry Potter and told him that she thought Draco Malfoy was going to carry out his plot against Hermione very soon. She was warning all the members of S.P.H.E.W., and she’d warned Professor Sprout, and she’d warned Professor Flitwick, and she was going to send a letter to her Aunt tonight, and now she was warning Harry Potter, too. Only they couldn’t quite talk about it with Padma – Susan said, looking very serious – because Padma was feeling torn between her loyalty to Hermione and her loyalty to her General.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres, who was at this point feeling more frustrated with the entire situation than anything really productive, snapped at her that yes, he knew something had to be done.

After Susan Bones left, Harry looked over at the other end of the Ravenclaw table, where Hermione had sat down away from him or Padma or Anthony or any of her other friends.

But Hermione didn’t look like she was in a mood where somebody going over and bothering her would be taken very well.

Later, looking backward, Harry would think of how, in his SF and fantasy novels, people always made their big, important choices for big, important reasons. Hari Seldon had created his Foundation to rebuild the ashes of the Galactic Empire, not because he would look more important if he could be in charge of his own research group. Raistlin Majere had severed ties with his brother because he wanted to become a god, not because he was incompetent at personal relationships and unwilling to ask for advice on how to do better. Frodo Baggins had taken the Ring because he was a hero who wanted to save Middle-Earth, not because it would’ve been too awkward not to. If anyone ever wrote a true history of the world – not that anyone ever could or would – probably 97% of all the key moments of Fate would turn out to be constructed of lies and tissue paper and trivial little thoughts that somebody could’ve just as easily thought differently.

Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres looked at Hermione Granger, where she’d sat down at the other end of the table, and felt a sense of reluctance to bother her when she looked like she was already in a bad mood.

So then Harry thought that it probably made more sense to talk to Draco Malfoy first, just so that he could absolutely positively definitely assure Hermione that Draco really wasn’t plotting against her.

And later on after dinner, when Harry went down to the Slytherin basement and was told by Vincent that the boss ain’t to be disturbed … then Harry thought that maybe he should see if Hermione would talk to him right away. That he should just get started on unravelling the whole mess before it ravelled any further. Harry wondered if he might just be procrastinating, if his mind had just found a clever excuse to put off something unenjoyable-but-necessary.

He actually thought that.

And then Harry James Potter-Evans-Verres decided that he’d just talk to Draco Malfoy the next morning instead, after Sunday breakfast, and then talk to Hermione.

Human beings did that sort of thing all the time.

It was Sunday morning, on the 5th of April, 1992, and the simulated sky above the Great Hall of Hogwarts showed great torrents of rain pouring down in such density that the lightning flashes were diminished and scattered into small pulses of white light that sometimes transformed the House tables, paling their faces and making all the students appear briefly to be ghosts.

Harry sat at the Ravenclaw table, wearily eating a waffle, waiting for Draco to make an appearance so that he could get started on sorting this whole thing out. There was a Quibbler being passed around which had somehow ended up with Hannah and Daphne on the front page, but it hadn’t reached his place yet.

A few minutes later Harry finished eating his waffle, and then looked around again to see if Draco had arrived yet for breakfast at the Slytherin table.

It was odd.

Draco Malfoy was almost never late.

Since Harry was looking in the direction of the Slytherin table, he didn’t see Hermione Granger entering through the huge doors of the Great Hall. Thus he was rather startled when he turned back and discovered Hermione sitting down directly beside him at the Ravenclaw table, just as if she hadn’t not-done that for more than a week.

‘Hi, Harry,’ Hermione said, her voice sounding almost exactly normal. She started to put toast on her plate and a selection of healthy fruits and vegetables. ‘How are you?’

‘Within one standard deviation of my own peculiar little average,’ Harry automatically replied. ‘How are you doing? Did you sleep okay?’

There were dark bags under Hermione Granger’s eyes.

‘Why, yes, I’m fine,’ said Hermione Granger.

‘Um,’ Harry said. He took a slice of pie onto his plate (as his brain was occupied with other things, Harry’s hand simply took the tastiest thing within range, without evaluating complex concepts like whether he was ready to eat dessert). ‘Um, Hermione, I’m going to need to talk to you later today, is that okay?’

‘Sure,’ said Hermione. ‘Why wouldn’t it be?’

‘Because –’ Harry said. ‘I mean – you and I haven’t – for the last few days –’

Shut up, suggested an internal part of Harry that seemed to have been recently allocated for governing Hermione-related issues.

Hermione Granger didn’t look like she was paying much attention to him in any case. She just stared down at her plate, and then, after about ten seconds of awkward silence, began to eat her tomato slices, one after another, without pause.

Harry looked away from her and began to eat a slice of pie which, he discovered, had somehow materialized on his plate.

‘So!’ Hermione Granger suddenly said after she’d polished off most of her plate in silence. ‘Anything happening today?’

‘Um …’ Harry said. He looked around frantically, as though to find something-happening that he could use as conversational fodder.

And so Harry was one of the first to see it, and wordlessly point, although the sudden swell of whispers that swept through the Great Hall showed that a number of other people had seen it too.

The distinctive crimson tinge of the robes would have been recognizable anywhere, but it still took Harry’s brain a few moments to place the faces. An Asianish-looking man, solemn, and today looking rather grim. A man with a piercing gaze that swept over the room, his long black hair waving behind him in a ponytail. A man thin and pale and unshaven, with a face so blank that it was like stone. It took Harry a few moment to place the faces, and remember the names, from that long-ago day in January when the Dementor had come to Hogwarts: Komodo, Butnaru, Goryanof.

‘An Auror trio?’ Hermione said in a strange bright voice. ‘Why, I wonder what they’d be doing here.’

Dumbledore was in their company as well, looking as worried as Harry had ever seen him; and after a moment’s pause while the old wizard’s eyes scanned the Great Hall and the students whispering over their breakfasts, he pointed –

– straight at Harry.

‘Oh, now what,’ Harry said under his breath. His inward thoughts were a lot more panicked than that, as he wondered frantically if anyone had connected him to the Azkaban breakout somehow. He looked at the Head Table, trying to make the glance casual, and realized that Professor Quirrell was nowhere to be seen, this morning –

The Aurors swept toward him with swift strides, Auror Goryanof approaching from the other side of the Ravenclaw table as though to block any escape in that direction, Auror Komodo and Auror Butnaru approaching from Harry’s side, the Headmaster following straight on Komodo’s heels.

All conversation everywhere had ground to utter silence.

The Aurors reached Harry’s place at the table, surrounding him from three angles.

‘Yes?’ Harry said, as normally as he could. ‘What is it?’

‘Hermione Granger,’ Auror Komodo said in a toneless voice, ‘you are under arrest for the attempted murder of Draco Malfoy.’

The words dropped into Harry’s consciousness and shattered his thoughts into a hundred shards of incredulity, the shock of adrenaline running into so much confusion that –

‘She –’ Harry said. ‘She – she wouldn’t – What?’

The Aurors weren’t paying any attention to him. Komodo spoke again, still in that colourless voice. ‘Mr Malfoy has regained consciousness in St. Mungo’s and named you, Hermione Granger, as his assaulter. He has repeated these accusations under two drops of Veritaserum. The Blood-Cooling Charm you cast upon Mr Malfoy would have killed him if he had not been found and treated, and it must be presumed known to you that this was a fatal curse. I therefore arrest you upon the serious charge of attempted murder and you will be taken into Ministry custody to be interrogated under three drops of Veritaserum –’

‘Are you mad?’ the words burst out of Harry’s mouth, as he shoved himself up from the Ravenclaw table, an instant before Auror Butnaru’s hand clamped down hard upon his shoulder. Harry ignored it. ‘That’s Hermione Granger you’re trying to arrest, the nicest girl in Ravenclaw, she helps Hufflepuffs with their homework, she’d die before she tried to kill anyone –’

Hermione Granger’s face had crumpled. ‘I did it,’ she whispered in a tiny voice. ‘It was me.’

Another huge rock fell on Harry’s thoughts and crushed their fragile order, bursting fragments of comprehension into dust.

Dumbledore’s face seemed to have aged decades over the course of seconds. ‘Why, Miss Granger?’ Dumbledore said, his own voice barely above a whisper. ‘Why would you do such a thing?’

‘I’m,’ Hermione said, ‘I’m, I’m – sorry – I don’t know why I –’ She seemed to collapse in on herself, her voice was formed of nothing but sobs, and the only words that could be made out were, ‘I thought – killed him – sorry –’

And Harry should have said something, should have done something, should have jumped up out of his seat and stunned all three Aurors and then gone on to some incredibly clever next move, but the twice-shattered fragments of his thought processes could yield no output. Butnaru’s hand pushed Harry gently but firmly back into his seat and Harry found himself stuck there like he’d been glued, he tried to grab his wand for a Finite and it wouldn’t come out of his pocket, the three Aurors and Dumbledore escorted Hermione out of the Great Hall amid a rising storm of outcries and the doors began to swing shut behind them – nothing made sense, it was surreal beyond all reckoning, like he’d been transported into an alternate universe, and then Harry’s mind flashed back to another day of confusion and in a moment of desperate inspiration he finally realized what the Weasley twins had done to Rita Skeeter, and his voice rose in a scream, ‘Hermione you didn’t do it you’ve been false-memory-charmed!’

But the doors had already shut.

Even as Harry Potter left the room for his own investigations, Severus spun on his heel and strode swiftly toward the jar of Floo powder, his cloak rising behind him with his speed. ‘I’ll get some raw Polyjuice, add the hair, and go. Headmaster, will you stand by to –’

‘Albus,’ Minerva said, surprised at how steady her own voice was, ‘did you leave those notes under Mr Potter’s pillow?’

Severus’s hand halted an instant before casting Floo powder into the fire.

Dumbledore nodded to her, though the accompanying smile seemed a bit hollow. ‘You know me far too well, my dear.’

‘And I suppose the portkey goes to a friendly home where Mr Potter would be kept safe and sound until you arrived to pick him up and return him to Hogwarts?’ Her voice tight – it was sensible, she could not deny it was sensible, but somehow it seemed a little cruel.

‘It would depend on the circumstances,’ the old wizard said quietly. ‘If Harry had gone so far – I might have let him make good his escape, for a time. Better to know where he was going, and ensure it was somewhere safe, with friends –’

‘And to think,’ said Professor McGonagall, ‘that I had thought to reprimand Mr Potter for not telling us about this important matter! Upbraid him for not having the sense to trust us!’ Her voice had risen in volume. ‘I shall skip that lecture, I suppose!’

Severus was gazing at the Headmaster with narrowed eyes. ‘And the notes to Miss Granger –’

‘The Defence Professor, very likely,’ the old wizard said. ‘Still – that is only a guess.’

‘I shall go and look for them,’ Severus said. ‘And then, I suppose, start looking for You-Know-Who.’ A frown crossed the Potions Master’s face. ‘A task which I haven’t the faintest idea of where to start. Do you know of any magics to find a soul, Headmaster?’

The Divination classroom was lit by the dim red light of a hundred small fires where burned a hundred kinds of incense, so that if you were to ask for one word describing what the room looked like, the answer would be smoke. (Assuming you bothered to look at anything, when your nose was threatening to overload and die.) If your gaze could pierce those dank mists, you would see a tiny, cluttered room in which forty stuffed armchairs, most of them unused, were crammed around a small open space in the centre of the room, where a circular trapdoor waited on your escape.

‘The grim!’ Professor Trelawney said in a quavering voice, as she peered into George Weasley’s teacup. ‘The grim! It is a sign of death! One whom you know, George – someone you know is to die! And soon – yes, it shall be quite soon, I think – unless of course it is later –’

It would have been a good deal scarier, thought Fred and George, if she hadn’t said the same thing to every single other student in their Divination class. They were hardly even thinking about it at this point; all their thoughts were on today’s disaster –

The trapdoor in the floor flew open with a bang that caused Professor Trelawney to shriek and spill George’s tea all over his robes, and then an instant later Dumbledore was whooshing up out of the floor with a bird of fire upon his shoulder.

‘Fred!’ the old wizard said commandingly. His robes were the black of a moonless night, his eyes hard like blue diamonds. ‘George! With me, now!’

There was an collective gasp and by the time Fred and George were climbing down the ladder after the Headmaster, the entire class was already speculating what role they’d played in the attempted murder of Draco Malfoy.

The trapdoor had hardly slammed shut above them before all nearby sounds muted and the old wizard spun on them and held out a hand and commanded, ‘Give me the map!’

‘M-map?’ said Fred or George in total shock. They’d never even suspected that Dumbledore suspected. ‘Why, w-we don’t know what you’re –’

‘Hermione Granger is in trouble,’ said the old wizard.

‘The Map is in our dorm,’ George or Fred said immediately. ‘Just give us a few minutes to get it and we’ll –’

The wizard’s arms swept them up as if they were hugging-pillows, there was a piercing cry and a flash of fire and then the three of them were in the third-year Gryffindor boys’ dorm.

A few moments later, Fred and George were handing over the Map to the Headmaster, wincing only slightly at the sacrilege of giving their precious piece of the Hogwarts security system to the person who actually owned it, and the old wizard was frowning at the apparent blankness.

‘You’ve got to say,’ they explained, ‘I solemnly swear that I am up to no good –’

‘I decline to lie,’ said the old wizard. He held the Map high and bellowed, ‘Hear me, Hogwarts! Deligitor prodi!’ An instant later the Headmaster was wearing the Sorting Hat, which looked scarily right upon his head, as though Dumbledore had always been waiting for a patchwork pointed hat to complete his existence.

(Fred and George immediately memorized this phrase, just in case it would work for somebody besides the Headmaster, and began trying to think of pranks that would involve the Sorting Hat.)

The old wizard wasted not a moment before sweeping the Sorting Hat off his head and turning it upside-down – it was hard to tell with the Hat upside-down, but it looked a bit cross at the treatment – and then plunged in his hand and drew out a crystal rod. With this instrument he began tracing rune-like patterns on the Map, muttering strange incantations that sounded not quite like Latin and echoed in their ears in an unusually creepy fashion. In the midst of tracing one rune he looked up at both of them, fixing them with a sharp glare. ‘I will return this to you later, sons of Weasley. Go back to class.’

‘Yes, Headmaster,’ they said, and hesitated. ‘Ah – about Hermione Granger, is she really going to be bound to serve Draco Malfoy forever as his –’

‘Go,’ said the old wizard.

They went.

When he was alone in the room, the old wizard looked down at the map, which had now written upon itself a fine line drawing of the Gryffindor dorms in which they stood, the small handwritten Albus P.W.B. Dumbledore the only name left therein.

The old wizard smoothed the map, bent over it, and whispered, ‘Find Tom Riddle.’

The interrogation room at the Department of Magical Law Enforcement was usually lit by a small orange light, so that the Auror interrogating you would be leaning toward your uncomfortable metal chair with most of their face in shadow, preventing you from reading their expression, even as they read yours.

As soon as Mr Quirrell had entered the room, the small orange light had dimmed and begun flickering like a candle about to be blown out by the wind. The room was now lit by a sourceless ice-coloured glow which illuminated all of Mr Quirrell’s pale skin like alabaster, except, somehow, his eyes, which stayed in darkness.

The Auror on duty outside had surreptitiously tried to dispel this effect four times without the slightest success, despite the fact that Mr Quirrell had politely surrendered his wand upon being detained for interrogation, and had shown no sign of speaking any incantations nor exerting any other power.

‘Quirinus … Quirrell,’ drawled the man now sitting across from where the Defence Professor had waited courteously. The interrogator had tawny hair that swept back like a lion’s mane, with yellowish eyes set into the sternly lined face of a man late in his tenth decade. The man was, at this moment, leafing through a large folder of parchments that he had taken from a black and very solid-looking briefcase after he had limped into the room and sat down, seeming not to look at the face of the man he was interrogating. He had not introduced himself.

After some further leafing through parchments, carried out in silence, the Auror spoke again. ‘Born the 26th of September, 1955, to Quondia Quirrell, of an acknowledged tryst with Lirinus Lumblung …’ intoned the Auror. ‘Sorted into Ravenclaw … O.W.L.s quite good … N.E.W.T.s in Charms, Transfiguration … an Outstanding in Muggle Studies, impressive … Ancient Runes, and ah yes, Defence. An Outstanding in that as well. Went on to become quite the tourist, visiting all sorts of places. Portkey visas for Transylvania, the Forbidden Empire, the City of Endless Night … my my, Texas.’ The man looked up from the portfolio, eyes narrowed. ‘What were you doing there, Mr Quirrell?’

‘Sightseeing, mostly in the Muggle areas,’ the Defence Professor said easily. ‘As you say, I am quite the tourist.’

The man listened to this with a frown, then looked back down, then up again. ‘I also see that you visited Fuyuki City in 1983.’

The Defence Professor lifted an eyebrow in mild puzzlement. ‘What of it?’

‘What did you do in Fuyuki City?’ The question snapped out razor-sharp.

The Defence Professor frowned slightly. ‘Nothing of any account. I visited some better-known sights, some less-known sights, and aside from that, kept to myself.’

‘Really?’ the Auror said softly. ‘I find that reply rather interesting.’

‘How so?’ said the Defence Professor.

‘Because there was no visa listed for Fuyuki City.’ The man slammed the folder shut. ‘You’re not Quirinus Quirrell. Who the hell are you?’

The Potions Master walked quietly into the Ravenclaw girls’ dorm, the first-year dorm, a festive place where bronze and blue competed to be the colour of stuffed animals, scarves and dresses, small bits of inexpensive jewellery, and posters of famous people. Hermione Granger’s bed was easy to identify; it was the one that had been attacked by a book monster.

Nobody else seemed to be around, at that time of day, and a number of spells verified this.

The Potions Master searched under Hermione Granger’s pillow, and beneath her bed, and then began going through her trunk, sorting through mentionable and unmentionable items without change of expression, and finally succeeded in drawing forth a set of papers describing places and times where bullies would be found, all of the papers signed only with an elaborate S.

A brief burst of fire later, the papers were gone, and the Potions Master left to report the failure of his mission.

The Defence Professor was sitting calmly with his hands still folded in his lap. ‘If you consult Headmaster Dumbledore,’ said the Defence Professor, ‘you will find that he is well aware of this matter, and that I agreed to teach his Defence class on the explicit condition that no inquiry be made into my –’

In a lightning motion, the interrogator whipped out his wand and spat ‘Polyfluis Reverso!’ at the same time that the Defence Professor sneezed, which somehow caused the mirror-silvered ray to disrupt in a shower of white sparks.

‘Pardon me,’ the Defence Professor said politely.

The smile that the Auror gave had absolutely no mirth in it. ‘So where’s the real Quirinus Quirrell, eh? Under an Imperius in the bottom of a trunk somewhere, while you take a hair now and then for your illegal Polyjuice?’

‘You are making highly questionable assumptions,’ the Defence Professor said with an edged voice. ‘What makes you think I did not steal his body outright using incredibly Dark magic?’

This was followed by a certain pause.

‘I suggest,’ the Auror said, ‘that you take this seriously, Mr Whoever-You-Are.’

‘I’m sorry,’ said the Defence Professor, leaning back in his chair, ‘but I see little reason to humble myself on this particular occasion. What are you going to do, kill me?’

‘I don’t appreciate your humour,’ the Auror said softly.

‘How unfortunate for you, Rufus Scrimgeour,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘You have my deepest sympathy.’ He tilted his head, seeming to study the interrogator; and even within the shadow of the ice-light, the eyes glinted.

Padma stared down at her plate.

‘Hermione wouldn’t just do that!’ yelled Mandy Brocklehurst, who was practically in tears, in fact she was in tears, her voice would have been loud enough to silence the Great Hall if it hadn’t been for all the other students also screaming at each other. ‘I – I bet Malfoy tried to – to do things to her –’

‘Our General would never do that!’ Kevin Entwhistle yelled even louder than Mandy.

‘Of course he would!’ shouted Anthony Goldstein. ‘Malfoy’s the son of a Death Eater!’

Padma stared down at her plate.

Draco was the General of her army.

Hermione was the founder of S.P.H.E.W.

Draco had trusted her to be his second-in-command.

Hermione was her fellow Ravenclaw.

Both of them were her friends, maybe the two best friends she had.

Padma stared down at her plate. She was glad the Sorting Hat hadn’t offered her Hufflepuff. If she’d been Sorted into Hufflepuff it would probably have been much more painful, trying to decide where her divided loyalties lay …

She blinked and realized that her vision had blurred again, and raised a trembling hand to wipe once more at her eyes.

Morag MacDougal snorted so loudly it was audible even amid the pandemonium of lunch, and said in a loud voice, ‘I bet Granger cheated in her battle yesterday, I bet that’s why Malfoy challenged her –’

‘All of you Shut up!’ roared Harry Potter, as he hit the table with his fists so hard that plates rattled all the way along it.

At any other time that would have earned him a Professorial reprimand; this time it just got a few nearby students to look.

‘I’d wanted to eat lunch,’ Harry Potter said, ‘and then get back to investigating, so I wasn’t going to talk. But you’re all being silly, and when the truth comes out you’re going to regret what you said about innocent people. Draco didn’t do anything, Hermione didn’t do anything, they were both False-Memory-Charmed!’ Harry Potter’s voice had been rising on the last words. ‘How is that not bloody obvious?’

‘You think we’ll believe that?’ Kevin Entwhistle yelled right back at him. ‘That’s what everyone says! “I didn’t do it, it was all just a False Memory Charm!” You think we’re stupid?’

And Morag nodded right along with him, with a condescending look.

The look that came over Harry Potter’s face then made Padma flinch.

‘I see,’ Harry Potter said; it wasn’t a shout, so Padma had to strain to hear it. ‘Professor Quirrell isn’t here to explain to me how stupid people are, but I bet this time I can get it on my own. People do something dumb and get caught and are given Veritaserum. Not romantic master criminals, because they wouldn’t get caught, they would have learned Occlumency. Sad, pathetic, incompetent criminals get caught, and confess under Veritaserum, and they’re desperate to stay out of Azkaban so they say they were False-Memory-Charmed. Right? So your brain, by sheer Pavlovian association, links the idea of False Memory Charms to pathetic criminals with unbelievable excuses. You don’t have to consider the specific details, your brain just pattern-matches the hypothesis into a bucket of things you don’t believe, and you’re done. Just like my father thought that magical hypotheses could never be believed, because he’d heard so many stupid people talking about magic. Believing a hypothesis that involves False Memory Charms is low-status.’

‘What are you blithering about?’ said Morag, looking down her nose at the Boy-Who-Lived.

‘You think we’d believe anything you say?’ yelled a slightly older-looking Ravenclaw witch who Padma didn’t recognize. ‘When you turned Granger Dark?’

‘And I’m not going to complain,’ Harry Potter said in an eerily calm voice, ‘about wizards not having any logic and believing the craziest things. Because I said that to Professor Quirrell once, and he just gave me this look and said that if I wasn’t blinded by my upbringing I could think of a hundred more ridiculous things that lots of Muggles believe. What you’re all doing is very human and very normal and doesn’t make you unusually bad people, so I’m not going to complain.’ The Boy-Who-Lived rose up from his bench. ‘I’ll see you all later.’

And Harry Potter walked away from them, walked away from all of them.

‘You’re not thinking he’s right, are you?’ said Su Li from beside her, in a tone which made it clear what she thought.

‘I –’ said Padma. Her words seemed to be caught in her throat, her thoughts seemed to be caught in her head. ‘I – I mean – I –’

If you think hard enough you can do the impossible.

(It had always been an article of faith with Harry. There’d been a time when he’d acknowledged the laws of physics as ultimate limitations, and now he suspected there were no true limits at all.)

If you think fast enough you can sometimes do the impossible quickly …

… sometimes.

Only sometimes.

Not always.

Not reliably.

The Boy-Who-Lived stared around the trophy room, surrounded by awards and cups and plates and shields and statues and medals kept behind thousands, perhaps tens of thousands, of crystal glass displays. For as many centuries as Hogwarts had existed, this room had been accumulating details. A week, a month, maybe even a year, wouldn’t have sufficed to take the examine option on every item in the room. With Professor Flitwick gone, Harry had asked Professor Vector if there was any way to detect damage to the wards around the crystal cases, verify the residue that a real duel should have left behind. Harry had raced through the Hogwarts library looking for spells to tell the difference between old fingerprints and new fingerprints, or to detect lingering exhalations in a room. And all those attempts at playing detective had failed.

There were no clues, none that he was smart enough to find.

Professor Snape had said that the portkey led to an empty house in London, with no sign of anyone or anything else.

Professor Snape hadn’t found any notes in Hermione’s dorm.

Headmaster Dumbledore had said that Voldemort’s spirit was probably hiding out in the Chamber of Secrets where the Hogwarts security system couldn’t find him. Harry had sneaked into the Slytherin dungeons under the Cloak of Invisibility and spent the rest of the afternoon looking through all the obvious places, but he hadn’t found anything snaky that answered back when spoken to. The entrance to the Chamber of Secrets, it seemed, hadn’t been meant to be found in a day.

Harry had talked to all of Hermione’s friends that would still talk to him, and none of them had remembered Hermione saying anything specific about why she’d believed that Draco was plotting against her.

Professor Quirrell hadn’t come back from the Ministry as of dinnertime. The older students seemed to think that this year’s Defence Professor would probably end up being blamed for the incident, and fired for teaching Hogwarts students to be too violent. They’d talked about the Defence Professor as though he were already gone.

Harry had used up all six hours from his Time-Turner, and there were still no clues, and he had to go to sleep now if he wanted to be functional at Hermione’s trial the next day.

The Boy-Who-Destroyed-A-Dementor was standing in the middle of the Hogwarts trophy room, his wand dropped at his feet.

He was crying.

Sometimes you call your brain and it doesn’t answer.

The trial of Hermione Granger started on schedule the next day.

Minerva was waiting, doing her best not to hover, beside the double doors to the Hogwarts infirmary, she’d always thought of those doors as ‘the ominous gates’ as a child in Hogwarts, and couldn’t help but remember that now. Too much bad news had been spoken here –

Albus stepped out. The old wizard did not pause on the way out of the infirmary, only kept walking toward Professor Flitwick’s office; and Minerva followed him.

Professor McGonagall cleared her throat. ‘Is it done, Albus?’

The old wizard nodded in affirmation. ‘If any hostile magic is cast on her, or any spirit touches her, I shall know, and come.’

‘I spoke to Mr Potter after Transfiguration class,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘He was of the opinion that Miss Granger should go to Beauxbatons, rather than Hogwarts, from now on.’

The old wizard shook his head. ‘No. If Voldemort truly desires to strike at Miss Granger – he is tenacious beyond measure. His servants are returning to him, he could not have retrieved Bellatrix alone. Azkaban itself is not safe from his malice, and as for Beauxbatons – no, Minerva. I do not think Voldemort can essay such possessions often, or against stronger targets, or this year would have gone quite differently. And Harry Potter is here, whom Voldemort must fear whether he admits it or no. Now that I have warded her, Miss Granger will be safer within Hogwarts than without.’

‘Mr Potter seemed to doubt that,’ Minerva said. She couldn’t quite keep the edge from her voice; there was a part of her that agreed rather strongly. ‘He seemed to feel that common sense said Miss Granger should continue her education anywhere but Hogwarts.’

The old wizard sighed. ‘I fear the boy has spent too much time among the Muggles. Always they reach for safety; always they imagine that safety can be reached. If Miss Granger is not safe within the centre of our fortress, she shall be no safer for leaving it.’

‘Not everyone seems to think so,’ said Professor McGonagall. It had been almost the first letter she’d seen when she’d taken a quick look at her desk; an envelope of the finest sheepskin, sealed in greenish-silver wax, pressed into the image of a snake that rose and hissed at her. ‘I have received Lord Malfoy’s owl withdrawing his son from Hogwarts.’

The old wizard nodded, but did not break stride. ‘Does Harry know?’

‘Yes.’ Her voice faltered, for a moment, remembering Harry’s expression. ‘After class, Mr Potter complimented Lord Malfoy’s excellent good sense, and said that he would be writing Madam Longbottom advising her to do the same with her grandson, in case he was the next target. In the event that Mr Longbottom’s guardian was so negligent as to keep him in Hogwarts, Mr Potter wanted him to have a Time-Turner, an invisibility cloak, a broomstick, and a pouch in which to carry them; also a toe-ring with an emergency portkey to a safe location, in case someone kidnaps Mr Longbottom and takes him outside Hogwarts’s wards. I told Mr Potter that I did not think the Ministry would consent to such use of our Time-Turners, and he said that we should not ask. I expect he will want Miss Granger to receive the same, if she stays. And for himself Mr Potter wants a three-person broomstick to carry in his pouch.’ She wasn’t awed by the list of precautions. Impressed with the cleverness, but not awed; she was a Transfiguration Mistress, after all. But it still sent shivers of disquiet through her, that Harry Potter now thought Hogwarts as dangerous as spell research.

‘The Department of Mysteries is not lightly defied,’ said Albus. ‘But for the rest –’ The old wizard seemed to slump in on himself slightly. ‘We may as well give the boy what he wishes. And I will ward Neville also, and write Augusta to say that he should stay here over holiday.’

‘And finally,’ she said, ‘Mr Potter says – this is a direct quote, Albus – whatever kind of Dark Wizard attractant the Headmaster is keeping here, he needs to get it out of this school, now.’ She couldn’t stop the edge in her own voice, that time.

‘I asked as much of Flamel,’ Albus said, the pain clear in his voice. ‘But Master Flamel has said – that even he can no longer keep safe the Stone – that he believes Voldemort has means of finding it wherever it is hidden – and that he does not consent for it to be guarded anywhere but Hogwarts. Minerva, I am sorry, but it must be done – must!’

‘Very well,’ said Professor McGonagall. ‘But for myself, I think that Mr Potter is right on every single count.’

The old wizard glanced at her, and his voice caught as he said, ‘Minerva, you have known me long, and as well as any soul still living – tell me, have I lost myself to darkness already?’

‘What?’ said Professor McGonagall in genuine surprise. Then, ‘Oh, Albus, no!’

The old wizard’s lips pressed together tightly before he spoke. ‘For the greater good. I have sacrificed so many, for the greater good. Today I almost condemned Hermione Granger to Azkaban for the greater good. And I find myself – today, I found myself – beginning to resent the innocence that is no longer mine –’ The old wizard’s voice halted. ‘Evil done in the name of good. Evil done in the name of evil. Which is worse?’

‘You are being silly, Albus.’

The old wizard glanced at her again, before turning his eyes back to their way. ‘Tell me, Minerva – did you pause to weigh the consequences, before you told Miss Granger how to bind herself to the Potter family?’

She took an involuntary breath as she understood what she had done –

‘So you did not.’ Albus’s eyes were saddened. ‘No, Minerva, you must not apologize. It is well. For what you have seen of me this day – if your first loyalty is now to Harry Potter, and not to me, then that is right and proper.’ She opened her lips to protest, but Albus went on before she could say a word. ‘Indeed – indeed – that will be necessary and more than necessary, if the Dark Lord that Harry must defeat to come into his power is not Voldemort after all –’

‘Not this again!’ Minerva said. ‘Albus, it was You-Know-Who, not you, who marked Harry as his equal. There is no possible way that the prophecy could be talking about you!’

The old wizard nodded, but his eyes still seemed distant, fixed only on the road ahead.

The holding cell, well to the centre of Magical Law Enforcement, was luxuriously appointed; more a remark on what adult wizards took for granted, than any special feeling toward prisoners. There was a self-reclining, self-rocking chair with plush, richly textured, self-warming cushions. There was a bookcase containing random books rescued from a bargain bin, and a full shelf of ancient magazines, including one from 1883. As for toiletries, well, it wasn’t exactly luxurious, but there was a spell on the room which put all that business on hold; you weren’t to go anywhere that the watching Auror couldn’t see you. But aside from that, it was quite a pleasant little cell. The Defence Professor of Hogwarts was being detained, not arrested, not even intimidated. There was no evidence to indict him … except that a terrible and unusual crime had been committed at the Hogwarts School of Witchcraft and Wizardry, and going by previous occasions the odds were five to one that the current Defence Professor was tangled up in it somehow. To this must be added the fact that nobody in the D.M.L.E. even knew who the Defence Professor was, and that the man had literally sneezed at all attempts to uncover his true identity. Why, no, they hadn’t released Quirinus Quirrell back to Hogwarts just yet.

Let us repeat this for emphasis:

The Defence Professor.

Was being detained.

In a cell.

The Defence Professor was staring at the watching Auror and humming.

The Defence Professor has not spoken a single word since he arrived in this particular cell. He has only been humming.

The humming started as a simple children’s lullaby, the one that in Muggle Britain begins, Rock-a-bye baby …

This tune was hummed, without variation, over and over, for seven minutes, to establish the underlying pattern.

Then began the elaborations upon the theme. Phrases hummed too slow, with long pauses in between, so that the listener’s mind helplessly waits and waits for the next note, the next phrase. And then, when that next phrase comes, it is so out of key, so unbelievably awfully out of key, not just out of key for the previous phrases but sung at a pitch which does not correspond to any key, that you would have to believe this person had spent hours deliberately practising their humming just to acquire such perfect anti-pitch.

It bears the same resemblance to music as the awful dead voice of a Dementor bears to human speech.

And this horrible, horrible humming is impossible to ignore. It is similar to a known lullaby, but it departs from that pattern unpredictably. It sets up expectations and then violates them, never in any constant pattern that would permit the humming to fade into the background. The listener’s brain cannot prevent itself from expecting the anti-musical phrases to complete, nor prevent itself from noticing the surprises.

The only possible explanation for how this mode of humming came to exist is that it was deliberately designed by some unspeakably cruel genius who woke up one day, feeling bored with ordinary torture, who decided to handicap himself and find out whether he could break someone’s sanity just by humming at them.

The Auror has been listening to this unimaginably dreadful humming for four hours, while being stared at by a huge, cold, lethal presence that feels equally horrible whether he looks at it directly or lets it hover at the corner of his vision –

The humming stopped.

There was a long wait. Time enough for false hope to rise, and be squashed down by the memory of previous disappointments. And then, as the interval lengthened, and lengthened, that hope rose again unstoppably –

The humming began once more.

The Auror cracked.

From his belt, the Auror took a mirror, tapped it once, and then said, ‘This is Junior Auror Arjun Altunay, I’m calling in code RJ-L20 on cell three.’

‘Code RJ-L20?’ the mirror said in surprised tones. There was a sound of pages being flipped, then, ‘You want to be relieved because a prisoner is attempting psychological warfare and succeeding?’

(Amelia Bones really is quite intelligent.)

‘What’d the prisoner say to you?’ said the mirror.

(This question is not part of procedure RJ-L20, but unfortunately Amelia Bones has failed to include an explicit instruction that the commanding officer should not ask.)

‘He’s –’ said the Auror, and glanced back at the cell. The Defence Professor was now leaning in back in his chair, looking quite relaxed. ‘He was staring at me! And humming!’

There was a pause.

The mirror spoke again. ‘And you’re calling in an RJ-L20 over that? You’re sure you’re not just trying to get out of watching him?’

(Amelia Bones is surrounded by idiots.)

‘You don’t understand!’ yelled Auror Altunay. ‘It’s really awful humming!’

The mirror transmitted a sound of muffled laughter in the background, sounding like it was coming from more than one person. Then speech again. ‘Mr Altunay, if you don’t want to be busted to Junior Auror Second Class, I suggest you buckle down and get back to work –’

‘Strike that,’ a crisp voice said, sounding slightly remote due to its distance from the mirror.

(Which is why Amelia Bones often sits in on a coordination centre of the D.M.L.E. while doing her Ministry-required paperwork.)

‘Auror Altunay,’ said the crisp voice, seeming to approach closer to the mirror, ‘you will be relieved shortly. Auror Ben Gutierrez, the procedure for RJ-L20 does not say that you ask why. It says that you relieve the Auror who calls it in. If I find that Aurors seem to be abusing it, I will modify the procedure to prevent its abuse –’ The mirror cut off abruptly.

The Auror turned back to look triumphantly at where the current Defence Professor of Hogwarts was leaning back in his cushioned chair.

That man then spoke the first words that had left his lips since he entered the cell.

‘Goodbye, Mr Altunay,’ said the Defence Professor.

A few minutes later, the door to the detention cell opened, and in walked a grey-haired woman, dressed in the crimson-tinged robes of an Auror without any sign of rank or other ornamentation, carrying a black leather folder under her left arm. ‘You’re relieved,’ the old woman said abruptly.

There was a brief delay while Auror Altunay tried to explain what had been happening. This was cut short by a nod and a stark, simple finger pointing out the door.

‘Good evening, Madam Director,’ said the Defence Professor.

Amelia Bones did not acknowledge this statement, but sat down abruptly in the vacated chair. The old witch opened the black folder and her gaze moved down to the parchments therein. ‘Possible hints to the identity of the current Hogwarts Defence Professor, as compiled by Auror Robards.’ The title parchment was turned, flipped aside. ‘The Defence Professor said that he was Sorted into Slytherin. Claimed that his family was killed by Voldemort. Said he had studied at a martial arts centre in Muggle Asia which was destroyed by Voldemort. A request filed with the Department of International Magical Cooperation identifies this incident as the Oni Affair of 1969.’ Another parchment was flipped aside. ‘It also seems this Defence Professor gave a most stirring speech to his students, just before last Yule, castigating the previous generation for their disunity against the Death Eaters.’ The old witch looked up from the leather folder. ‘Madam Longbottom was rather taken with it, and insisted that I read the entire thing. The argument struck me as familiar, though I could not place it at the time. But then, of course, I had thought you dead.’

The chief law enforcement officer of Magical Britain was now gazing sharply at the current Defence Professor of Hogwarts, across the pane of spell-reinforced glass separating them. The man in the cell returned the gaze equably, without apparent alarm.

‘I shall not name any names,’ said the old witch. ‘But I shall tell a story, and see if it sounds familiar.’ Amelia Bones looked back down, turning to the next parchment. ‘Born 1927, entered Hogwarts in 1938, sorted into Slytherin, graduated 1945. Went on a graduation tour abroad and disappeared while visiting Albania. Presumed dead until 1970, when he returned to magical Britain just as suddenly, without any explanation for the missing twenty-five years. He remained estranged from his family and friends, living in isolation. In 1971, while visiting Diagon Alley, he fended off an attempt by Bellatrix Black to kidnap the daughter of the Minister of Magic, and used the Killing Curse to slay two of the three Death Eaters accompanying her. Beyond this all Britain knows the story; need I continue it?’ The old witch looked up from her folder again. ‘Very well. There was a trial in the Wizengamot, during which this young man was exonerated for his use of the Killing Curse, not least due to the efforts of his grandmother, the Lady of his House. He was reconciled with his family, and they held a House gathering to welcome his return. The guest of honour arrived at that gathering to find his entire family slain by Death Eaters, even to the house elves; and that he himself, of cadet line, was now the last remaining scion of a Most Ancient House.’

The Defence Professor had not reacted at all to any of this, except that his eyes had half-closed, as though in weariness.

‘The young man took up his family’s seat in the Wizengamot, becoming among the most steadfast voices against You-Know-Who. Several times he led forces against the Death Eaters, fighting with skilful tactics and extraordinary power. People began to speak of him as the next Dumbledore, it was thought that he might become Minister of Magic after the Dark Lord fell. On the third of July, 1973, he failed to appear at a key Wizengamot vote, and was never heard from again. We assumed You-Know-Who had killed him. It was a grave blow to all of us, and matters went much the worse from that day on.’ The old witch’s gaze was questioning. ‘I mourned you myself. What happened?’

The Defence Professor’s shoulders moved lightly, a small shrug. ‘You make many assumptions,’ the Defence Professor said softly. ‘For myself, I would believe that man died years ago. But if that man is nonetheless alive – then it is clear he does not wish the fact announced, and has reasons enough for silence. That man was once of some help to you, it seems.’ The Defence Professor’s lips curved in a cynical smile. ‘But I am no longer surprised when gratitude is fleeting. Is there yet more that you would demand from him?’

The old witch leaned back in her Auror’s monitoring-chair, looking rather startled, maybe even hurt. ‘No –’ she said after a moment. Her fingers tapped the leather folder; nervously, you might have thought, if you had believed that Amelia Bones could ever be nervous. ‘But your House – there are not many Ancient Houses remaining –’

‘It shall matter little to this country whether eight Ancient Houses remain, or seven.’

The old witch sighed. ‘What does Dumbledore think of this?’

The man in the detention cell shook his head. ‘He does not know who I am, and promised not to inquire.’

The old witch’s eyebrows rose. ‘How did he identify you to the Hogwarts wards, then?’

A slight smile. ‘The Headmaster drew a circle, and told Hogwarts that he who stood within was the Defence Professor. Speaking of which –’ The tone went lower, flatter. ‘I am missing my classes, Director Bones.’

‘You seem to – rest, sometimes, in a peculiar manner. This has also been reported. And you seem to be resting more and more frequently, as time goes on.’ The old witch’s fingers tapped the leather folder again. ‘I cannot recall reading of such a symptom, but when one hears of such a thing, one imagines … Dark Wizards fought, and terrible curses received …’

The Defence Professor remained expressionless.

‘Do you require a healer’s help?’ said Amelia Bones. Her own mask had slipped, clearly showing the pain in her eyes. ‘Is there anything at all that can be done for you?’

‘I agreed to teach Defence at Hogwarts,’ the man in the cell said flatly. ‘Draw your own conclusions, Madam. And I am missing my classes, of which there are not many left. I would return to Hogwarts, now.’

When Hermione woke the third time (though it felt like she’d only closed her eyes for a moment) the Sun was even lower in the sky, almost fully set. She felt a little more alive and, strangely, even more exhausted. This time it was Professor Flitwick who was standing next to her bed and shaking her shoulder, a tray of steaming food floating next to him. For some reason she’d thought Harry Potter ought to be leaning over her bedside, but he wasn’t there. Had she dreamed that? She couldn’t remember dreaming.

It developed (according to Professor Flitwick) that Hermione had missed dinner in the Great Hall, and was being woken to eat. And then she could go back to the Ravenclaw dorm, and her own bed, to sleep the rest of the night.

She ate in silence. There was a part of her that wanted to ask Professor Flitwick whether he thought she’d been Memory-Charmed or she’d tried to kill Draco Malfoy of her own will –

– like she remembered doing –

– but most of her was afraid to find out. Afraid to find out was a warning sign, according to Harry Potter and his books; but her mind felt tired, bruised, and she couldn’t muster the strength to override it.

When she and Professor Flitwick left the infirmary they found Harry Potter sitting cross-legged outside the door, quietly reading a psychology textbook.

‘I’ll take her from here,’ said the Boy-Who-Lived. ‘Professor McGonagall said it would be all right.’

Professor Flitwick seemed to accept this, and departed after a stern look at both of them. She couldn’t imagine what the stern look was supposed to say, unless it was don’t try to kill any more students.

The footsteps of Professor Flitwick faded, and the two of them stood alone outside the doors of the infirmary.

She looked at the green eyes of the Boy-Who-Lived, the unruly hair that didn’t quite obscure the scar on his forehead; she looked upon the face of the boy who’d given all his money to save her without a second thought. There were feelings inside her – guilt, shame, embarrassment, other things as well – but no words. There was nothing she knew how to say.

‘So,’ Harry said abruptly, ‘I did a quick skim through my psychology books to see what they said about post-traumatic stress disorder. The old books said you should talk about the experience immediately afterwards with a counsellor. The newer research says that when they actually ran experiments, it turned out that talking about it immediately afterwards made it worse. Apparently what you really ought to do is run with your mind’s natural impulse to repress the memories and just not think about it for a while.’

It was so normal for the way she and Harry usually talked that she felt a sudden burning in her throat.

We don’t have to talk about it. That was what Harry had just said, more or less. It felt like cheating, maybe even like a lie. Nothing was normal. Everything wrong was still horribly wrong, everything left unsaid still needed to be said …

‘Okay,’ said Hermione, because there wasn’t anything else to say, anything else at all.

‘I’m sorry I wasn’t waiting when you woke up,’ Harry said, as they started to walk. ‘Madam Pomfrey wouldn’t let me in, so I just stayed out here.’ He gave a small, sad-looking shrug. ‘I suppose I should be out there trying to run damage control on public relations, but … honestly I’ve never been good at that, I just end up speaking sharply at people.’

‘How bad is it?’ She thought her voice should have come out in a whisper, a croak, but it didn’t.

‘Well –’ Harry said with obvious hesitation. ‘The thing you’ve got to understand, Hermione, is that you had a lot of defenders at breakfast-time today, but everyone on your side was … making stuff up. Draco tried to kill you first, things like that. It was Granger versus Malfoy, that’s how people saw it, like a see-saw where pushing his side down meant pushing your side up. I told them you were probably both innocent, that you’d both been Memory-Charmed. They didn’t listen, both sides treated me like a traitor trying to play the middle. And then people heard that Draco had testified under Veritaserum that he’d been trying to help you before the battle – stop making that expression, Hermione, you didn’t actually do anything to him. Anyway, all people understood was that the pro-Malfoy faction had been right and the pro-Granger faction had been wrong.’ Harry gave a small sigh. ‘I told them that when the truth came out later they’d be embarrassed …’

‘How bad is it?’ she said again. This time her voice did come out weaker.

‘Remember Asch’s conformity experiment?’ Harry said, turning his head to give her a serious look.

Her mind was slow to remember for a few seconds, which frightened her, but then the reference came back. In 1951, Solomon Asch had taken some experimental subjects, and each one had been put among a row of other people who looked like them, seeming like other experimental subjects, but actually confederates of the experimenter. They’d shown a reference line on a screen, labelled X, next to three other lines, labelled A, B, and C. The experimenter had asked which line X was the same length as. The correct answer had obviously been C. The other subjects, the confederates, had one after another said that X was the same length as B. The real subject had been put second-to-last in the order, so as not to arouse suspicion by being last. The test had been to see whether the real subject would conform to the standard wrong answer of B, or voice the obviously correct answer of C.

75% of the subjects had conformed at least once. A third of the subjects had conformed more than half the time. Some had reported afterwards actually believing that X was the same length as B. And that had been in a case where the subjects hadn’t known any of the confederates. If you put people around others who belonged to the same group as them, like someone in a wheelchair next to other people in a wheelchair, the conformity effect got even stronger …

Hermione had a sickening feeling where this was going. ‘I remember,’ she whispered.

‘I gave the Chaos Legion anti-conformity training, you know. I had each Legionnaire stand in the middle and say “Twice two is four!” or “Grass is green!” while everyone else in the Chaos Legion called them idiots or sneered at them – Allen Flint did really good sneers – or even just gave them blank looks and then walked away. The thing you’ve got to remember is, only the Chaos Legion has ever practised anything like that. Nobody else in Hogwarts even knows what conformity is.’

‘Harry!’ Her voice was wobbling. ‘How bad is it?’

Harry gave another sad-looking shrug. ‘Everyone in the second year and above, since they don’t know you. Everyone in Dragon Army. All of Slytherin, of course. And, well, most of the rest of magical Britain too, I think. Remember, Lucius Malfoy controls the Daily Prophet.’

‘Everyone?’ she whispered. Her limbs had started to feel cold, like she’d just got out of an unheated swimming pool.

‘What people really believe doesn’t feel like a belief, it feels like the way the world is. You and I are standing in a private little bubble of the universe where Hermione Granger got Memory-Charmed. Everyone else is living in the world where Hermione Granger tried to murder Draco Malfoy. If Ernie Macmillan –’

Her breath caught in her throat. Captain Macmillan –

‘– thinks he’s ethically prohibited from being your friend now, well, he’s trying to do the right thing as he understands it, in the world he thinks he lives in.’ Harry’s eyes were very serious. ‘Hermione, you’ve told me a lot of times that I look down too much on other people. But if I expected too much of them – if I expected people to get things right – I really would hate them, then. Idealism aside, Hogwarts students don’t actually know enough cognitive science to take responsibility for how their own minds work. It’s not their fault they’re crazy.’ Harry’s voice was strangely gentle, almost like an adult’s. ‘I know it’s going to be harder on you than it would be on me. But remember, eventually the real culprit gets nailed. The truth comes out, everyone who was confidently wrong gets embarrassed.’

‘And if the real culprit doesn’t get caught?’ she said in a trembling voice.

… or if it turns out to be me after all?

‘Then you can leave Hogwarts and go to the Salem Witches’ Institute in America.’

‘Leave Hogwarts?’ She’d never even thought of that possibility except as an ultimate punishment.

‘I … Hermione, I think you might want to do that anyway. Hogwarts isn’t a castle, it’s insanity with walls. You have got other options.’

‘I’ll …’ she stammered. ‘I’ll have … to think about it …’

Harry nodded. ‘At least nobody’s going to try hexing you, not after what the Headmaster said at dinner tonight. Oh, and Ron Weasley came up to me, looking very serious, and told me that if I saw you first, I should tell you that he’s sorry for having thought badly of you, and he’ll never speak ill of you again.’

‘Ron believes I’m innocent?’ said Hermione.

‘Well … he doesn’t think you’re innocent, per se …’

The whole Ravenclaw dorm went silent as the two of them walked in.

Staring at them.

Staring at her.

(She’d had nightmares like this.)

And then, one by one, people looked away from her.

Penelope Clearwater, the 5th-year prefect in charge of first-years, looked away slowly and deliberately, turning her head to face in another direction.

Su Li and Lisa Turpin and Michael Corner, all sitting at a table together, all of whom she’d helped with their homework at one time or another, all looked away, their faces suddenly nervous, the moment she tried to catch their eyes.

A third-year witch named Latisha Randle, whom S.P.H.E.W. had twice saved from Slytherin bullies, quickly bent back over her desk and started doing homework again.

Mandy Brocklehurst looked away from her.

If Hermione didn’t burst into tears, then, it was only because she’d expected it, had played it out in her mind over and over again. At least people weren’t screaming at her or shoving her or hexing her. They were just looking away –

Hermione walked very straight up to the staircase that led toward the first-year girl’s dorms. (She didn’t see Padma Patil or Anthony Goldstein looking at her, those two lone heads turning to track her as she left.) From behind her, she heard Harry Potter saying in a very calm tone, ‘Now eventually the truth’s going to come out, all of you. So if you’re all that confident she’s guilty, can I ask you all to sign this paper right here, saying that if she later turns out to be innocent, she gets to say “I told you so” and then hold it over you for the rest of your lives? Step on up, one and all, don’t be cowards, if you really believe you shouldn’t be afraid to bet –’

She was halfway up the stairs when she realized that there would be other girls inside her dorm, too.

The stars hadn’t quite come out yet, only one or two of the brightest ones visible through the reddish-purple haze of the horizon, though the Sun had fully sunk.

Hermione’s hands dug into the harsh stone of the parapet guarding the small balcony, where she’d ducked out of the stairwell after realizing that –

– she couldn’t just go back to bed –

– the words echoed in her mind like You can’t go home again ought to sound.

She stared out at the empty grounds, the fading sunset, the sprouting grass so far below.

Tired, she was tired, she couldn’t think now, she needed to sleep. Professor Flitwick had told her that she needed to sleep, and there’d been yet another potion with her dinner. Maybe that was how wizarding society treated horrible traumas to innocent young girls, just made them sleep a lot afterwards.

She should go to her room and sleep, but she was afraid to go somewhere where other people were. Afraid of how they might look at her, or look away.

Fragments of thought chased themselves around a mind too exhausted to finish or connect them, as the night fully set in.

Why –

Why did all this happen –

Everything was fine a week ago –

Why –

From behind her came the creaky sound of an opening door.

She turned her head and looked.

Professor Quirrell was leaning against the doorway she’d walked through, silhouetted like a cardboard cut-out by the light of the Hogwarts torches lit behind him, in the open door. She couldn’t see his expression, though the doorway behind him was bright; his eyes, his face, everything she could see from here lay within night’s shadow.

The Defence Professor of Hogwarts, number one on the list of people who might’ve done this. She hadn’t even realized she had a suspect list until that moment.

The man stood within that doorway, saying nothing; and she couldn’t see his eyes. What was he even doing there in the first place –

‘Are you here to kill me?’ said Hermione Granger.

Professor Quirrell’s head tilted at that.

Then the Defence Professor started toward her, the dark silhouette raising one hand slowly and deliberately, as though to push her off the Ravenclaw tower –

‘Stupefy!’

The burst of adrenaline overrode everything, she drew her wand without thinking, her lips formed the word of their own accord, the stunbolt leapt out of her wand and –

– slowed to a stop in front of Professor Quirrell’s raised hand, rippling in mid-air like it was still trying to fly and making a slight hissing sound.

The red glow illuminated Professor Quirrell’s face for the first time, showing a strange fond smile.

‘Better,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Miss Granger, you are still a student in my Defence class. As such, if you consider me a threat, I do not expect you to just look at me sadly and ask if I am there to kill you. Minus two Quirrell points.’

She was entirely unable to form words.

The Defence Professor flicked his forefinger casually at the suspended stunbolt, sending the hex shooting back over her head, far into the night, so that they stood again in darkness. Then Professor Quirrell walked out of the doorway, which swung shut behind him; and a soft white light sprung up around the two of them, so that she could see his face once more, still with that strange fond smile.

‘What are you – what are you doing here?’

A few more steps took Professor Quirrell to a higher part of the balcony’s ramparts, where he put his elbows down on the stone, and leaned over heavily, looking up into the night.

‘I came here straight upon being released by the Aurors, the moment I finished reporting to the Headmaster,’ said Professor Quirrell in a quiet voice, ‘because I am your teacher, and you are my student, and I am responsible for you.’

Hermione understood, then; remembering what Professor Quirrell had said to Harry in the second Defence lesson of the year, about controlling his anger. She felt the flush of shame all the way down her chest. It took a moment after that for knowledge to override mortification, for her to force out the words –

‘I –’ said Hermione. ‘Harry thinks – that I didn’t – lose my temper, I mean –’

‘So I heard,’ said Professor Quirrell in rather dry tones. He shook his head, as though at the stars themselves. ‘The boy is fortunate that I have crossed the line from annoyance at his self-destructiveness, into sheer curiosity as to what he will do next. But I agree with Mr Potter’s assessment of the facts. This crime was well-planned to evade detection both by the wards of Hogwarts and the Headmaster’s timely eye. Naturally, in such a thoughtful murder, some innocent would be placed to take the blame.’ A brief, wry smile crossed the Defence Professor’s lips, though he wasn’t looking at her. ‘As for the notion that you did it yourself – I consider myself a talented teacher, but even I could not teach such murderous intent to a student as obstinate and untalented as Hermione Granger.’

The part of her brain that said What? in indignation wasn’t anywhere near loud enough to reach her lips.

‘No …’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘That is not why I am here. You have made no effort to hide your dislike for me, Miss Granger. I thank you for that lack of pretence, for I much prefer true hate to false love. But you are still my student, and I have a word to say to you, if you will hear it.’

Hermione looked at him, still fighting down the after-effects of the adrenaline from before. The Defence Professor seemed to be just staring up at the dark sky, in which the stars were becoming visible.

‘I was going to be a hero, once,’ said Professor Quirrell, still looking upward. ‘Can you believe that, Miss Granger?’

‘No.’

‘Thank you again, Miss Granger. It is true nonetheless. Long ago, long before your time or Harry Potter’s, there was a man who was hailed as a saviour. The destined scion, such a one as anyone would recognize from tales, wielding justice and vengeance like twin wands against his dreadful nemesis.’ Professor Quirrell gave a soft, bitter laugh, looking up at the night sky. ‘Do you know, Miss Granger, at that time I thought myself already cynical, and yet … well.’

The silence stretched, in the cold and the night.

‘In all honesty,’ said Professor Quirrell, looking up at the stars, ‘I still don’t understand it. They should have known that their lives depended on that man’s success. And yet it was as if they tried to do everything they could to make his life unpleasant. To throw every possible obstacle into his way. I was not naive, Miss Granger, I did not expect the power-holders to align themselves with me so quickly – not without something in it for themselves. But their power, too, was threatened; and so I was shocked how they seemed content to step back, and leave to that man all burdens of responsibility. They sneered at his performance, remarking among themselves how they would do better in his place, though they did not condescend to step forward.’ Professor Quirrell shook his head as though in bemusement. ‘And it was the strangest thing – the Dark Wizard, that man’s dread nemesis – why, those who served him leapt eagerly to their tasks. The Dark Wizard grew crueller toward his followers, and they followed him all the more. Men fought for the chance to serve him, even as those whose lives depended on that other man made free to render his life difficult … I could not understand it, Miss Granger.’ Professor Quirrell’s face was in shadow, as he looked upward. ‘Perhaps, by taking on himself the curse of action, that man removed it from all others? Was that why they felt free to hinder his battle against the Dark Wizard who would have enslaved them all? Believing men would act in their own interest was not cynicism, it turned out, but sheerest optimism; in reality men do not meet so high a standard. And so in time that one realized he might do better fighting the Dark Wizard alone, than with such followers at his back.’

‘So –’ Hermione’s voice sounded strange in the night. ‘You left your friends behind where they’d be safe, and tried to attack the Dark Wizard all by yourself?’

‘Why, no,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I stopped trying to be a hero, and went off to do something else I found more pleasant.’

‘What?’ said Hermione without thinking at all. ‘That’s horrible!’

The Defence Professor turned his head down from the sky to regard her; and she saw, in the light of the doorway, that he was smiling – or at least half his face was smiling. ‘Are you going to tell me, Miss Granger, that I am an awful person? Well, perhaps I am. But then are people who never even try to be heroes still worse? If I had never done anything at all, like them, would you have thought better of me?’

Hermione opened her mouth and then found that, once again, she didn’t have anything to say. It wasn’t right to walk away from being a hero, you couldn’t just do that, but she didn’t want to say that everyone who wasn’t a hero was nothing, that was Quirrell-thinking …

The smile, or half-smile, had disappeared. ‘You were foolish,’ the Defence Professor said quietly, ‘to expect any lasting gratitude from those you tried to protect, once you named yourself a heroine. Just as you expected that man to go on being a hero, and called him horrible for stopping, when a thousand others never lifted a finger. It was only expected that you should fight bullies. It was a tax you owed, and they accepted it like princes, with a sneer for the lateness of your payment. And you have already witnessed, I wager, that their fondness vanished like dust in the wind once it was no longer in their interest to associate with you …’

The Defence Professor slowly straightened up from the balcony, standing almost erect, turning to regard her fully.

‘But you don’t have to be a hero, Miss Granger,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘You can stop anytime you please.’

That idea …

… had occurred to her before, several times over the last two days.

People become who they are meant to be, by doing what is right, Headmaster Dumbledore had told her. The trouble was that there seemed to be two different right things to do. There was the part of her which said that right was to go on being a heroine, and stay at Hogwarts, she didn’t know what was going on but a heroine wouldn’t just run away.

And there was also the voice of common sense saying that young children shouldn’t ever stay around danger, that was what adults were for; the voice of every school poster that said not to take sweets from strangers. That was also right.

Hermione Granger stood there on that balcony, looking at Professor Quirrell silhouetted by the emerging stars, and she didn’t understand; she didn’t understand how the Defence Professor could be gazing at her with his face showing concern; she didn’t understand the notes of pain in the Defence Professor’s voice that caught at her; she didn’t understand why she was being told all this.

‘You don’t even like me, Professor,’ said Hermione.

A small smile flickered on Professor Quirrell’s face. ‘I suppose I could go on about how I am angered that this affair has taken up my valuable time and disrupted my Defence classes. But mostly, Miss Granger, you are my student, and whatever other professions I may have once held, I think I have been a good teacher at Hogwarts, have I not?’ Suddenly Professor Quirrell’s eyes seemed very tired. ‘As your teacher, then, I am advising you that you have other career options. I should not like to see anyone else going down my path.’

Hermione swallowed. It was a side of Professor Quirrell she’d never seen or imagined, and it was eating away at her preconceptions.

Professor Quirrell watched her for a moment, and then looked away from her again, back up at the stars. When he spoke this time his voice was quieter. ‘Someone here is targeting you, Miss Granger, and I cannot ward you as I warded Mr Malfoy. The Headmaster has prevented it, for what he claims to be good reasons. It is easy to become fond of Hogwarts, I know, for I am fond of it as well. But in France they take a different view of the Ancient Houses than in Britain; and Beauxbatons would not mistreat you, I think. Whatever else you imagine of me, I swear that if you asked me to see you safely to Beauxbatons, I would do all in my power to convey you there.’

‘I can’t just –’ Hermione said.

‘But you can, Miss Granger.’ Now the pale blue eyes watched her intently. ‘Whatever you wish to make of your life, you cannot attain it at Hogwarts, not any more. This place is ruined for you now, even leaving aside all other threats. Simply ask Harry Potter to command you to go to Beauxbatons and live out your life in peace. If you stay here, he is your master in the eyes of Britain and its laws!’

She hadn’t even been thinking about that, it paled so much in comparison to being eaten by Dementors; it had been important to her before, but now it all seemed childish, unimportant, pointless, so why were her eyes burning?

‘And if that fails to move you, Miss Granger, consider also that Mr Potter has, just today at lunchtime, threatened Lucius Malfoy, Albus Dumbledore, and the entire Wizengamot because he cannot think sensibly when something threatens to take you from him. Are you not frightened of what he will do next?’

It made sense. Terrible sense. Dreadful awful sense.

It made too much sense –

She couldn’t have described it in words, what triggered the realization, unless it was the sheer pressure that the Defence Professor was exerting on her.

That if the Defence Professor was behind this whole thing – then Professor Quirrell had done it all just to get her out of the way of his plans for Harry.

Without any conscious decision, she shifted her weight to the other foot, her body moving away from the Defence Professor –

‘So you think I am the one responsible?’ said Professor Quirrell. His voice sounded a little sad as he said it, and her own heart almost stopped from hearing it. ‘I suppose I cannot blame you. I am the Defence Professor of Hogwarts, after all. But Miss Granger, even assuming that I am your enemy, common sense should still tell you to get away from me very quickly. You cannot use the Killing Curse, so the correct tactic is to Apparate away. I do not mind being the villain of your imagination if it makes matters clearer. Leave Hogwarts, and leave me to those who can handle me. I will arrange for the transportation to be through some family of good repute, and Mr Potter will know to blame me if you do not arrive safely.’

‘I –’ She was feeling cold, the night air chilling her skin, or maybe being chilled by it. ‘I’ve got to think about it –’

Professor Quirrell shook his head. ‘No, Miss Granger. Your departure will take time for me to arrange, and I have less time left than you may think. This decision may be painful for you, but it should not be ambiguous; much weighs in the balance of these scales, but not evenly. I must know tonight whether you intend to go.’

And if not –

Was the Defence Professor warning her deliberately? That if she didn’t run, he would strike again?

Why would it matter so much, what did Professor Quirrell want to do with Harry?

Hermione Granger, I shall be less subtle than is usual for a mysterious old wizard, and tell you outright that you cannot imagine how badly things could go if the events surrounding Harry Potter turn to ill.

The most powerful wizard in the world had told her that, when he was talking about how important it was that she not stop being Harry’s friend.

Hermione swallowed, she swayed a little where she stood, on the stone balcony of a magical castle. Suddenly the whole deadly absurdity of the situation seemed to rise up and grab her by the throat, that twelve-year-old girls shouldn’t be in danger, shouldn’t be thinking about such things, that Mum would want her to run away and her father would have a heart attack if he even knew she was being faced with the question.

And she knew, then, as Harry and Dumbledore had both tried to warn her, that everything she’d ever thought about being a heroine had been mistaken. That there wasn’t really any such thing as heroes, outside of stories. There was just horrible danger, and being arrested by Aurors and put in cells next to Dementors, pain and fear and –

‘Miss Granger?’ said the Defence Professor.

She said nothing. All the words were blocked in her throat.

‘I need a decision, Miss Granger.’

She kept her jaw locked, didn’t let any words come out.

Finally the Defence Professor sighed. Slowly the white light failed, and slowly the door behind him swung open, so that he was once again a black silhouette against the opening. ‘Good night, Miss Granger,’ he said, and turned his back to her, and walked away into Hogwarts.

It took a while for her breathing to slow down again. Whatever had happened here tonight, it didn’t feel anything like victory. She’d fought so hard just to stop herself from saying Yes in the face of the Defence Professor’s pressure, and now she didn’t even know if she’d done the right thing.

When she walked back into the light herself (after exhaustion had overtaken everything and sleep was once more a possibility), she thought she heard it as she was within the doorway, from behind her and above her, a distant cawing cry.

But it wasn’t meant for her, she knew, so she started climbing up the stairs toward her dorm.

The other girls were probably asleep by now, and wouldn’t look at her, or look away –

She felt the tears start, and this time she didn’t stop them.

Harry stayed very quiet.

The Potions-making had come to a temporary pause, a space where no ingredients were added while the cauldron simmered for a time. ‘I spent most of my time looking at the stars,’ Professor Quirrell said, his voice quieter now. The Defence Professor had turned from the potion, staring at the white-illuminated walls of the room. ‘My remaining hope was the horcruxes I had hidden in the hopeless idiocy of my youth. Imbuing them into ancient lockets, instead of anonymous pebbles; guarding them beneath wells of poison in the centre of a lake of Inferi, instead of portkeying them into the sea. If someone found one of those, and penetrated their ridiculous protections … but that seemed like a distant hope. I was not sure I would ever be embodied again. Yet at least I was immortal. The worst of all fates had been averted, my great creation had done that much. I had little left to hope for, and little left to fear. I decided that I would not go insane, since there seemed to be no advantage in it. Instead, I gazed out at the stars and thought, as the Sun slowly diminished behind me. I reflected on the errors of my past life; they were many, in that hindsight. In my imagination I constructed powerful new rituals I might attempt, if I was free to use my magic once more, and yet confident of my immortality. I contemplated ancient riddles at greater length than before, for all that I had once thought myself patient. I knew that if I won free, I would be more powerful by far than in my previous life; but I mostly did not expect that to happen.’ Professor Quirrell turned back to the potion. ‘Nine years and four months after that night, a wandering adventurer named Quirinus Quirrell won past the protections guarding one of my earliest horcruxes. The rest you know. And now, boy, you may say what we both know you are thinking.’

‘Um,’ Harry said. ‘It doesn’t seem like a very smart thing to say –’

‘Indeed, Mr Potter. It is not a clever thing to say to me. Not even a little. Not in the slightest. But I know you’re thinking it, and you will go on thinking it and I will go on knowing that until you say it. So speak.’

‘So. Um. I realise that this is something that is more obvious in hindsight than in foresight, and I’m certainly not suggesting that you try to correct the error now, but if you are a Dark Lord and you happen to hear about a child who has been prophesied to defeat you, there is a certain spell which is unblockable, unstoppable, and works every single time on anything with a brain –’

‘Yes thank you Mr Potter that thought occurred to me several times over the next nine years.’ Professor Quirrell picked up another bellflower and began crumbling it in his bare fist. ‘I made that principle the centrepiece of my Battle Magic curriculum after I learned its centrality the hard way. It was not the first Rule on the younger Tom Riddle’s list. It is only by harsh experience that we learn which principles take priority over which other principles; as mere words they all sound equally persuasive. In retrospect it would have been better if I had sent Bellatrix to the Potters’ home in my place; but I had a Rule telling me that for such matters I must go myself and not try sending a trusted lieutenant. Yes, I considered the Killing Curse; but I wondered if casting the Killing Curse at an infant would somehow cause the curse to bounce off and hit me, thus fulfilling the prophecy. How was I to know?’

‘So use an axe, it’s hard to get a prophecy-fulfilling spell backfire out of an axe,’ Harry said and then shut up.

‘I decided the safest path was to try to fulfil the prophecy on my own terms,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Needless to say, the next time I hear a prophecy I do not like, I will tear it apart at every possible point of intervention, rather than trying to play along.’ Professor Quirrell was crushing a rose as though to squeeze the juice out of it, still using his bare fist. ‘And now everyone thinks the Boy-Who-Lived is somehow immune to the Killing Curse, even though Killing Curses do not ruin houses or leave burnt bodies behind them, because it has not occurred to them that Lord Voldemort would ever use any other spell.’

Harry again stayed quiet. It had occurred to Harry that there was another obvious way that Lord Voldemort could have avoided his mistake. Something that might perhaps be easier to see given a Muggle upbringing, instead of the wizarding way of looking at things.

Harry had not yet decided whether to tell Professor Quirrell about his thought; there were both pros and cons to pointing out that particular error.

After a time Professor Quirrell picked up the next Potions ingredient, a strand of what looked like unicorn hair. ‘I tell you this as a caution,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Do not expect me to be delayed another nine years, if you somehow destroy this body of mine. I set horcruxes in better places at once, and now even that is unnecessary. Thanks to you, I learned where to find the Resurrection Stone. The Resurrection Stone does not bring back the dead, of course; but it holds a more ancient magic than my own for projecting the seeming of a spirit. And since I am one who has defeated death, Cadmus’s Hallow acknowledged me its master, and answered all my will. I have now incorporated it into my great creation.’ Professor Quirrell smiled slightly. ‘I had many years earlier considered making that device a horcrux, but decided against it at the time, since I realized that the ring had magic of unknown nature … ah, such ironies does life play upon us. But I digress. You, boy, you brought that about, you freed my spirit to fly where it pleases and seduce the most opportune victim, by being too casual with your secrets. It is a catastrophe for any who oppose me, and you wrought it with one finger drawing wetness on a tea-saucer. This world will be a safer place for all, if you learn the rectitude that wizardborns absorb in childhood. And all thiss that I have jusst said iss the truth.’

Harry closed his eyes, and his own hand massaged his forehead; if he had seen it from the outside, it would have looked the mirror of Professor Quirrell in deep thought.

The problem of defeating Professor Quirrell was looking increasingly difficult, even by the standards of the sort of impossible problems that Harry had solved already. If communicating that difficulty was what Professor Quirrell was trying to do, he was succeeding. Harry was starting to seriously consider the possibility that it might be better to offer to rule Britain as Voldemort’s non-homicidal delegate, if Professor Quirrell himself would just agree to stop killing people all the time. Even mostly.

But that wasn’t likely to happen.

Harry stared at his hands, from where he had sat down upon the floor, feeling sadness shading over into despair. The Lord Voldemort who’d given Harry his dark side had spent that long thinking things over and reflecting on his own thought processes … and had emerged as the calm, clear-headed, and still homicidal Professor Quirrell.

Professor Quirrell added a pinch of golden hair to the potion of effulgence, and that reminded Harry that time was continuing to move; the locks of bright hair were rarer than the bellflowers.

‘I ask my second question,’ Harry said. ‘Tell me about the Philosopher’s Stone. Does it do anything besides making Transfigurations permanent? Is it possible to make more Stones, and why is that problem hard?’

Professor Quirrell was bent over the potion, and Harry could not see his face. ‘Very well, I shall tell you the Stone’s story as I have inferred it. The one and only power of the Stone is the imposition of permanency, to render a temporary form into a true and lasting substance – a power absolutely beyond ordinary spells. Conjurations such as the castle Hogwarts are maintained by a constant well of magic. Even Metamorphmagi cannot manifest golden fingernails and then trim them for sale. It is theorized that the Metamorphmagus curse merely rearranges the substance of their flesh, like a Muggle smith manipulates iron with hammer and tongs; and their body contains no gold. If Merlin himself could create gold from thin air, history does not record it. So the Stone, we can guess even before research, must be a very old thing indeed. In contrast, Nicholas Flamel has been known to the world for a mere six centuries. Tell me the obvious next question to ask, boy, if you wanted to trace the Stone’s history.’

‘Um,’ Harry said. He rubbed his forehead, concentrating. If the Stone was old, but the world had only known Nicholas Flamel for six centuries … ‘Was there some other very long-lived wizard who disappeared at around the same time Nicholas Flamel showed up?’

‘Close,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘You recall that six centuries ago there was a Dark Lady called undying, the sorceress Baba Yaga? She was said to be able to heal any wound in herself, to change shape into any form she pleased … she held the Stone of Permanency, obviously. And then one year Baba Yaga agreed to teach Battle Magic at Hogwarts, under an old and respected truce.’ Professor Quirrell looked … angry, a look such as Harry had rarely seen on him. ‘But she was not trusted, and so there was invoked a curse. Some curses are easier to cast when they bind yourself and others alike; Slytherin’s Parselmouth curse is an example of such. In this case, Baba Yaga’s signature, and signatures from every student and teacher of Hogwarts, were placed within an ancient device known as the Goblet of Fire. Baba Yaga swore not to shed a drop of students’ blood, nor take from the students anything that was theirs. In return, the students swore not to shed a drop of Baba Yaga’s blood, nor take from her anything that was hers. So they all signed, with the Goblet of Fire to witness it and punish the transgressor.’

Professor Quirrell picked up a new ingredient, a loose thread of gold wrapped around a pinch of foul-looking substance. ‘Entering her sixth year at Hogwarts, then, was a witch named Perenelle. And although Perenelle was new-come into the beauty of her youth, her heart was already blacker than Baba Yaga’s own –’

‘You’re calling her evil?’ Harry said, then realized he had just committed the fallacy of ad hominem tu quoque.

‘Hush, boy, I am telling the story. Where was I? Ah, yes, Perenelle, the beautiful and covetous. Perenelle seduced the Dark Lady over the months, with gentle touches and flirtations and the shy pretence of innocence. The Dark Lady’s heart was captured, and they became lovers. And then one night Perenelle whispered how she had heard of Baba Yaga’s shape-changing power and how this thought had inflamed her desires; thus Perenelle swayed Baba Yaga to come to her with the Stone in hand, to assume many guises in a single night, for their pleasures. Among other forms Perenelle bid Baba Yaga take the form of a man; and they lay together in the fashion of a man and a woman. But Perenelle had been a virgin until that night. And since they were all rather old-fashioned in those days, the Goblet of Fire accounted that as the shedding of Perenelle’s blood, and the taking of what was hers; thus Baba Yaga was tricked into being forsworn, and the Goblet rendered her defenceless. Then Perenelle killed the unsuspecting Baba Yaga as she slept in Perenelle’s bed, killed the Dark Lady who had loved her and come peacefully to Hogwarts under truce; and that was the end of the pact by which Dark Wizards and Witches taught Battle Magic at Hogwarts. For the next few centuries the Goblet of Fire was used to oversee pointless inter-school tournaments, and then it resided in a disused chamber at Beauxbatons, until I finally stole it.’ Professor Quirrell dropped a pale beige-pink twig into the cauldron, and its colour changed to white just as it touched the surface. ‘But I digress. Perenelle took the Stone from Baba Yaga, and assumed the guise and name of Nicholas Flamel. She also kept her identity as Perenelle, calling herself Flamel’s wife. The two have appeared together in public, but that might be done by any number of obvious methods.’

‘And the Stone’s manufacture?’ said Harry, his brain working to process all this. ‘I saw an alchemical recipe for it, in a book –’

‘Another lie. Perenelle was making it appear as though “Nicholas Flamel” had earned the right to live forever by completing a great magic that any could attempt. And she was giving others a false path to pursue, instead of seeking the one true Stone as Perenelle had sought Baba Yaga’s.’ Professor Quirrell looked rather sour. ‘It should come as no surprise that I spent years trying to master that false recipe. Next you will ask why I did not kidnap, torture, and kill Perenelle after I learned the truth.’

This had not in fact been a question that had come into Harry’s mind.

Professor Quirrell continued to speak. ‘The answer is that Perenelle had foreseen and forestalled the ambitions of Dark Wizards like myself. “Nicholas Flamel” publicly took Unbreakable Vows not to be coerced by any means into relinquishing his Stone – to guard immortality from the covetous, he claimed, as if that were a public service. I was afraid the Stone would be lost forever, if Perenelle died without saying where it was hidden, and her Vow prevented attempts at torture. Further, I had hopes of gaining Perenelle’s knowledge, if I could find the right strategy to extract it from her. Though Perenelle began with little lore of her own, she has held hostage the lives of wizards greater than herself, holding out dribs and drabs of healing in exchange for secrets, and small reversals of age in exchange for power. Perenelle does not condescend to bestow any real youth upon others – but if you hear of a wizard who lived, grey-bearded, to the age of two hundred and fifty, you may be sure that her hand was in play. By my own generation, the centuries had given Perenelle enough of an advantage that she could raise up Albus Dumbledore as a counterweight to the Dark Lord Grindelwald. When I appeared as Lord Voldemort, Perenelle raised up Dumbledore yet further, parcelling out another drop of her hoarded lore whenever Lord Voldemort seemed to gain an advantage. I felt like I ought to be able to figure out something clever to do with that situation, but I never did. I did not attack her directly, for I was not sure of my great creation; it was not impossible that I would some day need to go begging to her for a dollop of reversed age.’ Professor Quirrell dropped two bellflowers at once into the potion, and they seemed to merge as they touched the bubbling liquid. ‘But now I am sure of my creation, and so I have decided that the time has come to take the Stone by force.’

Harry hesitated. ‘I would like to hear you answer in Parseltongue, was all of that true?’

‘None of it is known to me to be false,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Telling a tale implies filling in certain gaps; I was not present to observe when Perenelle seduced Baba Yaga. The basics should be mostly correct, I think.’

Harry had noticed a trace of confusion. ‘Then I don’t understand why the Stone is here in Hogwarts. Wouldn’t the best defence just be hiding it under an anonymous rock in Greenland?’

‘Perhaps she respected my abilities as a particularly good finder,’ said the Defence Professor. He appeared focused on his cauldron as he dipped a bellflower into a jar of liquid labelled with the Potions symbol for rainwater.

We are very much alike, the Defence Professor and I, in some ways if not others. If I imagine what I’d do, given his problem …

‘Did you bluff everyone into believing you had some way of finding the Stone?’ Harry said aloud. ‘So that Perenelle would put it inside Hogwarts, where Dumbledore could guard it?’

The Defence Professor sighed, not looking up from the cauldron. ‘I suppose that stratagem would be futile to conceal from you. Yes, after I possessed Quirrell and returned, I implemented a strategy I had conceived while gazing at the stars. First I made sure to be accepted as Defence Professor at Hogwarts, for it would not do to have suspicions raised while I was still seeking employment. When that was done, I arranged for one of Perenelle’s curse-breaking expeditions to discover a falsified but credible inscription describing how the Crown of the Serpent could be used to seek out the Stone wherever it was hidden. Immediately after, before Perenelle could buy up the Crown, it was stolen; furthermore I left clear indications that the thief had possessed the power to speak to snakes. So Perenelle thought that I could infallibly find the Stone’s location, and that it needed a guardian powerful enough to defeat me. That is how the Stone came to be held in Hogwarts, in Dumbledore’s domain. Just as I intended, naturally, since I had already gained access to Hogwarts for the year. I think that is all of this that concerns you, if I speak not of future plans.’

Harry frowned. Professor Quirrell should not have told him that. Unless the strategy had somehow become irrelevant to any future deception of Perenelle … ? Or unless, by answering so quickly, the Defence Professor had hoped to have people conclude that it was a double-bluff, and that the Crown of the Serpent really could find the Stone …

Harry decided not to question this answer in Parseltongue.

Another lock of bright hair, seeming white but not with age, was gently dribbled into the cauldron, again reminding Harry that they were on a time limit. Harry considered, but he couldn’t see any further path to pursue this line of questioning; there was no known way to manufacture more Philosopher’s Stones and no obvious way to invent such, which was probably the objectively worst news Harry had heard all day.

Harry took a deep breath. ‘I ask my third question,’ Harry said. ‘What’s the truth behind this entire school year? All the plots you ran, all the plots you know about.’

‘Hm,’ said Professor Quirrell, dropping another bellflower into the potion, accompanied by a plant-shape like a tiny cross. ‘Let me see … the most shocking twist is that the Defence Professor turns out to be secretly Voldemort.’

‘Well, obviously,’ Harry said, with a good deal of self-directed bitterness.

‘Then where do you wish me to start?’

‘Why did you kill Hermione?’ The question just slipped out.

Professor Quirrell’s pale eyes glanced up from the potion, watched him intently. ‘One would think that should be evident – but I suppose I cannot blame you for distrusting what seems evident. To understand the object of an obscure plot, observe its consequences and ask who might have intended them. I killed Miss Granger to improve your position relative to that of Lucius Malfoy, since my plans did not call for him to have so much leverage over you. I admit I am impressed by how far you managed to parlay that opening.’

Harry unclenched his teeth, which took an effort. ‘That’s after your failed attempt to frame Hermione for the attempted murder of Draco and send her to Azkaban because of why? Because you didn’t like the influence she was having on me?’

‘Don’t be ridiculous,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘If I had only wished to remove Miss Granger, I would not have brought the Malfoys into it. I observed your game with Draco Malfoy and found it amusing, but I knew it could not continue for very long before Lucius learned and intervened; and then your folly would have brought you great trouble, for Lucius would not take it lightly. Had you just been able to lose during the Wizengamot trial, lose as I had taught you, then in only two more weeks, ironclad evidence would have shown that Lucius Malfoy, after discovering his son’s seeming perfidy, had Imperiused Professor Sprout into using the Blood-Cooling Charm on Mr Malfoy and casting the False Memory Charm on Miss Granger. Lucius would have been swept off the political gameboard, sent to exile if not Azkaban; Draco Malfoy would have inherited the wealth of House Malfoy, and your influence over him would have been unchallenged. Instead I had to abort that plot in mid-course. You managed to completely disrupt the real plan in the course of sacrificing double your entire fortune, by giving Lucius Malfoy the perfect opportunity to prove his true concern for his son. You have an incredible anti-talent for meddling, I must say.’

‘And you also thought,’ Harry said, even with his dark side’s patterns he had to work to keep his voice level and cool, ‘that two weeks in Azkaban would improve Miss Granger’s disposition, and get her to stop being a bad influence on me. So you somehow arranged for there to be newspaper stories calling for her to be sent to Azkaban, rather than some other penalty.’

Professor Quirrell’s lips drew up in a thin smile. ‘Good catch, boy. Yes, I thought she might serve as your Bellatrix. That particular outcome would also have provided you with a constant reminder of how much respect was due the law, and helped you develop appropriate attitudes toward the Ministry.’

‘Your plot was stupidly complicated and had no chance of working.’ Harry knew he ought to be more tactful, that he was engaging in more of what Professor Quirrell called folly, but in that instant he could not bring himself to care.

‘It was less complicated than Dumbledore’s plot to have the three armies tie in the Christmas Battle, and not much more complicated than my own plot to make you think Dumbledore had blackmailed Mr Zabini. The insight you are missing, Mr Potter, is that these were not plots that needed to succeed.’ Professor Quirrell continued to casually stir the potion, smiling. ‘There are plots that must succeed, where you keep the core idea as simple as possible and take every precaution. There are also plots where it is acceptable to fail, and with those you can indulge yourself, or test the limits of your ability to handle complications. It was not as if something going wrong with any of those plots would have killed me.’ Professor Quirrell was no longer smiling. ‘Our journey into Azkaban was of the first type, and I was less amused by your antics there.’

‘What exactly did you do to Hermione?’ Some part of Harry wondered at the evenness of his voice.

‘Obliviations and False Memory Charms. I could not trust anything else to go undetected by the Hogwarts wards and the scrutiny I knew her mind would undergo.’ A flicker of frustration crossed Professor Quirrell’s face. ‘Part of what you rightly call complication is because the first version of my plot did not go as planned, and I had to modify it. I came to Miss Granger in the hallways wearing the appearance of Professor Sprout, to offer her a conspiracy. My first attempt at suasion failed. I Obliviated her and tried again with a new presentation. The second bait failed. The third bait failed. The tenth bait failed. I was so frustrated that I began going through my entire library of guises, including those more appropriate to Mr Zabini. Still nothing worked. The child would not violate her childish code.’

‘You do not get to call her childish, Professor.’ Harry’s voice sounded strange in his own ears. ‘Her code worked. It prevented you from tricking her. The whole point of having deontological ethical injunctions is that arguments for violating them are often much less trustworthy than they look. You don’t get to criticize her rules when they worked exactly as intended.’ After they resurrected Hermione, Harry would tell her that Lord Voldemort himself hadn’t been able to tempt her into doing wrong, and that was why he’d killed her.

‘Fair enough, I suppose,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘There is a saying that even a stopped clock is right twice a day, and I do not think Miss Granger was actually being reasonable. Still, Rule Ten: one must not rant about the opposition’s unworthiness after they have foiled you. Regardless. After two full hours of failed attempts, I realized that I was being over-stubborn, and that I did not need Miss Granger to carry out the exact part I had planned for her. I gave up on my original intent, and instead imbued Miss Granger with False Memories of watching Mr Malfoy plotting against her under circumstances that implied she should not tell you or the authorities. In the end it was Mr Malfoy who gave me the opening I needed, entirely by luck.’ Professor Quirrell dropped a bellflower and a scrap of parchment into the cauldron.

‘Why did the wards show the Defence Professor as having killed Hermione?’

‘I wore the mountain troll as a false tooth while Dumbledore was identifying me to the Hogwarts wards as the Defence Professor.’ A slight smile. ‘Other living weapons cannot be Transfigured; they will not survive the disenchantment for the requisite six hours to avoid being traced by Time-Turner. The fact that a mountain troll was used as a weapon of assassination was a clear sign that the assassin had needed a proxy weapon that could be Transfigured safely. Combined with the evidence of the wards, and Dumbledore’s own knowledge of how he had identified me to Hogwarts, you could have deduced who was responsible – in theory. However, experience has taught me that such puzzles are far harder to solve when you do not already know the solution, and I considered it a small risk. Ah, that reminds me, I have a question of my own.’ The Defence Professor was now giving Harry an intent look. ‘What gave me away at the last, in the corridor outside these chambers?’

Harry put aside other emotions to weigh up the cost and benefit of answering honestly, came to the conclusion that the Defence Professor was giving away far more information than he was getting (why?) and that it was best not to give the appearance of reticence. ‘The main thing,’ Harry said, ‘was that it was too improbable that everyone had arrived in Dumbledore’s corridor at the same time. I tried running with the hypothesis that everyone who arrived had to be coordinated, including you.’

‘But I had said that I was following Snape,’ the Defence Professor said. ‘Was that not plausible?’

‘It was, but …’ Harry said. ‘Um. The laws governing what constitutes a good explanation don’t talk about plausible excuses you hear afterwards. They talk about the probabilities we assign in advance. That’s why science makes people do advance predictions, instead of trusting explanations people come up with afterwards. And I wouldn’t have predicted in advance for you to follow Snape and show up like that. Even if I’d known in advance that you could put a trace on Snape’s wand, I wouldn’t have expected you to do it and follow him just then. Since your explanation didn’t make me feel like I would have predicted the outcome in advance, it remained an improbability. I started to wonder if Sprout’s mastermind might have arranged for you to show up, too. And then I realised the note to myself hadn’t really come from future-me, and that gave it away completely.’

‘Ah,’ said the Defence Professor, and sighed. ‘Well, I think it is all working out for the best. You did understand only too late; and there would have been inconveniences as well as benefits to you remaining unaware.’

‘What on Earth were you trying to do? The reason I was trying so hard to figure it out was that the whole thing was just so weird.’

‘That should have pointed at Dumbledore, not myself,’ said Professor Quirrell, and frowned. ‘The fact is that Miss Greengrass was not supposed to arrive in that corridor for several hours … though I suppose, since I did have Mr Malfoy give her the clue I assigned her, it is not too surprising they banded together. Had Mr Nott arrived seemingly alone, events would have played out less farcically. But I consider myself a specialist in battlefield control magics, and I was able to ensure that the fight went as I wished. I suppose it did end up looking a bit ridiculous.’ The Defence Professor dropped a peach slice and a bellflower into the cauldron. ‘But let us defer our discussion of the Mirror until we reach it. Did you have any more questions concerning Miss Granger’s regrettable and hopefully temporary demise?’

‘Yes,’ Harry said in an even voice. ‘What did you do to the Weasley twins? Dumbledore thought – I mean, the school saw the Headmaster go to the Weasley twins after Hermione was arrested. Dumbledore thought you, as Voldemort, had wondered why Dumbledore had done so, and that you’d checked on the Weasley twins, found and took their map, and Obliviated them afterwards?’

‘Dumbledore was quite correct,’ Professor Quirrell said, shaking his head as though in wonderment. ‘He was also an utter fool to leave the Hogwarts Map in the possession of those two idiots. I had an unpleasant shock after I recovered the Map; it showed my name and yours correctly! The Weasley idiots had thought it a mere malfunction, especially after you received your Cloak and your Time-Turner. If Dumbledore had kept the Map himself – if the Weasleys had ever spoken of it to Dumbledore – but they did not, thankfully.’

Showed my name and yours correctly –

‘I would like to see that,’ Harry said.

Without taking his eyes from the cauldron, Professor Quirrell drew a folded parchment from within his robes, hissed at it ‘Show our surroundings’, and tossed the folded parchment toward Harry. It cut unerringly through the air, an increase of doom breathing on Harry’s senses as it moved toward him, and then it fluttered gently to Harry’s feet.

Harry picked up the parchment and unfolded it.

At first the parchment seemed blank. Then, as though an unseen pen were moving across it, the outline of walls and doors appeared, all drawn in handwritten lines. The writing outlined a series of chambers, most of them shown as empty; the last chamber in the series had a confused scribble in its centre, as though the Map were trying to indicate its own bewilderment; and the second-to-last chamber showed two names within, written in positions within the chamber corresponding to where Harry was sitting and Professor Quirrell was standing.

Tom M. Riddle.

Tom M. Riddle.

Harry gazed at the parchment, an unpleasant chill coming over him. It was one thing to hear Lord Voldemort claim that your name was Tom Riddle; it was another thing to find that Hogwarts’s magic agreed. ‘Did you tamper with this map to achieve this result, or did it appear before you by surprise?’

‘Was surprise,’ replied Professor Quirrell, with an overtone of hissing laughter. ‘No tricks.’

Harry folded the Map and threw it back in Professor Quirrell’s direction; some force caught it in mid-air before it reached the floor, and drew the Map back into Professor Quirrell’s robes.

The Defence Professor spoke. ‘I should also like to volunteer that Snape was guiding Miss Granger and her underlings toward bullies, and sometimes intervening to protect them.’

‘I knew that.’

‘Interesting,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Did Dumbledore also learn of this? Answer in Parseltongue.’

‘Not so far as I know,’ hissed Harry.

‘Fascinating,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘You may be interested to know this as well: Potions-maker had to work in secret because his plot opposed schoolmaster’s plot.’

Harry thought about this, while Professor Quirrell blew on the potion as though to cool it, though the fire still burned under the cauldron; then added a pinch of dirt and a drop of water and a bellflower. ‘Please explain,’ Harry said.

‘Has it never occurred to you to wonder why Dumbledore chose Severus Snape as the Head of House Slytherin? To say that it was a cover for his work as Dumbledore’s spy explains nothing. Snape could have been a Potions Master only, and not the Head of Slytherin at all. Snape could have been made Keeper of Grounds and Keys, if he needed to stay within Hogwarts! Why the Head of House Slytherin? Surely it occurred to you that this could not have good effects upon the Slytherins, according to Dumbledore’s moral pretences?’

The thought hadn’t occurred to Harry in exactly those terms, no … ‘I wondered something like it. I didn’t put the dilemma in that precise form.’

‘And now that you have, is the solution obvious?’

‘No,’ Harry said.

‘Disappointing. You have not learned enough cynicism, you have not grasped the flexibility of what moralists call morality. To fathom a plot, look at the consequences and ask if they might be intended. Dumbledore was deliberately sabotaging Slytherin House – don’t give me that look, boy, I am sspeaking truth. During the last Wizarding War, Slytherins filled out my ranks of underlings, and other Slytherins in the Wizengamot supported me. Look at it from Dumbledore’s perspective, and remember that he has no native understanding of Slytherin’s ways. Think of Dumbledore becoming increasingly sad over this Hogwarts House that seems the source of so much ill-doing. And then behold, Dumbledore puts in as Head of Slytherin the person of Snape. Snape! Severus Snape! A man who would teach his House neither cunning nor ambition, a man who would impose lax discipline and make its children weak! A man who would offend students of other Houses, who would ruin Slytherin’s name among them! A man whose surname was unknown in magical Britain and certainly not noble, who went about half in rags! Do you think Dumbledore ignorant of the consequence? When Dumbledore was the one who brought it about, and had motive to bring it about? I expect Dumbledore told himself that more lives would be saved during the next Wizarding War if Voldemort’s future Death Eaters were weakened.’ Professor Quirrell dropped into the cauldron a chip of ice, slowly melting as it touched the surface froth. ‘Continue the process long enough, and no child would want to go to Slytherin. The House would be retired, and if the Hat kept calling the name, it would become a mark of ignominy among children who would afterwards be distributed among the other three Houses. From that day on, Hogwarts would have three upstanding Houses of courage and scholarship and industry, with no House of Bad Children added to the mix; just as if the three Founders of Hogwarts had been wise enough in the beginning to refuse Salazar Slytherin their company. That, I expect, was Dumbledore’s intended end-game; a short-term sacrifice for the greater good.’ Professor Quirrell smiled sardonically. ‘And Lucius let it all happen without protest or even, I expect, noticing that anything was going awry. I fear that in my absence my former servants have been quite outmatched in this battle of wits.’

Harry was having a bit of trouble taking this in, but decided, after some thought, that now was not the time to try to work it out. Whether Lord Voldemort believed it was not decisive; Harry would have to evaluate this accusation on his own.

Professor Quirrell’s mention of his servants had reminded Harry of something else that he was … obliged, Harry supposed, to ask. The bad news was predictable. On any other day it would have been horrible. Today it would just wash out in the flood. ‘Bellatrix Black,’ Harry said. ‘What was the truth about her?’

‘She was broken inside before I ever met her,’ Professor Quirrell said. He picked up what looked like a white-grey rubber band and held it over the cauldron; as the rubber was held within the steam, it turned black. ‘Using Legilimency on her was a mistake. But that glimpse showed me how easy it would be to make her fall in love with me, so I did. Ever after she was the most faithful of all my servants, the only one I could almost trust. I had no intention of giving her what she wanted from me; so I commended her to the Lestrange brothers for their use, and the three of them were happy in their own special way.’

‘I doubt it,’ Harry’s mouth said, mostly on autopilot. ‘If that were true, Bellatrix wouldn’t have remembered who the Lestrange brothers were, when we found her in Azkaban.’

Professor Quirrell shrugged. ‘You may be right.’

‘What the hell were we actually doing there?’

‘Finding out where Bellatrix had put my wand. I had told the Death Eaters of my immortality, in the hope – now proven futile – that they would stay together for at least a few days if I appeared to die. Bellatrix’s instructions were to recover my wand from wherever my body had been slain; and take that wand to a certain graveyard where my spirit would appear before her.’

Harry swallowed. The image came to him of Bellatrix Black waiting, waiting, waiting at the graveyard, in increasing desperation … it was no wonder she hadn’t been thinking strategically when she attacked the Longbottom household. ‘What did you do with Bellatrix once she was out?’

‘Ssent her to a peaceful place to recover sstrength,’ Professor Quirrell said. A cold smile. ‘I had a use remaining for her, or rather a certain portion of her, and on my future plans I shall not answer questions.’

Harry breathed deeply, trying to maintain control. ‘Were there any other secret plots in this school year?’

‘Oh, a fair number, but not many more that concern you, not that I can think of offhand. The true reason I demanded to try to teach the Patronus Charm to first-years was to bring a Dementor before your own person, and then I arranged for your wand to fall where the Dementor could continue to drain you through it. Was no malice in it, only hopes that you would recover some of your true memories. That was also why I arranged for certain witches to pull you down from the air during your rooftop episode, so I could appear to save your life; just in case any suspicion fell on me during the Dementor incident I had scheduled for shortly after. Also no malice there. I arranged some of the attacks on Miss Granger’s group, so that the attacks could be defeated; I do rather dislike bullies. Think that is all secret plots concerning you from this school-year, unless I have forgotten something.’

Life lesson learned, said his Hufflepart. Try to resist the temptation to randomly meddle in other people’s lives. Like, you know, Padma Patil’s life. If you don’t want to end up like this, that is.

It still hadn’t answered the most puzzling question, and Harry wasn’t sure that asking it would be wise. If, somehow, Lord Voldemort had managed not to think of it, and then Professor Quirrell had still managed not to think of it during nine years of contemplation, then it wasn’t wise to say … or maybe it was; the agonies of the Wizarding War had not been good for Britain.

Harry decided, and spoke. ‘One thing that did confuse me was why the Wizarding War lasted so long,’ Harry ventured. ‘I mean, maybe I’m underestimating the difficulties that were facing Lord Voldemort –’

‘You want to know why I did not Imperius some of the stronger wizards who could Imperius others, slay the very strongest wizards who could have resisted my Imperius, and take over the Ministry in, oh, perhaps three days.’

Harry nodded silently.

Professor Quirrell looked contemplative; his hand was sifting grass clippings into the cauldron, bit by bit. That ingredient, if Harry remembered correctly, was something like four-fifths towards the end of the recipe.

‘I wondered that myself,’ the Defence Professor said finally, ‘when I heard Trelawney’s prophecy from Snape, and I contemplated the past as well as the future. If you had asked my past self why he did not use the Imperius, he would have spoken of the need to be seen to rule, to openly command the Ministry bureaucracy, before it was time to turn his eyes outward to other countries. He would have remarked on how a quick and silent victory might bring challenges later. He would have remarked on the obstacle presented by Dumbledore and his incredible defensive prowess. And he would have had similar excuses for every other quick path he considered. Somehow it was never the right time to bring my plans to their final phase, there was always one more thing to do first. Then I heard the prophecy and I knew that it was time, for Time itself was taking notice of me. That the span for hesitation was done. And I looked back, and realised somehow this had been going on for years. I think …’ The occasional bit of grass was still dropping down from his hand, but Professor Quirrell did not seem to pay it any mind. ‘I thought, when I was contemplating my past beneath the starlight, that I had become too accustomed to playing against Dumbledore. Dumbledore was intelligent, he tried diligently to be cunning, he did not wait for me to strike but presented me with surprises. He made bizarre moves that played out in fascinating and unpredictable ways. In retrospect, there were many obvious plans for destroying Dumbledore; but I think some part of me did not want to go back to playing solitaire instead of chess. It was when I had the prospect of creating another Tom Riddle to plot against, someone even more worthy than Dumbledore, that I was first willing to contemplate the end of my war. Yes, in retrospect that sounds stupid, but sometimes our emotions are more foolish than we can bring our reason to admit. I would never have espoused such a policy deliberately. It would have violated Rules Nine, Sixteen, Twenty, and Twenty-two and that is too much even if you are enjoying yourself. But to repeatedly decide that there was one more thing left to be done, one more advantage left to be gained, one more piece that I simply had to move into place, before abandoning an enjoyable time in my life and moving on to the more tedious rule of Britain … well, even I am not immune to a mistake like that, if I do not realize that I am making it.’

And that was when Harry knew what was going to happen at the end of this, after the Philosopher’s Stone had been retrieved.

At the end of this, Professor Quirrell was going to kill him.

Professor Quirrell didn’t want to kill him. It was possible that Harry was the only person in the world against whom Professor Quirrell wouldn’t be able to use a Killing Curse. But Professor Quirrell thought he had to do it, for whatever reason.

That was why Professor Quirrell had decided that it was necessary to brew the potion of effulgence the long way. That was why Professor Quirrell had been so easily negotiated into answering these questions, into finally talking about his life with someone who might understand. Just like Lord Voldemort had delayed the end of the Wizarding War to play longer against Dumbledore.

Harry couldn’t exactly recall what Professor Quirrell had said earlier about not killing Harry. It hadn’t been anything straightforward along the lines of I am absolutely not planning to kill you in any way, shape, or form unless you positively insist on doing something stupid. Harry had been reluctant himself to push the promise too far and insist on unambiguous terms because Harry had already known that he would need to neutralize Lord Voldemort and had expected more precise language to reveal that fact, if they tried to exchange truly binding promises. So there certainly would have been loopholes, whatever had been said.

There was no particular shock to the realization, just an increased sense of urgency; some part of Harry had already known this, and had simply been waiting for an excuse to make it known to deliberation. There had been too many things said here that Professor Quirrell would not reveal to anyone with an expected lifespan measured in more than hours. The overwhelming isolation and loneliness of the life Professor Quirrell had described might explain why he was willing to violate his Rules and talk with Harry, given that Harry was going to die soon and that the world did not actually work like a play where the villain disclosing his plans would always fail to kill the hero afterwards. But Harry’s death certainly had to be in those future plans somewhere.

Harry swallowed, controlling his breathing. Professor Quirrell had just added a tuft of horsehair to the potion of effulgence, and that was very late in the potion, if Harry remembered correctly. There weren’t many bellflowers left in the heap to be added, either.

It was probably time to stop worrying so much about risk and play this conversation less conservatively, all things considered.

‘If I point out one of Lord Voldemort’s mistakes,’ Harry said, ‘does he punish me for it?’

Professor Quirrell lifted his eyebrows. ‘Not if the mistake is a real one. I do not suggest that you moralise at me. But I would not curse the bearer of bad news, nor the subordinate who makes an honest attempt to point out a problem. Even as Lord Voldemort I could never bring myself to that stupidity. Of course, there were some fools who mistook my policy for weakness, who tried to thrust themselves forward by pushing me down in their public counsel, thinking me obliged to tolerate it as criticism.’ Professor Quirrell smiled reminiscently. ‘The Death Eaters were better off without them, and I do not advise you make the same mistake.’

Harry nodded, a slight shiver going through him. ‘Um, when you told me about what happened in Godric’s Hollow, on Halloween night, in 1981 I mean, um … I thought I saw another flaw in your reasoning. A way you could have avoided disaster. But, um, I think you have a blind spot, a class of strategies you don’t consider, so you didn’t see it even afterwards –’

‘I hope you are not about to say anything stupid along the lines of “don’t try to kill people”,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘I shall be unhappy if that is the case.’

‘Not values difference. True mistake, given your goals. Will you hurt me, if I act the part of the teacher toward you, and teach lesson? Or if mistake is simple and obviouss, and makes you feel stupid?’

‘No,’ hissed Professor Quirrell. ‘Not if lesson is true.’

Harry swallowed. ‘Um. Why didn’t you test the horcrux system before you actually had to use it?’

‘Test it?’ said Professor Quirrell. He looked up from the brewing potion, and indignation came into his voice. ‘What do you mean, test it?’

‘Why didn’t you test if the horcrux system was working correctly, before you needed it on Halloween?’

Professor Quirrell looked disgusted. ‘You ridiculous – I didn’t want to die, Mr Potter, and that was the only way to test my great creation! What good would it have done to risk my life sooner rather than later? How would I have been better off?’

Harry swallowed a lump in his throat. ‘There wass way for you to tesst your horcrux ssysstem without dying. The general lesson is important. Do you see it now?’

‘No,’ Professor Quirrell said after a while. The Defence Professor gently crumbled one of the last bellflowers together with a strand of long blonde hair and then dropped it into the potion, which was bubbling brighter, now. Only two more bellflowers remained on the Potions table. ‘And I do hope your lesson is a sensible one, for your sake.’

‘Suppose, Professor, that I learned how to cast the improved horcrux spell and I was willing to use it. What would I do with it?’

Professor Quirrell answered at once. ‘You would find some person whom you found morally abhorrent and whose death you could convince yourself would save other lives, and murder them to create a horcrux.’

‘And then what?’

‘Make more horcruxes,’ said the Defence Professor. He picked up a jar of what looked like dragon scales.

‘Before that,’ Harry said.

After a time the Defence Professor shook his head. ‘I still do not see it, and you will cease this game and tell me.’

‘I would make horcruxes for my friends. If you’d ever really cared about one single other person in the entire world, if there’d been just one person who gave your immortality meaning, someone that you wanted to live forever with you –’ Harry’s throat choked. ‘Then, then the idea of making a horcrux for someone else wouldn’t have been such a counterintuitive thought.’ Harry was blinking hard. ‘You have a blind spot around strategies that involve doing nice things for other people, to the point where it stops you from achieving your selfish values. You think … it’s not your style, I suppose. That … particular part of your self-image … is what cost you those nine years.’

The dropper of mint oil that the Defence Professor was holding added liquid to the cauldron, drip by drip.

‘I see …’ the Defence Professor said slowly. ‘I see. I should have taught Rabastan the advanced horcrux ritual, and forced him to test the invention. Yes, that is supremely obvious in retrospect. For that matter, I could have ordered Rabastan to try marking himself onto some disposable infant, to see what happened, before I took myself to Godric’s Hollow to create you.’ Professor Quirrell shook his head bemusedly. ‘Well. I am glad I am realizing this now and not ten years earlier; I had enough to chide myself for at that time.’

‘You don’t see nice ways to do the things you want to do,’ Harry said. His ears heard a note of desperation in his own voice. ‘Even when a nice strategy would be more effective you don’t see it because you have a self-image of not being nice.’

‘That is a fair observation,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Indeed, now that you have pointed it out, I have just now thought of some nice things I can do this very day, to further my agenda.’

Harry just looked at him.

Professor Quirrell was smiling. ‘Your lesson is a good one, Mr Potter. From now on, until I learn the trick of it, I shall keep diligent watch for cunning strategies that involve doing kindnesses for other people. Go and practise acts of goodwill, perhaps, until my mind goes there easily.’

Cold chills ran down Harry’s spine.

Professor Quirrell had said this without the slightest visible hesitation.

Lord Voldemort was absolutely certain that he could never be redeemed. He wasn’t the tiniest bit afraid of it happening to him.

The second-to-last bellflower was dropped into the potion, gently.

‘Any other valuable lessons you would like to teach to Lord Voldemort, boy?’ said Professor Quirrell. He was looking up from the potion, and grinning as though he knew exactly what Harry was thinking.

‘Yes,’ Harry said, his voice almost breaking. ‘If your goal is to obtain happiness, then doing nice things for other people feels better than doing them for yourself –’

‘Do you really think I never thought of that, boy?’ The smile had vanished. ‘Do you think I am stupid? After graduating Hogwarts I wandered the world for years, before I returned to Britain as Lord Voldemort. I have put on more faces than I bothered counting. Do you think I never tried to play the hero, just to see how it would feel? Have you come across the name of Alexander Chernyshov? Under that guise, I sought out a forlorn hellhole ruled over by a Dark Wizard, and I freed the wretched inhabitants from their bondage. They wept tears of gratitude for me. It did not feel like anything in particular. I even stayed about and killed the next five Dark Wizards to try taking command of the place. I spent my own Galleons – well, not my own Galleons, but the same principle applies – to prettify their little country and introduce a semblance of order. They grovelled all the more, and named one in three of their infants Alexander. I still felt nothing, so I nodded to myself, wrote it off as a fair try, and went upon my way.’

‘And were you happy as Lord Voldemort, then?’ Harry’s voice had risen, grown wild.

Professor Quirrell hesitated, then shrugged. ‘It appears you already know the answer to that.’

‘Then why? Why be Voldemort if it doesn’t even make you happy?’ Harry’s voice broke. ‘I’m you, I’m based on you, so I know that Professor Quirrell isn’t just a mask! I know he’s somebody you really could have been! Why not just stay that way? Take your curse off the Defence Position and just stay here, use the Philosopher’s Stone to take David Monroe’s shape and let the real Quirinus Quirrell go free, if you say you’ll stop killing people I’ll swear not to tell anyone who you really are, just be Professor Quirrell, for always! Your students would appreciate you, my father’s students appreciate him –’

Professor Quirrell was chuckling over the cauldron as he stirred it. ‘There are perhaps fifteen thousand wizards living in magical Britain, child. There used to be more. There’s a reason they’re afraid to speak my name. You’d forgive me that because you liked my Battle Magic lessons?’

Seconded, said Harry’s inner Hufflepuff. Seriously, what the hell?

Harry kept his head raised, though it was trembling. ‘It’s not my place to forgive anything you’ve done. But it’s better than another war.’

‘Ha,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘If you ever find a Time-Turner that goes back forty years and can alter history, be sure to tell Dumbledore that before he rejects Tom Riddle’s application for the Defence position. But alas, I fear that Professor Riddle would not have found lasting happiness in Hogwarts.’

‘Why not?’

‘Because I still would’ve been surrounded by idiots, and I wouldn’t have been able to kill them,’ Professor Quirrell said mildly. ‘Killing idiots is my great joy in life, and I’ll thank you not to speak ill of it until you’ve tried it for yourself.’

‘There’s something that would make you happier than that,’ Harry said, his voice breaking again. ‘There has to be.’

‘Why?’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Is this some scientific law I have not yet encountered? Tell me of it.’

Harry opened his mouth, but couldn’t find any words, there had to be something had to be something if he could just find the right thing to say –

‘And you,’ said Professor Quirrell, ‘have no right to speak of happiness either. Happiness is not what you hold precious above all. You decided that in the beginning, all the way back in the beginning of this year, when the Sorting Hat offered you Hufflepuff. Which I know about, because I received a similar offer and warning all those years ago, and I refused it just as you did. Beyond this there is little more to say, between Tom Riddles.’ The Defence Professor turned back to the cauldron.

Before Harry could think of any way to reply, Professor Quirrell dropped in the last bellflower, and a burst of glowing bubbles boiled up from the cauldron.

‘I believe we are done here,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘If you have further questions, they must wait.’

Harry shakily rose to his feet; even as Professor Quirrell took up the cauldron and poured out a ridiculously huge volume of effulgent liquid, more than seemed like it could fit in a dozen cauldrons, onto the purple fire that guarded the doorway.

The purple fire winked out.

‘Now for the Mirror,’ said Professor Quirrell, and he drew forth the Cloak of Invisibility from his robes, and floated it to drop before Harry’s shoes.

Harry put on the Cloak of Invisibility, at Professor Quirrell’s orders, to sstop the man who sshall believe himsself to be sschoolmasster from sseeing you, as Professor Quirrell said in Parseltongue.

‘Wearing the Cloak or no, you will stand in range of the Mirror yourself,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘If a gush of lava comes forth, you will also burn. I feel that much symmetry should apply.’

Professor Quirrell pointed to a spot near the right of the door through which they’d entered the room, before the Mirror and well back of it. Harry, wearing the Cloak, went to where Professor Quirrell had pointed him, and did not argue. It was increasingly unclear to Harry whether both Riddles dying here would be a bad thing, even with hundreds of other student hostages at stake. For all of Harry’s good intentions, he’d mostly shown himself so far to be an idiot, and the returned Lord Voldemort was a threat to the entire world.

(Though either way, Harry couldn’t see Dumbledore doing the lava thing. Dumbledore was probably sufficiently angry at Voldemort to discard his usual restraint, but lava wouldn’t permanently stop an entity that Dumbledore believed to be a discorporate soul.)

Then Professor Quirrell pointed with his wand, and a shimmering circle appeared around where Harry was standing on the floor. This, Professor Quirrell said, would soon become a Greater Circle of Concealment, by which nothing within that circle could be heard or seen from the outside. Harry would not be able to make himself apparent to the false Dumbledore by taking off the Cloak, nor by shouting.

‘You will not cross this circle once it is active,’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘That would cause you to touch my magic, and while Confunded I might not remember how to halt the resonance that would destroy us both. And further, since I do not want you throwing shoes –’ Professor Quirrell made another gesture, and just within the Greater Circle of Concealment, a slight shimmer appeared in the air, a globe-shaped distortion. ‘Thiss barrier will explode if touched, by you or other material thing. The resonance might lash at me afterwards, but you would also be dead. Now tell me in Parseltongue that you do not intend to cross this circle or take off your Cloak or do anything at all impulsive or stupid. Tell you me you will wait quietly here, under the Cloak, until this is over.’

This Harry repeated back.

Then Professor Quirrell’s robes became black tinged with gold, such robes as Dumbledore might wear upon a formal occasion; and Professor Quirrell pointed his own wand at his head.

Professor Quirrell stayed motionless for a long time, still holding his wand to his head. His eyes were closed in concentration.

And then Professor Quirrell said, ‘Confundus.’

At once the expression of the man standing there changed; he blinked a few times as though confused, lowering his wand.

A deep weariness spread over the face Professor Quirrell had worn; without any visible change his eyes seemed older, the few lines in his face calling attention to themselves.

His lips were set in a sad smile.

Without any hurry, the man quietly walked over to the Mirror, as though he had all the time in the world.

He crossed into the Mirror’s range of reflection without anything happening, and stared into the surface.

What the man might be seeing there, Harry could not tell; to Harry it seemed that the flat, perfect surface still reflected the room behind it, like a portal to another place.

‘Ariana,’ breathed the man. ‘Mother, father. And you, my brother, it is done.’

The man stood still, as if listening.

‘Yes, done,’ the man said. ‘Voldemort came before this mirror, and was trapped by Merlin’s method. He is only one more sealed horror now.’

Again the listening stillness.

‘I would that I could obey you, my brother, but it is better this way.’ The man bowed his head. ‘He is denied his death, forever; that vengeance is terrible enough.’

Harry felt a twinge, watching this, a sense that this was not what Dumbledore would have said, it seemed more like a strawman, a shallow stereotype … but then this wasn’t the real Aberforth’s spirit either, this was who Professor Quirrell imagined Dumbledore imagined Aberforth was, and that doubly-reflected image of Aberforth wouldn’t notice anything amiss …

‘It is time to give back the Philosopher’s Stone,’ said the man who thought he was Dumbledore. ‘It must go back into Master Flamel’s keeping, now.’

Listening stillness.

‘No,’ said the man, ‘Master Flamel has kept it safe these many years from all who would seek immortality, and I think it will be safest in his hands … no, Aberforth, I do think his intentions are good.’

Harry couldn’t control the tension that was running through him like a live wire; he was having trouble breathing. Imperfect, Professor Quirrell’s Confundus Charm had been imperfect. The underlying personality of Professor Quirrell was leaking through and seeing the obvious question: why was it okay for Nicholas Flamel himself to have the Stone if immortality was so awful? Even if Professor Quirrell imagined Dumbledore was blind to the question, he hadn’t included a clause in the Confundus saying that Dumbledore’s image of Aberforth wouldn’t think of it; and all of this was ultimately a reflection of Professor Quirrell’s own mind, an image from within the intelligence of Tom Riddle …

‘Destroy it?’ said the man. ‘Maybe. I am not sure it can be destroyed, or Master Flamel would have done it long since. I think, many times, that he has regretted making it … Aberforth, I promised him, and we are not so ancient or so wise ourselves. The Philosopher’s Stone must go back into the keeping of the one who made it.’

And Harry’s breath stopped.

The man was holding an irregular chunk of scarlet glass in his left hand, the size perhaps of Harry’s thumb from fingernail to the first joint. The surface sheen of the scarlet glass made it seem wet; the appearance was of blood, suspended in time and made into a jagged surface.

‘Thank you, my brother,’ the man said quietly.

Is that what the Stone should look like? Does Professor Quirrell know what the true Stone should look like? Will the Mirror give back the real Stone under these conditions, or make an imitation and return that?

And then –

‘No, Ariana,’ the man said, smiling gently, ‘I fear I must go now. Be patient, my dearest, it will be soon enough that I join you in truth … why? Why, I am not sure why I must go … when I hold the Stone I am to step aside from the Mirror and wait for Master Flamel to contact me, but I am not sure why I need to step aside from the Mirror to do that …’ The man sighed. ‘Ah, I am getting old. It is well this dreadful war ended when it did. I suppose there is no harm if I speak to you for a time, my dearest, if you wish it so.’

A headache was starting behind Harry’s eyes; some part of Harry was trying to send a message about not having breathed in a while, but no one was listening. Imperfect, Professor Quirrell’s Confundus Charm had been imperfect, Professor Quirrell’s image of Dumbledore’s image of Ariana wanted to talk to Dumbledore, and maybe didn’t want to wait because Professor Quirrell knew on some level that there wasn’t really an afterlife, and the previously implanted impulse to leave after getting the Stone wasn’t standing up to Riddle-Ariana’s arguments …

And then Harry felt himself become very calm. He started breathing again.

Either way, there wasn’t much Harry could do about it. Professor Quirrell had stopped Harry from intervening; well, Professor Quirrell was welcome to reap the consequences of that decision. If the consequences caught Harry as well, so be it.

The man who thought he was Dumbledore was mostly nodding patiently, sometimes replying to his dearest sister. Sometimes the man cast an uneasy look to one side; as if feeling a strong impulse to go, but suppressing that impulse with the great patience and politeness and concern for his sister that Professor Quirrell imagined Albus Dumbledore having.

Harry saw it the instant the Confundus wore off, and the man’s expression changed, becoming again the face of Professor Quirrell.

And in the same instant the Mirror changed, no longer showing Harry the reflection of the room, showing instead the form of the real Albus Dumbledore, as though he were standing just behind the Mirror and visible through it.

The real Dumbledore’s face was set, and grim.

‘Hello, Tom,’ said Albus Dumbledore.

The grimness on Albus Dumbledore’s face lasted only an instant before giving way to bewilderment. ‘Quirinus? What –’

And then there was a pause.

‘Well,’ said Albus Dumbledore. ‘I do feel stupid.’

‘I should hope so,’ Professor Quirrell said easily; if he had been at all shocked himself at being caught, it did not show. A casual wave of his hand changed his robes back to a Professor’s clothing.

Dumbledore’s grimness had returned and redoubled. ‘There I am, searching so hard for Voldemort’s shade, never noticing that the Defence Professor of Hogwarts is a sickly, half-dead victim possessed by a spirit far more powerful than himself. I would call it senility, if so many others had not missed it as well.’

‘Quite,’ said Professor Quirrell. He lifted his eyebrows. ‘Really, am I that hard to recognise without the glowing red eyes?’

‘Oh, yes indeed,’ Albus Dumbledore said in level tones. ‘Your acting was perfect; I confess myself utterly deceived. Quirinus Quirrell seemed – what is the term I am looking for? Ah yes, that is the word. He seemed sane.’

Professor Quirrell chuckled; he looked for all the world as though the two of them were just having a casual conversation. ‘I never was insane, you know. Lord Voldemort was just another game for me, the same as Professor Quirrell.’

Albus Dumbledore did not look like he was enjoying a casual chat. ‘I thought you might say that. I regret to inform you, Tom, that anyone who can bring himself to act the part of Voldemort is Voldemort.’

‘Ah,’ said Professor Quirrell, raising an admonishing finger. ‘There is a loophole in that reasoning, old man. Anyone who acts the part of Voldemort must be what moralists call “evil”, on this we agree. But perhaps the real me is completely, utterly, irredeemably evil in an interestingly different fashion from what I was pretending with Voldemort –’

‘I find,’ Albus Dumbledore ground out, ‘that I do not care.’

‘Then you must think yourself to be rid of me very soon,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘How interesting. My immortal existence must depend on discovering what trap you have set, and finding a way to escape from it, as soon as possible.’ Professor Quirrell paused. ‘But let us pointlessly delay to talk of other matters first. How did you come to be waiting inside the Mirror? I thought you would be elsewhere.’

‘I am there,’ Albus Dumbledore said, ‘and also inside the Mirror, unfortunately for you. I have always been here, all along.’

‘Ah,’ said Professor Quirrell, and sighed. ‘I suppose my little distraction was for naught, then.’

And the rage of Albus Dumbledore was no longer leashed. ‘Distraction?’ roared Dumbledore, his sapphire eyes tight with fury. ‘You killed Master Flamel for a distraction?’

Professor Quirrell looked dismayed. ‘I am wounded by the injustice of your accusation. I did not kill the one you know as Flamel. I simply commanded another to do so.’

‘How could you? Even you, how could you? He was the library of all our lore! Secrets you have forever lost to wizardry!’

There was an edge to Professor Quirrell’s smile, now. ‘You know, I still do not comprehend how your twisted mind can consider it acceptable for Flamel to be immortal, but when I seek the same it makes me a monster.’

‘Master Flamel never descended into immortality! He –’ Dumbledore choked. ‘He only stayed awake past his evening, for our sakes, through his long, long day –’

‘I don’t know if you recall this,’ Professor Quirrell said, his voice airy, ‘but do you recall that day in your office with Tom Riddle? The one where I begged you, where I went down on my knees and begged you, to introduce me to Nicholas Flamel so that I could ask to become his apprentice, to some day make for myself the Philosopher’s Stone? That was my last attempt to be a good person, if you are curious. You told me no, and gave me a lecture on how disgraceful it was to be afraid of death. I went from your office in bitterness and in fury. I reasoned that if I was to be called evil in any case, just for not wanting to die, then I might as well be evil; and one month later I killed Abigail Myrtle to pursue immortality by other means. Even when I knew more of Flamel, I remained quite put out with your hypocrisy; and for that reason I tormented you and yours more than I otherwise would have done. I have often felt that you ought to know this, but we never had a chance to talk frankly.’

‘I decline,’ said Albus Dumbledore, whose gaze did not waver. ‘I do not accept the tiniest shred of responsibility for what you have become. That was all, entirely, you and your own decisions.’

‘I am not surprised to hear you say that,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Well, now I am curious as to what responsibilities you do accept. You have access to some unusual power of Divination; that much I deduced long ago. You made too many nonsensical moves, and the paths by which they worked out in your favour were too ridiculous. So tell me. Were you forewarned of the result, that night of All Hallow’s Eve when I was vanquished for a time?’

‘I knew,’ said Albus Dumbledore, his voice low and cold. ‘For that, I accept responsibility, which is something you will never understand.’

‘You arranged for Severus Snape to hear the Prophecy that he brought to me.’

‘I allowed it to happen,’ said Albus Dumbledore.

‘And there I was, all excited at having finally gained my own foreknowledge.’ Professor Quirrell shook his head as though in sadness. ‘So the great hero Dumbledore sacrificed his unwitting pawns, Lily and James Potter, merely to banish me for a few years.’

Albus Dumbledore’s eyes were like stones. ‘James and Lily would have gone willingly to the death, if they had known.’

‘And the little baby?’ Professor Quirrell said. ‘Somehow I doubt the Potters would have been so eager to leave him in the path of You-Know-Who.’

You could scarcely see the flinch. ‘The Boy-Who-Lived came out of it well enough. Tried to turn him into you, did you? Instead you turned yourself into a corpse, and Harry Potter became the wizard you should have been.’ Now there was something like the usual Dumbledore behind the half-moon glasses, a tiny twinkle in those eyes. ‘All of Tom Riddle’s icy brilliance, tamed to the service of James and Lily’s warmth and love. I wonder how you felt when you saw what Tom Riddle could have become, if he had grown up in a loving family?’

Professor Quirrell’s lips twitched. ‘I was surprised, even shocked, by the abyssal depths of Mr Potter’s naivete.’

‘I suppose the humour of the situation would be lost on you.’ It was then, finally, that Albus Dumbledore smiled. ‘How I laughed when I realised it! When I saw you had made a Good Voldemort to oppose the evil one – ah, how I laughed! I never had the steel for my role, but Harry Potter shall be more than equal to it, when he comes into his power.’ Albus Dumbledore’s smile disappeared. ‘Though I suppose Harry shall have to find some other Dark Lord to vanquish for it, since you will not be there.’

‘Ah, yes. That.’ Professor Quirrell made to walk away from the Mirror, and seemed to halt just before reaching the point where the Mirror would no longer have reflected him, if it had been reflecting him. ‘Interesting.’

Dumbledore’s smile was colder, now. ‘No, Tom. You are not going anywhere.’

Professor Quirrell nodded. ‘What have you done, exactly?’

‘You have refused death,’ said Dumbledore, ‘and if I destroyed your body, your spirit would only wander back, like a dumb animal that cannot understand it is being sent away. So I am sending you outside Time, to a frozen instant from which neither I nor any other can return you. Perhaps Harry Potter will be able to retrieve you someday, if prophecy speaks true. He may wish to discuss with you just who is at fault for the deaths of his parents. For you it will only be an instant – if you ever return at all. Either way, Tom, I wish you the best of it.’

‘Hm,’ said Professor Quirrell. The Defence Professor had paced past where Harry stood, watching mute and with something like horror, only to halt again at the other edge of the mirror. ‘As I suspected. You are using Merlin’s old method of sealing, what the tale of Topherius Chang names as the Process of the Timeless. If legend speaks true, not even you can stop the process, now that it has been in motion this long.’

‘Indeed,’ said Albus Dumbledore. But his eyes were suddenly wary.

And Harry, from where he stood just before and to the right of the door, waiting in silence and controlled terror, could feel it in the air; he could feel the sense of a presence gathering within the Mirror’s field. Something more alien than magic, everything about it incomprehensible except for the fact of its strangeness and the fact of its power. It had been slow but now it was waxing faster, that presence.

‘But you could still reverse the effect, if Chang’s account is true,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Most powers of the Mirror are double-sided, according to legend. So you could banish what is on the other side of the Mirror instead. Send yourself, instead of me, into that frozen instant. If you wanted to, that is.’

‘And why would I do that?’ Albus Dumbledore’s voice was tight. ‘I suppose you are going to tell me that you have taken hostages? That was futile, Tom, you fool! You utter fool! You should have known that I would give you nothing for any hostages you had taken.’

‘You always were one step too slow,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘Allow me to introduce you to my hostage.’

Another presence invaded the air around Harry, a crawling sensation all over his flesh as another Tom Riddle’s magic passed very close to his skin. The Cloak of Invisibility was torn away from him, and the shimmering black Cloak flew away from him, through the air.

Professor Quirrell caught it, and swiftly drew it over himself; in less than a second he had pulled down the Cloak’s hood over his head, and disappeared.

Albus Dumbledore staggered, as though some essential support had been removed from him.

‘Harry Potter,’ the Headmaster breathed. ‘What are you doing here?’

Harry stared at the image of Albus Dumbledore, on whose face utter shock and utter dismay were warring.

The guilt and the shame were too much, too much, hitting Harry all at once, and he could feel the incomprehensible presence around him rising to a peak. Harry knew without words that there was no time left, and that he was done.

‘It’s my fault,’ Harry said in a tiny voice, from whatever part of him had taken over his throat in the final extremity. ‘I was stupid. I’ve always been stupid. You mustn’t rescue me. Goodbye.’

‘Why, look at that,’ sang out Professor Quirrell’s voice from the empty air, ‘I don’t seem to have a reflection any more.’

‘No,’ said Albus Dumbledore. ‘No, no, No!’

Into the hand of the Albus Dumbledore flew from his sleeve his long, dark-grey wand, and in his other hand, as though from nowhere, appeared a short rod of dark stone.

Albus Dumbledore threw these both violently aside, just as the building sense of power rose to an unbearable peak, and then disappeared.

The Mirror returned to showing the ordinary reflection of a gold-lit room of white stone, without any trace of where Albus Dumbledore had been.

The two of them came into a dark, dank stone building. Dirty old stone doors swung open without being touched.

Before them lay marble slabs, rising up from bare ground, upon them names and dates. The tombstones were scattered in nothing like neat rows, and the rest of the graveyard ran wild.

The moon above was over three-quarters full, already seeming bright with night not fully fallen.

Harry had stopped walking upon seeing the graveyard. There was a blaring alarm in his brain saying to be anywhere other than here, but there weren’t any options for accomplishing that. So that alarm cried unanswered, even as behind Harry the stone doors of the mausoleum swung shut again and sealed themselves.

The Dark Lord came into the centre of the scattered graveyard. He stopped walking, and waved his wand above his head in a small circle.

There was a rumbling sound, and smoothly from the ground rose an altar, at least two metres wide and of black stone carved with grey sigils. And then surrounding the altar groaned up six dark-marble obelisks, regularly spaced, gleaming darkly beneath the fading twilight sky.

The unanswerable alarm in Harry’s brain grew louder.

‘This,’ said the Dark Lord in Professor Quirrell’s cadences, ‘is a workspace I made for myself, convenient to either Hogwarts or Hogsmeade.’ The Dark Lord flourished a hand at the altar. ‘That is where Miss Granger shall revive, and also where I shall be reborn into my true body. I shall remake myself first, of course. Magicss to revive girl-child eassier with true body.’ A strange snakish laughter accompanied these words. ‘Rest assured that though some aspects of girl-child’s resurrection shall be what others consider Dark, girl-child will not be harmed or made ugly by it. Shall still look like herself, mind shall be her own, nor shall I or mine harm her after.’

Harry’s tongue was dry and his mind was having trouble functioning. ‘Please, Professor, would you say in Parseltongue what is your real purpose in resurrecting Miss Granger?’

‘To restore to you girl-child friend’s counsel and restraint. To make sure she is part of the world for you to care about. That, boy, is truly the greater part of the reason I am doing this deed.’ Again snakish laughter accompanied these words, conveying sardonic awareness of some vast irony.

A small spark of hope kindled inside Harry, alongside the much greater note of confusion, and the fear that a perfect Occlumens could indeed lie in Parseltongue. Harry didn’t understand why the Dark Lord was doing this, if the next step was just to kill the Boy-Who-Lived or enslave him …

Maybe he’d just never understood Professor Quirrell at all, maybe somehow Harry’s model of Tom Riddle was just that wrong … maybe the Boy-Who-Lived would be Obliviated of the last day and dropped off somewhere with a confused Hermione Granger, while Lord Voldemort went on to conquer the world … ?

Hope flared up in Harry, but it was a confused hope that didn’t make any sense. It didn’t square with the Dark Lord who had mocked Dumbledore and laughed at his defeat. Harry couldn’t come up with any consistent account of Professor Quirrell’s motives that allowed for something like that.

I do not know what is meant to happen next.

The Dark Lord had moved forward to the altar. He knelt there, and seemed to reach deep into the stone of the altar itself, drawing forth a vial of liquid that looked black in the fading twilight.

When the Dark Lord spoke again his voice was clipped and precise. ‘Blood, blood, blood so wisely hidden,’ said the Dark Lord.

And the obelisks surrounding the altar began to speak, voices like a chanting chorus coming from the motionless stones, cadences older than Latin.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi.

The obelisks’ chant echoed after the end of each line, as if they were speaking out of synchrony with each other. The blood was poured from the vial, and it seemed to catch and hang over the altar, slowly expanding through the air, taking on a shape.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi (emoi).

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma mou emoi (emoi).

A tall form rested upon the altar, and even in the dimming twilight it looked too pale.

The Defence Professor reached his hand into his robe, and drew forth a small irregular chunk of red glass.

He placed that upon the tall pale body.

The Stone stayed there for a time, minutes at least. The irregular chunk of red glass did not glow, or flash, or give any other indication of power.

Then the Stone moved, just a little, turning slightly upon the body.

The Defence Professor took back the Stone into his robes, and prodded the tall form that lay motionless upon the altar, touching the eyes with his fingers, poking the chest with his wand.

He threw back his head, then, and laughed.

‘Incredible,’ said the Dark Lord, in the voice of the Defence Professor that Harry had known. ‘Fixed, it is fixed in form! A mere construct sustained by magic, become the true substance at the Stone’s touch! And yet I sensed nothing! Nothing! I feared I had been deceived, that I had obtained a false Stone, but the substance proves true to my every test!’ The Defence Professor tucked the red glass back into his robes. ‘That is eldritch even by my standards, I admit.’

Then the Defence Professor walked around the altar, five times he walked around it, chanting something too low for Harry to hear.

The Dark Lord placed his wand in the hand of the figure lying on the altar.

He placed his hands, both of them, over the body’s forehead.

The Dark Lord spoke. ‘Fal. Tor. Pan.’

Without any warning there was a flash like lightning that lit up the entire graveyard, and Harry staggered back a step, his hands involuntarily going to his forehead. It felt as if he had been shot there, or a wasp stung him, upon his scar.

The Defence Professor collapsed.

And the too-tall figure sat up upon the altar.

It swung around smoothly, and stood tall upon the ground, at least a head higher than a normal man. The form’s limbs were lean and pale, little-muscled but giving an impression of terrible strength.

Harry took another staggering step back, his hands still clasped to his scar. Though the distance between them was wide, Harry felt a sense of terrifying apprehension in the air, as though the sense of doom had always been been out of focus and had now clarified, concentrated into a physical pain in the scar on Harry’s forehead.

Was that what Voldemort was supposed to look like? The nose looked like, it looked like it had malfunctioned during the resurrection process –

The too-tall figure threw back his head and laughed, raising his hands and wand to look at them. The left hand opened wide and it was like a pale half-spider with four over-long legs, fingers caressing the wand held in the other hand. Leaves stirred up from the graveyard, approaching to dance around the too-tall figure, surrounding him and clothing him, reforming into a high-necked shirt and flowing robes; and Lord Voldemort was laughing. Exactly the mirthless laughter that Harry remembered coming from his own throat inside the Dementor’s nightmare, precise in tone and timbre.

Red eyes gleamed beneath the fading twilight, their pupils slitted like a cat’s.

The form that Voldemort had abandoned raised itself, quivering, from the ground; and in a voice that Harry could barely hear, Quirinus Quirrell gasped, ‘Free – oh, free –’

‘Stupefy,’ said the high cold voice of Voldemort, and Quirinus Quirrell was blasted down into the ground; then, with a wave of Voldemort’s other hand, Quirinus Quirrell was picked up and flung away from the altar.

Voldemort walked away from the altar, then turned and looked at Harry; and the pain in Harry’s scar flared at it.

‘Frightened, child?’ Voldemort hissed, like there was an undercurrent of Parseltongue even to the Dark Lord’s human speech. ‘Good. Place the girl on the altar, and break your Transfiguration. Iss time for me to revive her.’

Is this really going to happen? Are we really going to do this?

Harry swallowed, mastering his fear through that note of impossible hope amid the confusion, and walked over to the altar. Then Harry took off his left shoe, and his left sock, and took off the toe-ring that was Hermione Granger, the Transfigured shape identical to the toe-ring that had been given Harry as an emergency portkey. There was a twinge of regret in Harry for not having the real portkey now, but only a twinge; an inner-circle Death Eater would routinely put up boundaries against portkeys, if Severus had been right. Behind Harry, Voldemort laughed again in what sounded like surprised appreciation.

‘I need my wand to Finite her,’ Harry said aloud.

‘You do not.’ High the voice and cruel. ‘You learned to sustain a Transfiguration by touch alone, without further use of the wand. You can likewise break your own Transfiguration wandlessly, by commanding your sustaining magic to drain away. Do so now.’

Harry swallowed, and touched the toe-ring. He had to try three times, and clear his mind, before he could push his magic out of the toe-ring, as before he had learned to make a tiny stream of magic flow in.

The breaking of the spell went much more slowly that way than a Finite Incantatem, almost like the sped-up reverse of watching something being Transfigured. The toe-ring distorted, flowing together, expanding. Colours changed, textures changed.

Two-thirds of a dead girl lay strewn across the altar, on her side with one arm falling off the altar’s edge, the position in which the reversion had chanced to place her. No blood flowed now from the chewed stumps of her thighs. The dead girl wore Hermione Granger’s face, but twisted and pale. It was as Harry had seen before in the hospital’s back room, the image burned into his brain during thirty long minutes of Transfiguration, the image he had reproduced during four even longer hours to Transfigure the decoy. The dead girl was naked, for her clothes were not part of her, and had not been Transfigured.

The sight brought back flashbacks, of the hours spent in the infirmary room, of the nightmares afterwards, all of which Harry suppressed.

‘Go back,’ said Voldemort’s high voice. ‘This is my work, now.’

Harry swallowed, and retreated from the altar, to the mouth of the long corridor where he’d stood before. ‘Her body is, should be, around five Celsius, I cooled her so, so there wouldn’t be brain damage –’ Harry’s own voice was wavering in pitch. Is he really going to do this? Really? There had to be a catch and Harry just couldn’t see it. Voldemort had said that neither he nor any of his would harm Hermione, that her body and mind would be her own – why?

Voldemort walked forth to the altar once more, orienting the body before him with a wave of his hand to lie straight across the altar. The Dark Lord spoke with high monotone precision, ‘Flesh, flesh, flesh so wisely hidden.’

The obelisks began chanting once more.

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma hou emoi (emoi).

Apokatastethi, apokatastethi, apokatastethi to soma hou emoi (emoi).

New flesh flowed out of the stumps of the girl’s thighs, creeping forward like an ooze and solidifying.

The obelisks ceased chanting. A complete form lay naked upon the altar.

It didn’t look like Hermione. A Hermione Granger should be standing up and talking, she should have her Hogwarts uniform.

Voldemort raised a hand, then hissed, as though in annoyance. With a violent gesture, the robes around Quirinus Quirrell’s sleeping from were torn in half, his purple-and-green tie shredded, and his suit-jacket drawn from him to where Voldemort stood. Some part of Harry flinched, as if seeing the Dark Lord Voldemort attacking Professor Quirrell.

Voldemort plunged his hand deliberately into the suit jacket, which jerked as though something were being broken; then Voldemort shook out the suit jacket onto the ground beside him, emptying out the contents. Harry’s pouch fell from it, and his Time-Turner, and a broomstick, and Voldemort’s gun, and the Cloak, and a number of amulets and rings and stranger devices that Harry did not recognize.

And finally a chunk of red glass, which was laid upon Hermione Granger’s form, and allowed to stay there for a time.

Minutes passed. The Dark Lord donned an amulet from the heap of things beside the altar; also from the heap, Voldemort took four short wooden rods with straps upon them, and reached beneath his robes to attach them, it looked like they went on his upper arms and upper thighs. The Dark Lord rose into the air, moved left, right, up and down, seeming to wobble slightly at first; then his flight stabilized.

The chunk of red glass turned, slightly.

The Dark Lord Voldemort floated to the ground, and prodded Hermione Granger’s body with his wand.

‘There is an obstacle,’ hissed Voldemort.

In Harry’s mind the expectation of betrayal or other failure had already been so strong that the confirmation came only as a dull shock, not a sharp one. ‘What obstacle?’

‘Girl’s body is restored. Substance is repaired. But not magic, or life … this is body of dead Muggle.’ Voldemort turned from the altar, began to pace. ‘The full ritual would solve this. But that would require time … time and the blood of Granger’s enemy, and I do not think Draco Malfoy still qualifies, nor can I take my own blood unwillingly … foolish.’ Voldemort’s voice was a lower hiss. ‘Foolish, I should have foreseen this, and prepared. Her brain might awaken with an electrical shock, I know that much of Muggle medicine … but would her magic return to her? That I do not know, and I suspect if she awakens as a Muggle she will be a Muggle forever. Still, I can think of nothing better.’ The Dark Lord raised his wand –

‘Wait!’ Harry blurted, feeling hope return. She needs a spark of life and magic, just a spark to get her started …

Voldemort turned and looked at him. The snakelike face showed some slight degree of surprise.

‘Think I have something that might work,’ Harry hissed. ‘Needs wand. Have no intentions to use it against you.’ Harry said nothing about expecting his intentions wouldn’t change; he’d simply blurted out the idea fast enough that he hadn’t formed any specific intentions yet.

‘This,’ Voldemort hissed, ‘I desire to see.’ The Dark Lord reached into the heap of things by the altar, and picked up the wrapped form of Harry’s wand. It was thrown, gliding through the air and then dropping at Harry’s feet; and then the Dark Lord floated back, the heap of things moving smoothly backwards with him.

Harry unwrapped his wand, and moved forward.

We have our wand back, that’s step one, said the last voice, the voice of hope.

No part of Harry had any idea what step two might be, but it was still step one accomplished.

And Harry stood before the reformed body of Hermione Granger, who was still naked and dead, on a twilight-lit stone altar.

‘Lord Voldemort,’ Harry said, ‘I beg you, please give her some clothes. It might help me do this.’

‘Granted,’ hissed Voldemort. The pain in Harry’s scar flared as the naked girl’s body lifted into the air, then flared again as dead leaves danced around her and she was clothed in the seeming of a Hogwarts uniform, though the trim was red instead of blue. Hermione Granger’s hands folded over her chest, her legs straightened, and her body drifted back down.

Harry looked at her.

Focused on her, now that she looked human again.

She looks like she is sleeping, not dead. It took a conscious effort to look for breathing, fail to see it, and make the deduction. So far as naked perception was concerned … Hermione might as well be alive, right now.

That Hermione Granger would not approve of this situation, taken as a whole, seemed beyond question. But it didn’t mean that she would rather stay dead than be alive, other things being equal, though they might not be.

Because you wish to live, because my best guess is that you would wish to live …

Harry reached out his shaking left hand, and touched Hermione’s forehead. It was warm now, not the chill of five degrees Celsius; either Voldemort had increased her body temperature to normal, or the magic of the ritual had done it automatically. Which meant that Hermione’s brain was currently warm and without oxygen, come to think.

That did it, the sense of urgency rising in him.

Harry’s feet assumed the stance, his wand swung up to point at Hermione Granger’s dead body. The only thing wrong with Hermione’s body was that it was dead; everything else about that body was right, only one thing needed changing.

You don’t belong here, death.

‘Expecto,’ Harry shouted, feeling the magic and the life rise up into the Patronus Charm that was fuelled by both, ‘Patronum!’

The girl in the Hogwarts uniform was surrounded by a blazing aura of silver fire, as the Patronus was born inside her.

Harry staggered, as he felt a dip, a bite. Intuition or Tom Riddle’s memory told Harry that the life and magic that had just flowed into Hermione would never return to him, either one. It hadn’t been all his life or all his magic, not by a long shot, there hadn’t been time to expend that much, but whatever he’d just expended was gone forever.

And Hermione Granger was breathing, just like she was sleeping, rhythmic inhalations and exhalations. The twilight sky had dimmed further, and Harry could not see if colour was returning to her, but it should have been, it certainly should have been. She looked to be sleeping peacefully, and it wasn’t because being dead looked like sleeping, it was because she was asleep and her body was fine and nothing was hurting her while she slept.

Some part of Harry, that had somehow managed not to speak up earlier, quietly pointed out that they were still in a graveyard, the recently victorious Lord Voldemort was still in control of the situation, and that his guess about Hermione wanting to be alive was just a guess.

Harry was still smiling, as he slowly lowered his wand. The celebratory fireworks going off inside his mind were restrained, Harry wasn’t screaming and running around in little circles like Professor Flitwick, but that –

That –

That, Harry said aloud inside his mind, That is what I call Step Two.

‘Interesting,’ said the cold high voice. ‘Your Patronus draws upon your life as well as your magic … I guessed that much, for it was too powerful for a first-year to fuel with magic alone. And yet there must be more to the puzzle, since not just any life-fuelled spell would have done … was your happy thought the image of her returning to life? Was that all it took?’ Lord Voldemort was again toying with his wand, a dark interest in those red-slitted eyes. ‘I suspect I will feel quite stupid when I finally comprehend that spell, someday in my eternity. Now step away from the girl. There iss more work I intend to do, to give her besst chance of continued life.’

Harry stepped back, reluctantly, the sense of tension starting to return to him. He almost tripped over one haphazard grave marker, as the Dark Lord continued to walk forward.

Standing before the altar, the Dark Lord laid one finger upon Hermione Granger’s forehead.

Then the Dark Lord tapped his finger upon Hermione Granger’s forehead, and said, in a voice so low Harry almost did not hear, ‘Requiescus.’

Voldemort waved his hand at an obelisk, which began to rotate, turning itself to lay flat upon the ground, pointing outward. ‘Fascinating indeed,’ Voldemort hissed. ‘She is alive, and magical, and not another Tom Riddle as I feared you might have made her.’

The tension was rising again in Harry. He’d put his wand away into the back belt of his trousers, he did not want to remind Voldemort that he still had the wand on him. ‘What are you doing to her now?’

Another obelisk turned, lay flat upon the ground. ‘There is old, lost ritual to sacrifice magical creature, transfer magical nature to subject. Limitations are great. Transfer is temporary, only few hours. Subject sometimes dies when transfer wears off. But Stone will make permanent.’

Four obelisks lay flat upon the ground, evenly spaced; the other two obelisks had been floated away.

Voldemort began to reach into his own mouth, checked himself, hissed with annoyance again. He gestured at the sleeping mouth of Quirinus Quirrell, and from Quirrell’s mouth floated up two teeth, almost invisible in the falling night. One of these went to the pile of items, the other floated to before the altar.

Moments later, Harry cried out and took a step back.

Huge and misshapen, lumpy skin, legs thick as tree-trunks, a small head that looked like a coconut perched upon a boulder.

A mountain troll stood within the circle of obelisks, motionless as though asleep while standing.

‘What are you doing?’

Voldemort’s mouth was stretched in a wide smile; it looked horrible on him, like his face had too many teeth. ‘Shall sacrifice my fallback weapon, and girl-child shall gain troll’s power of regeneration. Transfiguration sickness is nothing before that, if perchance it was not fixed by previous ritual. And no knife shall slay girl-child, nor cutting curse, nor sickness take her.’

‘Why – why are you doing this?’ Harry’s voice shook.

‘Have not the tiniest intention of letting girl-child die again, after going to such lengths to resurrect her.’

Harry swallowed. ‘I’m very confused.’ Was Voldemort practising being nice? This hypothesis did not seem like a sufficient explanation.

‘Stay well back,’ Voldemort said coldly. ‘This ritual is Darker than the last.’ The Dark Lord began a new chant, softer syllables that seemed to seethe through the air like living things; and Harry, feeling a new surge of apprehension, stepped backwards.

Then Harry cried aloud, as pain flared again within his scar. The mountain troll crumbled in on itself, becoming ashes hanging in the air, then dust, and then the dust seemed to blow away without going anywhere; it was gone.

Hermione Granger slept on peacefully, whatever spell of repose Voldemort had cast on her being sufficient to the task.

‘Um,’ Harry said in a small voice. ‘Did it work?’

‘Diffindo.’

Harry stepped forward with a choked yell, and then halted, both as the stupidity of his motion caught up with him, and as the sudden cut that the Severing Charm had opened on Hermione’s leg closed almost as quickly as it had been made. In seconds there was only a light stain of blood on the surrounding flesh.

The Stone was laid again on Hermione, and after a time it turned. Voldemort laughed once more, as he passed his hand over her. ‘Marvellous.’

Then another tiny tooth was floating within the circle of obelisks; and an instant later, a unicorn stood where the troll had stood before, eyes dull and head lowered.

‘What?’ Harry said. ‘Why a unicorn?’

‘Power of unicorn’s blood to preserve life makes excellent combination with troll’s healing. Only Fiendfyre and Killing Curse shall girl-child fear, from this day.’ A flicker of snakish laughter. ‘Besides, had spare unicorn left over, might as well use.’

‘Unicorn’s blood has side effects-’

‘That is only when power of unicorn’s blood is stolen by another. This spell will make power of unicorn belong inside girl-child, as if she was always born that way.’

The grim chant and its seething words began again.

Harry watched, not understanding in the slightest.

Forget understanding, what am I seeing?

I’m seeing the Dark Lord Voldemort going to enormous lengths to resurrect Hermione Granger and keep her alive. It’s like he thinks that his own life depends on Hermione Granger being alive, somehow.

The confused parts of Harry looked around for a procedure to follow. Make a prediction based on your best current hypothesis was the first thought that came to mind, but it didn’t seem to lead anywhere. The plot of the story wasn’t going how it ought to, after the villain had won.

Again the blaze of pain in his scar, like a blow to Harry’s forehead. The unicorn swayed, and then disintegrated as the troll had done.

The Dark Lord laid the Stone upon Hermione’s form once more, clasping her hands around it.

Voldemort watched the unremarkable process for a time, then turned while the Stone still laid on her, making a high humming sound in his throat. ‘Ah, yes,’ hissed Voldemort. ‘That would be most appropriate. Do you still have the diary I gave you, boy? The diary of the famous scientist?’

Harry’s brain took a moment to place what Voldemort was talking about. It had been in Mary’s Room, in Mary’s Place, in October, that precious gift from a friend. The thought should have triggered a wave of awful sadness, for the Professor Quirrell that had been lost or never real; but there had been enough of that emotion already, and his brain had set it aside for now.

‘Yes,’ Harry said aloud. ‘I think it’s in my pouch, can I check?’ Harry knew it was in the pouch. He’d loaded it up with everything that he might possibly conceivably need, that he owned or had bought; everything that could have been a quest item.

From the heap of items by the altar, Harry’s mokeskin pouch was drawn out, tossed to Harry’s feet.

‘Roger Bacon’s diary,’ Harry said as he reached in a hand, and the diary appeared. Professor Quirrell had said that the diary would emerge unscathed from a fire, so Harry threw it toward Voldemort’s altar. Harry did not wince; there were more important things to worry about than polite treatment of books, even that one.

Voldemort picked up the diary, examining it, appearing quite absorbed.

Harry, as quietly and unobtrusively as he could, attached the pouch to his belt loop in back, where it wouldn’t be visible, near where Harry had put his wand.

Step three, the pouch.

‘Yes,’ Voldemort hissed as he flipped pages of the diary, ‘this will do quite well.’ The Stone moved slightly, and the Dark Lord’s other hand stored the Stone again within his robes.

‘What was your hidden purpose behind the diary?’ Harry said when the pouch was attached to his belt, and he’d put both of his empty hands where Voldemort could see them again. ‘I tried translating a little at the beginning, but it was going slowly –’ Actually, it had been excruciatingly slow and Harry had found other priorities.

‘Diary was exactly what it seemed, a gift meant to seduce you to my side.’ Voldemort made intricate gestures in the air with his wand, not even looking at what his hand was doing, as he held the diary in his other hand. For a moment Harry thought he could see a trail of darknes in the air, but the moonlight was too faint for certainty. ‘And now, my dear boy,’ Voldemort’s high voice was laced with grim amusement, as his wand briefly tapped Hermione Granger’s forehead with a casual gesture, ‘I make this diary into a far more precious gift, a sign of how much wisdom I have learned from you. For I would never want you to be deprived of Hermione Granger’s counsel and restraint, not ever while the stars yet live. Avadakedavra.’

The green bolt of the Killing Curse blazed out faster than Harry could possibly have cast the Patronus Charm, faster than he could possibly have moved, it was already over even as Harry cried out and went for his wand.

Quirinus Quirrell’s unconscious body did not even jerk, in death. The green light struck into it without other sign.

Darkness glowed in the air, anti-light in the trails that Voldemort had made before, and the Diary of Roger Bacon darkened as though corruption were creeping over it, even as a shiver appeared in the air around Hermione Granger’s form.

The pain in Harry’s scar flared overwhelmingly, like a brand driven into his forehead, it sent Harry dodging unthinkingly to one side as Tom Riddle’s reflexes took over.

And Voldemort was also screaming, shrieking as he dropped the diary to the ground, holding his own head and screaming.

Chance –

The last voice of hope said that, as Harry tried frantically to think, to understand. There wasn’t any point in trying to kill Voldemort now, it might only annoy him, weapons couldn’t kill him while any of his hundreds of horcruxes remained –

But it still seemed worth it to temporarily discarnate Voldemort, take the Stone and Hermione and run.

Harry’s right hand had already taken his wand. His left hand went around to his back, reached awkwardly into his pouch, began to make a silent sign, three English letters.

‘No!’ cried Voldemort. He’d dropped his hands from his head, was staring at Hermione’s body as though bewildered. ‘No, no!’

The item came up from Harry’s pouch into his hand, and Harry began to step forward as smoothly as he could, diminishing the range between them to what his brief trials had shown was doable.

‘My great creation –’ gasped Voldemort. His voice was high, sounding panicked. ‘Two different spirits cannot exist in the same world – it is gone, it is severed! A horcrux, I must make a horcrux at once –’ Voldemort’s gaze fell on Hermione Granger’s still-sleeping form, and he began to raise his wand in the air, executing the same gestures as before.

Harry raised his gun and pulled the trigger three times.

Even as Harry had raised the gun, he’d known he was making a mistake, his forebrain saw it and tried to stop his hand, but somehow the sick certainty didn’t propagate fast enough to prevent his finger from pulling the trigger –

The echo of the shots died away within the graveyard.

A fraction of a second before Harry had pulled the trigger, Voldemort had jabbed his wand downward, and a wide wall of dirt had shot up between them from the graveyard earth, intercepting all three bullets.

An instant after that, pain flared in Harry’s scar, a crawling feeling came close to his skin; and then Harry’s pouch, clothes, gun, everything except his wand disappeared, leaving him naked but for the wand still in his right hand, and the glasses he’d Charmed to stick to his nose. The steel ring upon his left pinky finger was yanked off hard enough to scrape skin, taking the Transfigured jewel with it.

‘That,’ said the voice of Voldemort from behind the dirt wall, ‘was absolutely predictable. Do you really think I would shout it aloud for you to hear, if my immortality were disrupted? Really, stupid child? Lower your wand, do not raise it up again at any time, or you die upon the spot.’

Harry swallowed, and pointed his wand downward. ‘You would have been disappointed in me,’ Harry said, his own voice now unusually high, ‘if I’d missed an opportunity like that, I mean.’ There was no time to think, and Harry’s mouth was operating on autopilot for trying to placate evil overlords that might have paternal feelings for you and whom you’d just failed to assassinate.

Voldemort stepped around from behind the dirt wall, smiling that horrible smile that seemed to contain too many teeth. ‘I promised not to raise my hand or wand against you, child, if you did not raise your hand or wand against me.’

‘I used bullets,’ Harry said, his voice still high. ‘That’s not a fist or a spell.’

‘My curse thinks differently. That is the puzzle piece that you missed. Did you think I would leave the peace between us to mere fortune? Before I created you, I invoked a curse upon myself and all other Tom Riddles who would descend from me. A curse to enforce that none of us would threaten the others’ immortality, so long as the other made no attempt upon our own. Typical of that ridiculous fiasco, the curse seems to have ended up binding me, but taking no hold upon the infant with his self so lost.’ A low, lethal chuckle. ‘But you tried to end my true life just then, stupid child. Now curse is lifted, and I may kill you any time I wish.’

‘I see,’ Harry said. He did see; that was why Voldemort had told him about his horcrux system in the first place, just to set up the moment when Harry knowingly tried to violate his immortality. Harry’s mind was frantically churning through options, none of which seemed helpful. His pouch, his clothes, Harry saw by the moonlight that they all now lay in another heap by the altar, out of reach. ‘And now you kill me?’ Harry still had his wand, presumably the Dark Lord couldn’t cast his own magic on that, or his glasses, because of the disharmony. Cast my own spell first? No, Voldemort just jabs his wand downward to make another shield, then shoots me – what else is there? What else?

‘Still a fool. If no further matters remained between us, I would already have killed you.’ The dirt wall crumbled at another gesture of the wand, and Voldemort moved smoothly back toward the heap of items by the altar. The Dark Lord stretched out a hand, and the diary of Roger Bacon flew to him. ‘This is, indeed, horcrux of girl-child, my superior version.’ In his other hand appeared a parchment. ‘This is ritual for resurrecting her, if it must be done again. Instructions are honest, no traps. Remember that girl-child’s spirit cannot float free like ghost, Resurrection Stone is my horcrux, not hers. Do not lose her horcrux, or her spirit may be trapped within it.’ Voldemort reached down, picked up Harry’s pouch, fed both the diary and the parchment into it. ‘Remember that, in case something goes wrong with next moves.’

‘I don’t understand what is happening,’ Harry said. There was nothing else left. ‘Please explain to me.’

The Dark Lord was now regarding Harry with a grim look. ‘When girl-child died, was in company of school’s Seer, heard prophecy spoken that you would become force of vast destruction. You would become threat beyond imagination, beyond apocalypse. That is why I went to such lengths to undo my killing of girl-child, keep it undone.’

‘Are,’ what ‘are you sure,’ what.

‘Dare not say specifics to you. Prophecy I heard of myself led me to fulfill it. Have not forgotten that disaster.’ Voldemort backed further away from Harry, red slitted eyes fixed upon the Boy-Who-Lived, gun unwavering in the left hand. ‘All this, all I have done, is to smash that destiny at every point of intervention. If some fate makes me fail in what comes next, idiot-child of foretold destruction, then you must kill yourself to save girl-child. Else all you claim to value dies by your own hand.’

‘I,’ Harry’s voice went up an octave, ‘I,’ another octave, ‘I really really wouldn’t do that, seriously!’

‘Silence, fool. Remain silent unless given leave by me to speak. Keep your wand pointed down and do not raise it unless told. Else you die upon the spot, and mark that I said that in Parseltongue.’ Voldemort reached into the altar again.

For a second Harry’s mind couldn’t process what he was seeing, and then he saw that Voldemort was holding a human arm, severed near the shoulder; it seemed too thin, that arm.

The Dark Lord pressed his wand to the flesh above the severed arm’s elbow, and the fingers twitched, twitched like they were alive; by dim moonlight Harry saw a darker mark appear on that flesh, just above the elbow.

Seconds later the first hooded figure appeared inside the graveyard with the popping sound of an Apparition. A moment after that came another pop, and then another.

The hooded figures wore silver skull masks, and moonlight fled from the robes beneath them.

‘Master!’ cried one of the black robes, the third to arrive. The voice was of peculiar timbre, from behind the silver skull mask. ‘Master – it has been so long – we had lost hope –’

‘Silence!’ shouted the high voice of the Dark Lord Voldemort. Every trace of Professor Quirrell was now gone from the too-tall figure. ‘Train your wand upon the Boy-Who-Lived, and watch him! Do not be distracted, not by anything! Stun him at once if he moves, if he begins to speak!’

More pops. Between graves, behind a tree, in all the shadowy spaces, more black robes were Apparating, all hooded and masked. Some of them voiced exclamations of joy, many of those sounding rather forced; others moved forwards as though to greet their Master. Voldemort gave them all the same instruction, except that some were commanded to Cruciate Harry Potter if he moved, others to restrain the Boy-Who-Lived if he moved, others told to fire hexes and curses, others told to cancel his magic.

Thirty-seven pops, Harry counted before the black robes and skull masks seemed to stop arriving.

All of them were now holding their wands pointed at Harry, aligned in a semicircle before him, where they wouldn’t get into each other’s lines of fire.

Harry continued pointing his wand downward, insofar as he had been told that, if he tried to raise it, he would die. He remained silent, insofar as he had been told that if he tried to speak, he would die. He tried not to shiver in the falling night temperatures, for he was naked, and it was getting colder.

You know, said the last voice within Harry, the voice of hope, I think this is getting pretty bad even by my standards.

The sky had gone full blue-grey, dawn barely short of sunrise, by the time that Harry heard the sound of footsteps coming from the ladder that opened into his new office. Hastily Harry stood up and began to brush off his robes; and then, realising what he was doing, stopped the nervous motions. He’d just defeated Voldemort, damn it, he ought not to be this nervous.

The young witch’s head and chestnut curls appeared in the opening and peered around. Then she rose up higher, seemed almost to run up the ladder steps, like she was walking along an ordinary pavement but vertically; Harry could have blinked and missed it, how her shoe came down on the top rung of the ladder and then she leaped lightly onto the roof an instant later.

Hermione. Harry’s lips moved around the word, but made no sound.

There’d been something Harry had meant to say, but it had gone right out of his mind.

Maybe a quarter of the minute passed, on the rooftop, before Hermione Granger spoke. She was wearing a blue-edged uniform now, and the blue-bronze-striped tie of her proper House.

‘Harry,’ said Hermione Granger, a terribly familiar voice that almost brought tears to Harry’s eyes, ‘before I ask you all the questions, I’d like to start by saying thank you very much for, um, whatever it is you did. I mean it, really. Thank you.’

‘Hermione,’ Harry said, and swallowed. The phrase may I have permission to hug you, which Harry had imagined using for his opening line, seemed impossible to say. ‘Welcome back. Hold on while I put up some privacy spells.’ Harry took the Elder Wand out of his robes, got a book from his pouch that he opened to a bookmark, and then carefully pronounced ‘Hominem Revelio,’ along with two other recently-acquired security Charms that Harry had found himself barely able to cast if he wielded the Elder Wand. It wasn’t much, but it was marginally better security than just relying on Professor Vector.

‘You have Dumbledore’s wand,’ Hermione said. Her voice was hushed, and sounded as loud as an avalanche in the still dawn air. ‘And you can use it to cast fourth-year spells?’

Harry nodded, making a mental note to be more careful who else saw him do that. ‘Is it okay if I hug you?’

Hermione moved lightly over to him; her movements were peculiarly swift, more graceful than they’d been before. Her motions seemed to radiate an air of something pure and untouched, reminding Harry again of how peaceful Hermione had looked when she was sleeping on Voldemort’s altar –

Realization hit Harry like a ton of bricks, or at least a kilogram of brick.

And Harry hugged Hermione, feeling how very alive she seemed. He felt like crying, and suppressed it, because he didn’t know whether that was just her aura affecting him or not.

Hermione’s arms around him were gentle, exceedingly light in their pressure, as if she were being deliberately careful not to snap his body in half like a used toothpick.

‘So,’ Hermione said, once Harry had let go of her. Her young face looked very serious, as well as pure and innocent. ‘I didn’t tell the Aurors you were there, or that it was Professor Quirrell and not You-Know-Who who killed all the Death Eaters. Professor Flitwick only let them give me one drop of Veritaserum, so I didn’t have to say. I just told them the troll was the last thing I remembered.’

‘Ah,’ Harry said. He had somehow found himself staring at Hermione’s nose instead of her eyes. ‘What do you think happened, exactly?’

‘Well,’ Hermione Granger said thoughtfully, ‘I got eaten by a troll, which I’d frankly rather not do again, and then there was a really loud bang and my legs were back, and I was lying on a stone altar in the middle of a graveyard in a dark moonlit forest I’d never seen before, with somebody’s severed hands clutched around my throat. So you see, Mr Potter, finding myself in a situation that weird and dark and scary, I wasn’t going to make the same mistake I did last time with Tracey. I knew right away that it was you.’

Harry nodded. ‘Good call.’

‘I said your name, but you didn’t answer,’ said Hermione. ‘I sat up and one of the bloody hands slid down over my shirt, leaving little bits of flesh behind. I didn’t scream though, even when I looked around and saw all the heads and bodies and realized what the smell was.’ Hermione stopped, took another deep breath. ‘I saw the skull masks and realized that the dead people had been Death Eaters. I knew right away that the Defence Professor had been there with you and killed them all, but I didn’t notice Professor Quirrell’s body was also there. I didn’t realize it was him even when I saw Professor Flitwick checking the body. He looked … different, when he was dead.’ Hermione’s voice became quieter. She looked humbled somehow, in a way Harry couldn’t often remember seeing. ‘They said David Monroe sacrificed his life to bring me back, the same way your mother sacrificed herself for you, so that the Dark Lord would explode again when he tried to touch me. I’m pretty sure that’s not the whole truth, but … I’ve thought a lot of nasty things about our Defence Professor that I never should’ve thought.’

‘Um,’ Harry said.

Hermione nodded solemnly, her hands clasped in front of her as though in penitence. ‘I know you’re probably too nice to say the things to me that you have a right to say now, so I’ll say them for you, Harry. You were right about Professor Quirrell, and I was wrong. You told me so. David Monroe was a little bit Dark and a whole lot Slytherin, and it was childish of me to think that was the same thing as being evil.’

‘Ah …’ Harry said. This was very hard to say. ‘Actually, the rest of the world doesn’t know this part, not even the Headmistress. But in point of fact you were one hundred and twelve percent correct about him being evil, and I’ll remember for future reference that although “Dark” and “evil” may not technically be the same thing, there’s a great big statistical correlation.’

‘Oh,’ said Hermione, and fell silent again.

‘You’re not saying that you told me so?’ said Harry. His mental model of Hermione was yelling: I told you so! Didn’t I tell you so, Mr. Potter? Didn’t I tell you? Professor Quirrell is eeeeviiil, I said, but you didn’t listen to me!

The actual Hermione just shook her head. ‘I know you cared about him a lot,’ she said softly. ‘Since I was right after all … I knew you’d probably be hurting a lot after Professor Quirrell turned out to be evil, and that it wouldn’t be a good time to say I told you so. I mean, that’s what I decided when I was thinking that part through several months earlier.’

Thank you, Miss Granger. Harry was glad she’d said that much, though, it just wouldn’t have felt like Hermione otherwise.

‘So, Mr Potter,’ said Hermione Granger, tapping her fingers on her robe at around thigh level. ‘After the medi-witch drew my blood, it stopped hurting right away, and when I brushed away the little bit of blood on my arm, I couldn’t find where the needle had poked me. I bent some of the metal in my bedframe without trying hard, and though I haven’t had a chance to test it yet, I feel like I should be able to run really fast. My fingernails are pearly-white and shiny even though I don’t remember painting them. And my teeth look like that too, which, being the daughter of dentists, makes me nervous. So it’s not that I’m ungrateful, but just what exactly did you do?’

‘Um,’ Harry said. ‘And I’m expecting you’re also wondering why you’re radiating an aura of purity and innocence?’

‘I’m what?’

‘That part wasn’t my idea. Honestly.’ Harry’s voice went small. ‘Please don’t kill me.’

Hermione Granger raised her hands in front of her face, staring somewhat cross-eyed at her fingers. ‘Harry, are you saying … I mean, my radiating innocence and being all fast and graceful and my teeth being pearly white … is it alicorn my fingernails are made of?’

‘Alicorn?’

‘It’s the term for unicorn horn, Mr Potter.’ Hermione Granger seemed to be trying to nibble her fingernails, and not having much luck. ‘So, I guess if you bring a girl back from the dead she ends up as, what did Daphne call it, a Sparkling Unicorn Princess?’

‘That’s not exactly what happened,’ Harry said, though it was frighteningly close.

Hermione took her finger out of her mouth, frowning at it. ‘I can’t bite through it either. Mr Potter, did you consider the problems now that it’s literally impossible for me to trim my fingernails and toenails?’

‘The Weasley twins have a magical sword that should work,’ Harry volunteered.

‘I think,’ Hermione Granger said firmly, ‘that I would like to know the whole story behind all this, Mr Potter. Because knowing you and knowing Professor Quirrell, there was some sort of plan going on.’

Harry took a deep breath. Then he exhaled. ‘Sorry, it’s … classified. I could tell you if you studied Occlumency, but … do you want to?’

‘Do I want to study Occlumency?’ Hermione said, looking slightly surprised. ‘That’s at least a sixth-year thing, isn’t it?’

‘I learned it,’ Harry said. ‘I started with an unusual boost, but I doubt that really mattered in the long run. I mean, I’m sure you could learn calculus if you studied hard, regardless of what age Muggles usually learn it. The question is, um.’ Harry was having to control his breathing. ‘The question is, do you still want to do … that kind of stuff.’

Hermione turned, and looked at where the sky was lightening in the east. ‘You mean,’ she said quietly, ‘do I still want to be a hero now that it’s earned me a horrible death that one time.’

Harry nodded, then said ‘Yes’ because Hermione wasn’t turning toward him, though the word felt blocked in his throat.

‘I’ve been thinking about that,’ Hermione said. ‘It was, in fact, an exceptionally gruesome and painful death.’

‘I, um. I did set some things up just in case you still wanted to be a hero. There were some short windows of opportunity where I didn’t have time to consult you, I couldn’t let you see me because I expected you to be given Veritaserum later. But if you don’t like it, I can undo most of what I did and you can just ignore the rest.’

Hermione nodded distantly. ‘Like making everyone think that I … Harry, did I actually do anything to You-Know-Who?’

‘No, that was all me, though please don’t tell anyone that. Just so you know, that time the Boy-Who-Lived supposedly defeated Voldemort, on the night of Halloween in 1981, that was Dumbledore’s victory and he let everyone think it was me. So now I’ve defeated a Dark Lord once, and had the credit for it once. It all balances out eventually, I guess.’

Hermione went on gazing to the east. ‘I’m not really comfortable with this,’ she said after a while. ‘People thinking I defeated the Dark Lord Voldemort, when I haven’t done anything at all … oh, that’s the same thing you went through, isn’t it?’

‘Yeah. Sorry about inflicting that on you. I was … well, I was trying to create a separate identity for you in people’s minds, I guess. There was just the one opportunity and everything was sort of rushed and … I realized afterwards that maybe I shouldn’t have, but it was too late.’ Harry cleared his throat. ‘Though, um. If you’re feeling like you want to do something that’s actually worthy of the way people think about the Girl-Who-Revived, um. I might have an idea for what you can do. Very soon, if you want.’

Hermione Granger was giving him a look.

‘But you don’t have to!’ Harry said hastily. ‘You can just ignore this whole thing and be the best student in Ravenclaw! If that’s what you prefer.’

‘Are you trying to use reverse psychology on me, Mr Potter?’

‘No! Honestly!’ Harry took a deep breath. ‘I’m trying not to decide your life for you. I thought I saw, yesterday, I thought I saw what might come next for you – but then I remembered how much of this year I’d spent being a total idiot. I thought of some things Dumbledore said to me. I realized it genuinely wasn’t my place to say. That you could do anything you wanted with your life, and that above all, the choice had to be your own. Maybe you don’t want to be a hero after this, maybe you want to become a great magical researcher because that’s who Hermione Granger really was all along, never mind what your fingernails are made out of now. Or you could go to the Salem Witches’ Institute in America instead of Hogwarts. I won’t lie and say I’d like that, but it really is up to you.’ Harry turned to the horizon and swept his hand wide, as though to indicate all the world that lay beyond Hogwarts. ‘You can go anywhere from here. You can do anything with your life. If you want to be a wealthy sixty-year-old merman, I can make it happen. I’m serious.’

Hermione nodded slowly. ‘I’m curious about how you’d do that exactly, but what I want isn’t to have things done for me.’

Harry sighed. ‘I understand. Um …’ Harry hesitated. ‘I think … if it helps you to know … in my case, things were being arranged for me a lot. By Dumbledore, mostly, though Professor Quirrell too. Maybe the power to earn your own way in life is itself something you have to earn.’

‘Why, that sounds very wise,’ Hermione said. ‘Like my parents paying for me to go to university, so I can some day get my own job. Professor Quirrell bringing me back to life as a Sparkling Unicorn Princess and you telling everyone that I offed the Dark Lord Voldemort is just like that, really.’

‘I am sorry,’ Harry said. ‘I know I should’ve done it differently, but … I didn’t have much time to plan and I was exhausted and not really thinking straight –’

‘I’m grateful, Harry,’ Hermione said, her voice softer now. ‘You’re being too harsh on yourself, even. Please don’t take it so seriously when I’m sarcastic to you. I don’t want to be the sort of girl who comes back from the dead, and then starts complaining about which superpowers she got and that her alicorn fingernails are the wrong shade of pearly white.’ Hermione had turned, was again gazing off at the east. ‘But, Mr Potter … if I do decide that dying a horrible death isn’t enough to make me rethink my life choices … not that I’m saying that just yet … then what happens next?’

‘I do my best to support you in your life choices,’ Harry said firmly. ‘Whatever they are.’

‘You have a quest already lined up for me, I’m guessing. A nice safe quest where there’s no chance of my getting hurt again.’

Harry rubbed his eyes, feeling tired inside. It was like he could hear the voice of Albus Dumbledore inside his head. Forgive me, Hermione Granger … ‘I’m sorry, Hermione. If you go down that path I’m going to have to Dumbledore you, and not tell you some things. Manipulate you, if only for a short while. I do believe there’s something you might be able to do now, something real, something worthy of the way people are thinking about the Girl-Who-Revived … that you might have a destiny, even … but in the end that’s just a guess, I know a lot less than Dumbledore did. Are you willing to risk the life you just got back?’

Hermione turned to look at him, her eyes widening in surprise. ‘Risk my life?’

Harry didn’t nod, because that would have been outright lying. ‘Are you willing to do that?’ Harry said instead. ‘The quest that I think might be your destiny – and no, I don’t know any specific prophecies, it’s just a guess – involves literal descent-into-Hell type stuff.’

‘I thought …’ Hermione said. She sounded uncertain. ‘I thought for sure that after this, you and Professor McGonagall wouldn’t … you know … let me do anything the least bit dangerous ever again.’

Harry said nothing, feeling guilty about the false relationship credit he was getting. It was in fact the case that Hermione was modelling him with tremendous accuracy, and that if not for Hermione having a horcrux, the surface of the planet Venus would have dropped to fractional-Kelvin temperatures before Harry tried this.

‘On a scale of zero to a hundred, how literal a descent into Hell are we talking about here?’ said Hermione. The girl now looked a bit worried.

Harry mentally calibrated his scales, remembering Azkaban. ‘I’d say maybe eighty-seven?’

‘This sounds like something I should do when I’m older, Harry. There’s a difference between being a hero and being a complete lunatic.’

Harry shook his head. ‘I don’t think the risk would change much,’ Harry said, leaving aside the question of how much risk that really was, ‘and it’s the sort of thing that’s better done sooner, if someone does it at all.’

‘And my parents don’t get a vote,’ Hermione said. ‘Or do they?’

Harry shrugged. ‘We both know how they’d vote, and you can take that into account if you like. Um, I said for Mr and Mrs Granger not to be told yet that you’re alive. They’ll find out after you come back from your mission, if you choose to accept it. That seems a bit … kinder on your parents’ nerves, they just get the one pleasant surprise, instead of having to worry about, um, stuff.’

‘Why, that’s very thoughtful of you,’ Hermione said. ‘It’s nice that you’re so concerned about their feelings. May I think about this for a few minutes, please?’

Harry gestured toward the cushion he’d set down opposite his own, and Hermione moved over with fluid grace, and sat down to look out over the castle-edge, still radiating peacefulness all over the place. They’d really need to do something about that, maybe pay someone to invent an Anti-Purity Potion.

‘Do I have to decide without knowing what the mission is?’ Hermione asked.

‘Oh hell no,’ Harry said, thinking of a similar conversation before his own trip to Azkaban. ‘This is the sort of thing you have to choose freely if you do it at all. I mean that’s an actual mission requirement. If you say that you still want to be a hero, I’ll tell you afterwards about the mission – after you’ve had some time to eat and talk to people and recover a bit – and you’ll decide then if it’s something you want to do. And we’ll test in advance whether returning from death has allowed you to cast the spell that normal wizards think is impossible, before you go out.’

Hermione nodded, and fell back into silence.

Harry, having now finished his cauldron, was carefully scooping acorns into the container while the scouts searched for a nearby source of water that could be used as a liquid base. They’d come across frequent sinkholes and miniature creeks in the forest before, so it ought not to take long. Another scout had brought a straight stick that would serve as a stirrer, so Harry didn’t have to Transfigure one.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

How can I invoke magical powers that ought to be beyond the reach of first-year students?

There was a cautionary tale the Potions Master had told them (with much sneers and laughter to make the stupidity seem low-status instead of daring and romantic) about a second-year witch in Beauxbatons who’d stolen some extremely restricted and expensive ingredients, and tried to brew Polyjuice, so she could borrow the form of another girl for purposes better left unmentioned. Only she’d managed to contaminate the potion with cat hairs, and then instead of seeking a healer immediately, the witch had hidden herself in a bathroom, hoping the effects would just wear off; and when she’d finally been found, it had been too late to reverse the transformation completely, condemning her to a life of despair as a sort of cat-girl hybrid.

Harry hadn’t realized what that meant until the instant of thinking the right question – but what that implied was that a young wizard or witch could do things with Potions-Making that they couldn’t even come close to doing with Charms. Polyjuice was one of the most potent potions known … but what made Polyjuice a N.E.W.T.-level potion, apparently, wasn’t the required age before you had enough magical power; it was how difficult the potion was to brew precisely and what happened to you if you messed up.

Nobody in any army had tried brewing any potions up until then. But Professor Quirrell would let you get away with nearly anything, if it was something you could also have done in a real war. Cheating is technique, the Defence Professor had once lectured them. Or rather, cheating is what the losers call technique, and will be worth extra Quirrell points when executed successfully. In principle, there was nothing unrealistic about Transfiguring a couple of cauldrons and brewing potions out of whatever came to hand, if you had enough time before the armies met.

So Harry had retrieved his copy of Magical Drafts and Potions, and begun looking for a safe but useful potion he could brew in the minutes before the battle started – a potion which would win the battle too fast for counter-spells, or produce spell effects too strong for first-years to Finite.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

What potion can I brew using only components gathered from an ordinary forest?

Every recipe in Magical Drafts and Potions used at least one ingredient from a magical plant or animal. Which was unfortunate, because all the magical plants and animals were in the Forbidden Forest, not the safer and lesser woods where battles were held.

Someone else might have given up at that point.

Harry had turned the pages from one recipe to another, skimming faster and faster in dawning realization, confirming what he had already read and was now seeing for the first time.

Every single Potions recipe seemed to demand at least one magical ingredient, but why should that be true?

Charms required no material components at all; you just said the words and waved your wand. Harry had been thinking about Potions-Making as essentially analogous: instead of your spoken syllables triggering a spell effect for no comprehensible reason, you collected a batch of disgusting ingredients and stirred four times clockwise, and that arbitrarily triggered a spell effect.

In which case, given that most potions used ordinary components like porcupine quills or stewed slugs, you’d expect to see some potions using only ordinary components.

But instead every single recipe in Magical Drafts and Potions demanded at least one component from a magical plant or animal – an ingredient like silk from an Acromantula or petals from a Venus Fire Trap.

Sometimes, even though you were looking straight at something, you didn’t realize what you were looking at until you happened to ask exactly the right question …

If making a potion is like casting a Charm, why don’t I fall over from exhaustion after brewing a draught as powerful as boil-curing?

The Friday before last, Harry’s double Potions class had brewed potion of boil-curing … although even the most trivial healing Charms, if you tried to cast them with wand and incantation, were at least fourth-year spells. And afterwards, they’d all felt the way they usually felt after Potions class, namely, not magically exhausted to any discernible degree.

Harry had shut his copy of Magical Drafts and Potions with a snap, and rushed down to the Ravenclaw common room. Harry had found a seventh-year Ravenclaw doing his N.E.W.T. potions homework and paid the older boy a Sickle to borrow Moste Potente Potions for five minutes; because Harry hadn’t wanted to run all the way to the library to find confirmation.

After skimming through five recipes in the seventh-year book, Harry had read the sixth recipe, for a potion of fire breathing, which required Ashwinder eggs … and the book warned that the resulting fire could be no hotter than the magical fire which had spawned the Ashwinder which had laid the eggs.

Harry had shouted ‘Eureka!’ right in the middle of the Ravenclaw common room, and been severely rebuked by a nearby prefect, who’d thought Mr Potter was trying to cast a spell. Nobody in the wizarding world knew or cared about some ancient Muggle named Archimedes, nor the ur-physicist’s realization that the water displaced from a bathtub would equal the volume of the object entering the bathtub …

Conservation laws. They’d been the critical insight in more Muggle discoveries than Harry could easily count. In Muggle technology you couldn’t raise a feather one metre off the ground without the power coming from somewhere. If you looked at molten lava spilling from a volcano and asked where the heat came from, a physicist would tell you about radioactive heavy metals in the centre of the Earth’s molten core. If you asked where the energy to power the radioactivity came from, the physicist would point to an era before the Earth had formed, and a primordial supernova in the early days of the galaxy which had baked atomic nuclei heavier than the natural limit, the supernova compressing protons and neutrons into a tight unstable package that yielded back some of the supernova’s energy when it split. A light bulb was fuelled by electricity, fuelled by a nuclear power plant, fuelled by a supernova … You could play the game all the way back to the Big Bang.

Magic did not appear to work like this, to put it mildly. Magic’s attitude toward laws like Conservation of Energy was somewhere between a giant extended middle finger, and a shrug of total indifference. Aguamenti created water out of nothingness, so far as anyone knew; there was no known lake whose water level went down each time. That was a simple fifth-year spell, not considered impressive by wizards, because creating a mere glass of water didn’t seem amazing to them. They didn’t have the wacky notion that mass ought to be conserved, or that creating a gram of mass was somehow equivalent to creating 90,000,000,000,000 joules of energy. There was an upper-year spell Harry had run across whose literal incantation was Arresto Momentum! and when Harry had asked if the momentum went anywhere else he’d just got a puzzled look. Harry had kept an increasingly desperate eye out for some kind of conservation principle in magic, anywhere whatsoever …

… and the whole time it had been right in front of him in every Potions class. Potions-Making didn’t create magic, it preserved magic, that was why every potion needed at least one magical ingredient. And by following instructions like stir four times anticlockwise and once clockwise – Harry had hypothesized – you were doing something like casting a small spell that reshaped the magic in the ingredients. (And unbound the physical form so that ingredients like porcupine quills dissolved smoothly into a drinkable liquid; Harry strongly suspected that a Muggle following exactly the same recipe would end up with nothing but a spiny mess.) That was what Potions-Making really was, the art of transforming existing magical essences. So you were a little tired after Potions class, but not much, because you weren’t empowering the potions yourself, you were just reshaping magic that was already there. And that was why a second-year witch could brew Polyjuice, or at least get close.

Harry had kept scanning through Moste Potente Potions, looking for something that might disprove his shiny new theory. After five minutes he’d flipped the older boy another Sickle (over his protests) and kept going.

The potion of giant strength required a Re’em to trample the mashed Dugbogs you stirred into the potion. It was odd, Harry had realized after a moment, because crushed Dugbogs weren’t strong themselves, they were just … very, very crushed after the Re’em got through with them.

Another recipe said to touch with forged bronze, i.e., grasp a Knut in pliers so you could skim the potion’s surface; and if you dropped the Knut all the way in, the book warned, the potion would instantly superheat and boil over the cauldron.

Harry had stared at the recipes and their warnings, forming a second and stranger hypothesis. Of course it wouldn’t be as simple as Potions-Making using magical potentials imbued in the ingredients, like Muggle cars fuelled by the combustion potential of gasoline. Magic would never be as sensible as that …

And then Harry had gone to Professor Flitwick – since he didn’t want to approach Professor Snape outside of class – and Harry had told Professor Flitwick that he wanted to invent a new potion, and he knew what the ingredients ought to be and what the potion should do, but he didn’t know how to deduce the required stirring pattern –

After Professor Flitwick had stopped screaming in horror and running in little circles, and Professor McGonagall had been called into the ensuing fierce interrogation to promise Harry that in this case it was both acceptable and important for him to reveal his underlying theory, it had developed that Harry had not made an original magical discovery, but rediscovered a law so ancient that nobody knew who had first formulated it:

A potion spends that which is invested in the creation of its ingredients.

The heat of goblin forges that had cast the bronze Knut, the Re’em’s strength that had crushed the Dugbogs, the magical fire that had spawned the Ashwinder: all these potencies could be recalled, unlocked, and restructured by the spell-like process of stirring the ingredients in exact patterns.

(From a Muggle standpoint it was just odd, a deranged version of thermodynamics invented by someone who thought life ought to be fair. From a Muggle standpoint, the heat expended in forging the Knut hadn’t gone into the bronze, the heat had left and dissipated into the environment, becoming permanently less available. Energy was conserved, could be neither created nor destroyed; entropy always increased. But wizards didn’t think that way: from their perspective, if you’d put some amount of work into making a Knut, it stood to reason that you could get exactly the same work back out. Harry had tried to explain why this sounded a bit odd if you’d been raised by Muggles, and Professor McGonagall had asked bemusedly why the Muggle perspective was any better than the wizarding one.)

The fundamental principle of Potions-Making had no name and no standard phrasing, since then you might be tempted to write it down.

And someone who wasn’t wise enough to figure out the principle themselves might read it.

And they would start having all sorts of bright ideas for inventing new Potions.

And then they would be turned into cat-girls.

It had been made very clear to Harry that he wasn’t going to be sharing this particular discovery with Neville, or Hermione either after the next armies’ battle. Harry had tried to say something about Hermione seeming really off lately and this being just the sort of thing that might cheer her up. Professor McGonagall had said flatly that he wasn’t even to think it, and Professor Flitwick had raised his little hands and made a gesture as of snapping a wand in half.

Although the two Professors had been kind enough to suggest that if Mr Potter thought he knew what the potion’s ingredients should be, he might be able to find an already-existing recipe that did the same thing; and Professor Flitwick had mentioned several volumes in the Hogwarts library that might be useful …

The vast parchment-like screen now showed only an aerial view of the forest, from which you could barely make out the camouflaged forms of three armies, split up into two groups each, converging to fight their three-way battle.

The benches of the Quidditch stadium were now rapidly filling up with the more easily bored sort of spectator who only wanted to be there for the final battle and skip out on all the boring points along the way. (If there was anything wrong with Professor Quirrell’s battles, it was widely agreed, it was that his spectacles didn’t last nearly as long as Quidditch matches, once they actually started. To this Professor Quirrell had replied only, Such is realism, and that had been that.)

Within the huge window – it was all one window now, observing from a great height – the vague collections of tiny camouflaged forms grew closer.

Closer.

Almost touching –

The vast white parchment window showed the first touch of battle between Sunshine and Chaos, a screaming mass of running children with smiley-faces upon their breasts, charging forward with Contego shields held high and others shouting ‘Somnium!’ –

Until one of their number shrieked ‘Prismatis!’ in a terrified voice and the entire charge came to a sudden halt before the sparkling wall of force that had appeared in front of them.

Tracey Davis had walked out from behind the trees.

‘That’s right,’ said Tracey, her voice low and grim as she levelled her wand on the barrier. ‘You should fear me. For I am Tracey Davis, the Darke Lady! That’s Darke Lady spelled D-A-R-K-E, with an E!’

(Amelia Bones, Director of the Department of Magical Law Enforcement, was sending an inquiring look at Mr and Mrs Davis, both of whom looked like they would have dearly loved to die on the spot.)

Behind the Prismatic Barrier, there was some kind of hushed argument taking place among the Sunshine Soldiers, one of whom in particular seemed to be getting scolded by several of the others.

Then, a moment later, Tracey flinched.

Susan Bones had come to the front of the Sunshine contingent.

(‘Goodness,’ said Augusta Longbottom. ‘What do you suppose your grand-niece has been learning at Hogwarts?’)

(‘I don’t know,’ Amelia Bones said calmly, ‘but I shall owl her a Chocolate Frog and instructions to learn more of it.’)

The Prismatic Barrier vanished.

The Sunshine Soldiers resumed their charge forward.

Tracey yelled, her voice high with strain, ‘Inflammare!’ and the Sunshine charge came to another sudden halt as a line of fire blazed up between them in the half-dry grass, extending to follow the path of Tracey’s wand as she pointed it; an instant later Susan Bones cried ‘Finite Incantatem!’ and the flames dimmed, brightened, dimmed in the contest of their wills, other soldiers raising their wards to aim at Tracey; and that was when Neville Longbottom plunged shrieking out of the sky.

One of the Dragon Warriors, Raymond Arnold, made a hand-sign, pointing forward and oblique left; and there was a sudden hushed hiss of whispers among the Dragon Army contingent as they all quietly reoriented themselves in the direction of the enemy. The Sunnies knew they were there, of course both armies knew; but somehow, in this moment, they had all become instinctively quiet.

The Dragons crept forward further, and then further, the dull camouflaged forms of the Sunnies beginning to appear among the distant trees, and still nobody spoke, nobody bellowed the call to charge.

Draco was now at the forefront of his soldiers, Vincent behind him and Padma only a shade further back; if the three of them could take the shock of Sunshine’s best, the rest of Dragon Army might stand a chance.

Then Draco saw one Sunnie staring at him from the distance, in the vanguard of her own army; staring at him with a look of fury –

Across the forest battleground, their eyes met.

Draco had only a fraction of a second to wonder, in the back of his mind, what Hermione Granger was so angry about, before the shout went up from both their armies; and they were all running forward to the charge.

The other Chaotics had appeared now from among the trees, some had dropped out of trees, and the battle was in full force now, everyone firing in every direction at anything that looked like an enemy. Plus a number of Sunnies crying ‘Luminos!’ at Neville Longbottom as the Chaos Hufflepuff twisted and rocketed up through the air on courses that could only be described as, indeed, ‘chaotic’ –

And it happened, the way it happened only one time out of twenty in mock aerial combat, that Neville Longbottom’s broomstick glowed bright red beneath his clenched hands.

It should’ve meant that Longbottom was out of the game.

Then, in the Hogwarts stands, among the watching crowds of students, a scream went up –

Combat realism. It was Professor Quirrell’s one master rule. You could get away with anything if it was realistic, and in real life, a soldier didn’t just vanish when their broomstick got hit by a curse.

Neville was falling toward the ground and screaming ‘Chaotic landing!’ and the Chaotics were wrenching their attention away from fights to cast the Hover Charm (and run at the same time so they wouldn’t be sitting ducks), almost everyone else stopping to gape –

And Neville Longbottom slammed into the leaf-laden forest ground, landing on one knee, one foot, and both hands, as though he were kneeling down to be knighted.

Everything stopped. Even Tracey and Susan paused in their duel.

In the stadium, all crowd noises vanished.

There was a universal silence composed of astonishment, concern, and sheer dumbstruck gaping awe, as everyone waited to see what would happen next.

And then Neville Longbottom slowly rose to his feet, and levelled his wand at the Sunshine Soldiers.

Though nobody on the battlefield heard it, a large segment of the stadium audience had begun chanting, in steadily rising notes each time the word was uttered, ‘doom doom doom doom doom’, because you just couldn’t see that and not think it required musical accompaniment.

‘The crowd is cheering your grandson,’ said Amelia Bones. The old witch was favouring the screen with a measuring look.

‘So they are,’ said Augusta Longbottom. ‘Some, if I hear correctly, are cheering, Our blood for Neville! Our souls for Neville!’

‘Quite,’ said Amelia, taking a sip from a teacup which had not been there moments earlier. ‘It shows the lad has leadership potential.’

‘These cheers,’ continued Augusta, her voice taking on an even more stunned quality, ‘seem to be coming from the Hufflepuff benches.’

‘It is the House of the loyal, my dear,’ said Amelia.

‘Albus Percival Wulfric Brian Dumbledore! What in Merlin’s name has been happening in this school?’

Lucius Malfoy was watching the screens with an ironic smile, his fingers tapping at his armrest in no discernible pattern. ‘I do not know what is more frightening, the thought that he has some hidden plan behind all this, or the thought that he does not.’

‘Look!’ cried the Lord of Greengrass. The dapper young man had risen half out of his chair, pointing his finger at the screen. ‘There she goes!’

‘We’ll both take him at once,’ Daphne whispered. She knew that a few fear-filled minutes of real combat experience, a handful of times each week, might not be enough to match Neville’s regular duelling practise with Harry and Cedric Diggory over the same period. ‘He’s too much for one of us, but both of us together – I’ll use my Charm, you just try to stun him –’

Hannah, beside her, nodded, and then they both screamed at the top of their lungs and charged forward, the Hover Charms of two supporting Sunshine Soldiers moving them faster and making them light on their feet, Daphne already crying ‘Tonare!’ even as Hannah kept a huge Contego shield moving in front of them, and with a brief extra lift they leapt over the heads of the front screen of soldiers and landed in front of Neville with their hair billowing high around them –

(Photographs were strictly prohibited at all Hogwarts games, but somehow this moment still ended up on the front page of the next day’s Quibbler.)

– and in the same instant, because fighting older bullies had burned away the slightest traces of hesitation, Hannah fired her first Sleep Hex at Neville (she’d started the incantation while she was still in the air) even as Daphne, concentrating more on speed than on force, slashed down with her Ancient Blade at where she thought Neville’s thighs would be after he dodged –

But Neville leapt up, not sideways, leapt up higher than he should’ve been able to go, so that her glowing sword cut only the air beneath his feet. Somehow Daphne realized what it meant, that Neville still had other Chaotics Hovering him, in time for her to raise her Blade up over her head, but Neville fell too fast and when his Blade smashed into hers it was like being hit by a Bludger. It knocked Daphne off her feet and sent her sprawling backward onto the grass, hitting the ground hard on her back. It might have been all over for her, then, if Neville hadn’t landed too hard himself and gone to his knees with a pained gasp. And then before Neville could bring his glowing Blade down, Hannah shouted ‘Somnium!’ and Neville lurched frantically backward – though of course no spell had actually come from Hannah’s wand, the Hufflepuff girl couldn’t really have fired again that fast – which gave Daphne a second to scramble to her feet and get both hands around her wand again –

‘Dear Merlin,’ said Lady Greengrass. Her voice seemed unsteady, the aristocratic poise well-punctured. ‘My daughter is fighting with the Charm of the Most Ancient Blade. In her first year. I never knew she possessed – such extraordinary talent –’

‘Excellent blood,’ Charles Nott said approvingly, causing Augusta to snort.

‘My good Lady,’ said Professor Quirrell, sounding grave. ‘Do not wrong your daughter so. That is not mere talent which you see.’ His voice grew a little dryer. ‘Rather, it is what happens when children put their competitive efforts into a game which involves actual spell-casting.’

‘Expelliarmus!’ shouted Draco, trying not to let his voice crack as he simultaneously dodged the blazing red stunbolt that Hermione Granger had fired at him, his muscles twisting with the need to dodge in the wrong direction – she’d pointed to his left, and then with a mysterious twitch fired right –

Hermione dodged the fast-moving duelling hex, and cried with hardly another moment’s pause, ‘Steleus!’, a wide-angle Hex that Draco couldn’t avoid, but he managed to point his wand at his own face and cry ‘Quiescus!’ before the sudden urge to inhale could devolve into a sneezing fit that would’ve ended the battle.

Draco Malfoy was already half-exhausted from all the Locking Charms and Transfigurations earlier, but his confusion was beginning to give way to a sense of his own blood boiling, he didn’t know why Granger was attacking him so angrily all of a sudden, but if she wanted a fight he’d give her one –

(The Dragons and Sunnies weren’t stopping to watch the duel of their Generals, the Dragons were too disciplined to stop and watch and that meant the Sunnies had to go on fighting too; but the gaping audience in the Hogwarts Quidditch stands were being distracted even from Neville and Daphne’s spectacle, shifting their eyes to the duel of two Generals as Malfoy and Granger fired hex after hex and jinx after jinx at each other, casting more rapidly than any other student in their year could have managed, the Dragon General’s trained duelling dance matched by the Sunshine General’s frantic energy, the combat between them beginning to resemble an adult duel as the two most magically powerful first-years resorted to spells more exotic than the usual Sleep Hex.)

– although, Draco was beginning to realize, when he and Harry and Professor Quirrell had dismissed Miss Granger as having as much intent to kill as a bowl of wet grapes, they’d never seen her angry.

Daphne lashed out with her Ancient Blade, again not trying to hit hard but just moving the Blade as fast as possible, at the same time Hannah cried ‘Somnium!’ and Neville leapt back again, but it had been another bluff and Hannah was moving in to fire a real spell almost point-blank –

– and Neville Longbottom did exactly what – he would explain afterwards – Cedric Diggory had trained him to do if he was fighting Bellatrix Black, which was to spin around and kick Hannah really hard in the pit of her stomach.

The Hufflepuff girl made a sad little sound, a gasping cry of pain, as she was knocked off her feet by the hard shoe sinking into her abdomen with the force of Neville’s whole body behind it.

For an instant the battlefield stood still, everything halted except Hannah’s falling form.

Then Neville’s face turned to absolute dismay and he lowered his wand, the Chaotic Lieutenant starting instinctively toward his House-mate as he reached for her with his other hand –

Even as Hannah turned her fall into a roll and came out with her wand raised and shot him.

A fractional second later, Daphne, who hadn’t hesitated either, sank her Most Ancient Blade squarely into Neville’s back, causing the Chaotic Lieutenant’s muscles to jerk convulsively with the stunning magic discharging into him even as Hannah’s Sleep Hex took effect, and then the last scion of Longbottom was sprawled still on the ground with a look of total surprise frozen to his face.

‘Today Mr Longbottom has learned a valuable lesson about his feelings of pity and remorse,’ said Professor Quirrell.

‘And chivalry,’ said Amelia, sipping her tea again.

‘Are you all right?’ whispered Daphne, as she stood protectively over where Hannah lay on the ground clutching her stomach. The girl didn’t give anything back in reply except more retching sounds that sounded like Hannah was trying not to throw up while trying not to cry.

Somehow, even though it might not have been good tactics – it would’ve been better if Hannah had been hexed outright, than for other soldiers to be tied up protecting her – a number of Sunnies seemed to be standing in front of Hannah with their wands clutched tightly, staring angrily at the Chaotics. Someone had thrown up a Prismatic barrier between the two groups, Daphne couldn’t see who.

And for some reason the Chaotics didn’t seem to be pressing the attack. Even Tracey had completely dropped the grim look on her face and was shifting her weight nervously from one foot to another, as though she was having trouble remembering which side she was on –

‘Hold!’ shouted a voice. ‘Hold battle!’

There wasn’t much battle going on anyway, but it held.

General Potter, looking every inch the Boy-Who-Lived, strode out from the trees with something large and camouflage-cloth-covered held under one arm.

‘Is Miss Abbott breathing all right?’ General Potter yelled.

Daphne didn’t look back. She didn’t trust that this wasn’t a trap – it was absolutely certain that if the Chaotics took the opportunity to attack, Professor Quirrell would not only rule it legal but also award them extra points afterwards. But Daphne could hear the answer well enough with her ears, it wasn’t like Hannah was trying to breathe quietly, and so she said, ‘Sort of.’

‘She should get out of here and to someone who can use healing Charms,’ Harry said. ‘Just in case that broke something.’

From behind Daphne, a small gasping voice said, ‘I – can – still – fight –’

‘Miss Abbott, don’t –’ Harry said, just as there was the sound from behind Daphne of someone collapsing back to the grass after trying and failing to get to her feet. Everyone winced, but Daphne didn’t turn her back on Harry.

‘Why haven’t the teachers stopped the battle?’ said Susan, her voice angry.

‘I expect it’s because Miss Abbott is in no danger of permanent damage and Professor Quirrell thinks we’re learning valuable lessons,’ Harry said in a hard voice. ‘Look, Miss Abbott, if you go, Tracey will also retire from the battle. You already outnumber us, so that’s a very good deal for your side. Please take it.’

‘Hannah, just go!’ said Daphne. ‘I mean, just say you’re out!’

When Daphne glanced back she saw that Hannah was shaking her head, still curled up in a ball on the grass.

‘Oh, screw this,’ said Harry. ‘Chaotics! The faster we stun them, the faster she’s out of here! We’re going to do this very quickly, even if we take casualties! End truce! Tunafish!’

Daphne’s political hindbrain had only an instant to admire how Harry’s few words had just made the Chaotics the good guys, and then in almost perfect unison, the Chaotics were plunging their hands into the pockets of their uniforms and drawing out green sunglasses in an unfamiliar style. Not like anything you would wear to the beach, more like goggles for advanced Potions –

Then Daphne realized what was about to happen and snapped up her other hand to shield her eyes, just as Harry ripped the cloth off the cauldron.

The fluid that spilled forth as Harry Potter threw the cauldron’s contents into the air was too bright to be seen, too brilliant to be imagined, incandescent like the Sun magnified a dozen times –

(which was exactly what it was)

(the sunlight which had been invested to create the acorns, the bright energy that had fuelled a tree rising up from the bare dirt)

(blazing a searing purple, the colour of the mixed blue and red wavelengths that chlorophyll absorbed)

(with almost none of the green wavelengths that chlorophyll reflected to create the green colour of leaves)

(which was the colour of the Chaos Legion’s sunglasses, made to pass through green wavelengths, blocking red and blue, reducing even the most incandescent purple glare to something bearable)

– the violet light blazed on and on, Daphne tried dropping her arm from her eyes but found that she couldn’t look directly at anything, even the second-hand purple glare was so bright she had to squint; and she had only time to cry one Finite Incantatem, which didn’t work, before a Sleep Hex took her.

What was left of the battle didn’t take very long after that.

‘Now!’ bellowed Blaise Zabini, formerly of Sunshine, now commanding a detachment of Chaos Legionnaires. ‘I mean, Tunafish!’ The Slytherin boy’s hand grasped the cloth shielding the cauldron from the triggering touch of daylight, already beginning to move it aside.

‘Now!’ bellowed Dean Thomas, formerly of Chaos, commanding a consignment of Dragon Warriors. ‘Do whatever they do!’

The Chaotics of Zabini’s detachment plunged their hands into their uniform pockets, and came forth bearing green sunglasses –

– an action almost perfectly mirrored by Dean and the Dragon Warriors, who drew forth green-coloured Potions goggles, and quickly drew the straps over their own heads, even as the Chaotics put on their sunglasses and the violet incandescence blasted forth.

(As General Malfoy had explained, if Mr Goyle reported that the Chaos Legion was wearing green-coloured Potions goggles, you didn’t have to know why to Transfigure some copies.)

‘That’s cheating!’ shrieked Blaise Zabini.

‘That’s technique!’ Dean yelled back. ‘Dragons, charge!’

(‘Pardon me,’ the Lady Greengrass said. ‘Could you stop laughing like that, Mr Quirrell? It’s unnerving.’)

‘Finite their goggles!’ shouted Blaise Zabini, as the two armies ran headlong toward each other through omnipresent eye-searing purple glare. ‘We can still win!’

‘You heard him!’ bellowed Dean. ‘Get their glasses!’

Blaise Zabini’s reply to this wasn’t anything articulate.

That battle went on a lot longer.

‘Stupefy!’ shrieked the Sunshine General.

Draco didn’t dodge, he didn’t counter, he didn’t have enough energy left for either, all he could do was whip his left hand into position and hope –

The red stunbolt dissipated again on Draco’s Colloportused glove, which he’d Transfigured and spell-locked to his hand the same as the rest of Dragon Army. It was all that was saving him now, that shield.

It should have been a time to counter-attack, but Draco could only catch his breath, as the two of them danced backward and forward beneath the trees in the never-ending movements of their duel. Across from him, General Granger was panting hard, the young girl’s face glistening with sweat like dew, her chestnut hair wetted into brown plaits. Her camouflage uniform was stained with damp spots, her shoulders visibly trembling with exhaustion, but her wand was still steel-steady where it stayed level on Draco through all their motion. Her eyes glaring, her cheeks flushed with rage.

So, little girl, why’re you pretending to fight like a grown-up today?

The taunt came to mind, but he didn’t really think he needed Granger any angrier; so instead Draco just said – though he could hear his own voice cracking – ‘Any reason you’re feeling mad at me, Granger?’

The girl was gasping for breath herself, her own voice wobbling as she spoke. ‘I know what you’re up to,’ said Hermione Granger, her voice rising. ‘I know what you and Snape are up to, Malfoy, and I know who’s behind it!’

‘Huh?’ Draco said without even thinking about it.

That only seemed to increase Granger’s fury, and her fingers whitened on the wand she held levelled on him.

And then Draco got it, and it boiled his own blood in his veins. Even she thought he was secretly plotting against her –

‘You too?’ Draco yelled. ‘I helped you, you bucktoothed bint! You, you, you,’ – stuttering past all the Dark curses that came to mind until he found something he could actually cast at her – ‘Densaugeo!’

But Granger flashed and whirled around the Tooth-Lengthening Hex, and then her own wand came around and levelled at almost point-blank range, even as Draco brought up his left hand like a shield, placing the magic-locked glove between himself and whatever she was about to fire, and the Sunshine General’s own voice rose to a shriek audible across the whole battleground –

‘Alohomora!’

Time should have paused.

But it didn’t.

Instead the padlock clicked and fell off the glove.

Just like that.

Just like that.

The screens showed it all very clearly, to the entire watching Hogwarts stadium.

And the bone-dead-silent hush that fell over every bench in every stand said that everyone understood quite clearly what it meant, that the scion of House Malfoy had just had his magic overcome by a Muggleborn.

Hermione Granger didn’t pause in her fight, gave no sign that she even knew what she’d done; instead her foot snapped out in a Muggle-style kick that knocked Draco’s wand cleanly out of his hand, his shocked mind and body moving just a little too slowly. Draco dove after his wand, scrabbling frantically on the ground, but from behind him a girl’s cracking voice said ‘Somnium!’ and Draco Malfoy fell and didn’t rise again.

There was another moment of frozen silence. The Sunshine General was wobbling on her feet, looking like she might faint.

Then the Dragon Warriors screamed at the top of their lungs and charged forward to avenge their fallen commander.

Mr and Mrs Davis were shaking as they stood up from the comfortable chairs of the faculty Quidditch box; they couldn’t quite clutch each other while walking, but they held hands tightly, pretending hard to be invisible. If they’d been children young enough for accidental magic they probably would’ve spontaneously Disillusioned themselves.

The elderly Charles Nott said nothing as he stood from his chair. The scarred Lord Jugson said nothing, as he stood from his own chair.

Lucius Malfoy said nothing as he stood.

All three of them turned without pause and strode toward the stairwell of the elevated stands, moving in eerie unison like an Auror trio –

‘Lord Malfoy,’ the Defence Professor said in mild tones. That man was still seated in his own chair, looking upon his parchment-like screens, arms limp at his side, as though for some reason he didn’t feel like moving.

The white-haired man halted just before reaching the exit archway, and the elderly man and the scarred man halted as well, flanking him. Lord Malfoy’s head turned, too slightly to be any form of acknowledgement, but in the Defence Professor’s direction.

‘Your son performed exceptionally well today,’ said Professor Quirrell. ‘I must confess that I underestimated him. And he has earned his army’s loyalty, as you have witnessed.’ Still very mild, the Defence Professor’s voice. ‘Speaking as your son’s teacher, it is my opinion that he will not benefit if you interfere in his –’

Lord Malfoy and his compatriots vanished down the stairs.

‘A fine try, Quirinus,’ Dumbledore said quietly. The old wizard’s face showed small lines of worry; he hadn’t risen from his own seat either, staring at the parchment screens as though they were still active. ‘Do you think he will listen?’

The Defence Professor’s shoulders twitched in a slight shrug, the only movement they’d shown since the battle ended.

‘Well,’ said the Lady Greengrass, as she rose up and cracked her knuckles, stretching, her husband silent beside her. ‘I must say, that was quite … interesting …’

Amelia Bones had risen from her own cushioned seat without any fuss. ‘Interesting indeed,’ said Director Bones. ‘I do confess, I find myself disturbed by the skill with which those children were fighting one another.’

‘The skill?’ Lord Greengrass said. ‘Their spells didn’t seem all that impressive to me. Except for Daphne’s, of course.’

The old witch did not move her eyes from where she was gazing at the Defence Professor’s balding head. ‘The Stunning Hex is not a first-year spell, Lord Greengrass, but that is not the skill I had in mind. They supported each other with those simple spells, they reacted at speed to surprises …’ The Director of the DMLE paused, as though searching for words that a mere civilian could understand. ‘In the midst of battle,’ she said finally, ‘with spells flying in every direction … those children seemed quite at home.’

‘Indeed, Director Bones,’ said the Defence Professor. ‘Some arts are best begun in youth.’

The old witch’s eyes narrowed. ‘You are readying them to become a military force, Professor. To what end?’

‘Now hold on!’ interjected Lord Greengrass. ‘There’s plenty of schools where they teach duelling in first year!’

‘Duelling?’ said the Defence Professor. From behind it wasn’t visible if the pale face was smiling. ‘That is nothing, Lord Greengrass, to what my students have learned. They have learned not to hesitate in the face of ambushes and greater foes. They have learned to adapt when combat conditions change and change again. They have learned to protect their allies, to protect more those who are more valuable, to abandon pieces which cannot be rescued. They have learned that to survive they must follow orders. Some have even learned a little creativity. Oh, no, Lord Greengrass, these wizards will not hide in their manors and wait to be protected, when the next threat comes. They will know that they know how to fight.’

Augusta Longbottom loudly clapped her hands together three times.

The platform was starting to fill up now, but there was still a quieter area on the far side away from the red steam engine. Along the way they passed a stall containing a bald, bearded man offering newspapers and comic books and stacked neon-green cans.

The stall-holder was, in fact, leaning back and drinking out of one of the neon-green cans at the exact point when he spotted the refined and elegant Draco Malfoy approaching along with a mysterious boy looking incredibly stupid with a scarf tied over his face, causing the stall-holder to experience a sudden coughing fit in mid-drink and dribble a large amount of neon-green liquid onto his beard.

‘’Scuse me,’ Harry said, ‘but what is that stuff, exactly?’

‘Comed-Tea,’ said the stall-holder ‘If you drink it, something surprising is bound to happen which makes you spill it on yourself or someone else. But it’s charmed to vanish just a few seconds later –’ Indeed the stain on his beard was already disappearing.

‘How droll,’ said Draco. ‘How very, very droll. Come, Mr Bronze, let’s go find another –’

‘Hold on,’ Harry said.

‘Oh come on! That’s just, just juvenile!’

‘No, I’m sorry Draco, I have to investigate this. What happens if I drink Comed-Tea while doing my best to keep the conversation completely serious?’

The stall-holder smiled mysteriously. ‘Who knows? A friend walks by in a frog costume? Something unexpected is bound to happen –’

‘No. I’m sorry. I just don’t believe it. That violates my much-abused suspension of disbelief on so many levels I don’t even have the language to describe it. There is, there is just no way a bloody drink can manipulate reality to produce comedy setups, or I’m going to give up and retire to the Bahamas –’

Draco groaned. ‘Are we really going to do this?’

‘You don’t have to drink it but I have to investigate. Have to. How much?’

‘Five Knuts the can,’ the stall-holder said.

‘Five Knuts? You can sell reality-manipulating fizzy drinks for five Knuts the can?’ Harry reached into his pouch, said ‘four Sickles, four Knuts’, and slapped them down on the counter. ‘Two dozen cans please.’

‘I’ll also take one,’ Draco sighed, and started to reach for his pockets.

Harry shook his head rapidly. ‘No, I’ve got this, doesn’t count as a favour either, I want to see if it works for you too.’ He took a can from the stack now placed on the counter and tossed it to Draco, then started feeding his pouch. The pouch’s Widening Lip ate the cans accompanied by small burping noises, which wasn’t exactly helping to restore Harry’s faith that he would some day discover a reasonable explanation for all this.

Twenty-two burps later, Harry had the last purchased can in his hand, Draco was looking at him expectantly, and the two of them pulled the ring at the same time.

Harry rolled up his scarf to expose his mouth, and they tilted their heads back and drank the Comed-Tea.

It somehow tasted bright green – extra-fizzy and limer than lime.

Aside from that, nothing else happened.

Harry looked at the stall-holder, who was watching them benevolently.

All right, if this guy just took advantage of a natural accident to sell me twenty-four cans of nothing, I’m going to applaud his creative entrepreneurial spirit and then kill him.

‘It doesn’t always happen immediately,’ the stall-holder said. ‘But it’s guaranteed to happen once per can, or your money back.’

Harry took another long drink.

Once again, nothing happened.

Maybe I should just chug the whole thing as fast as possible … and hope my stomach doesn’t explode from all the carbon dioxide, or that I don’t burp while drinking it …

No, he could afford to be a little patient. But honestly, Harry didn’t see how this was going to work. You couldn’t go up to someone and say ‘Now I’m going to surprise you’ or ‘And now I’m going to tell you the punchline of the joke, and it’ll be really funny.’ It ruined the shock value. In Harry’s state of mental preparedness, Lucius Malfoy could have walked past in a ballerina outfit and it wouldn’t have made him do a proper spit-take. Just what sort of wacky shenanigan was the universe supposed to cough up now?

‘Anyway, let’s sit down,’ Harry said. He prepared to swig another drink and started towards the distant seating area, which put him at the right angle to glance back and see the portion of the stall’s newspaper stand that was devoted to a newspaper called The Quibbler, which was showing the following headline:

Boy-Who-Lived Gets
Draco Malfoy Pregnant

‘Gah!’ screamed Draco as bright green liquid sprayed all over him from Harry’s direction. Draco turned to Harry with fire in his eyes and grabbed his own can. ‘You son of a mudblood! Let’s see how you like being spat upon!’ Draco took a deliberate swig from the can just as his own eyes caught sight of the headline.

In sheer reflex action, Harry tried to block his face as the spray of liquid flew in his direction. Unfortunately he blocked using the hand containing the Comed-Tea, sending the rest of the green liquid to splash out over his shoulder.

Harry stared at the can in his hand even as he went on choking and spluttering and the green colour started to vanish from Draco’s robes.

Then he looked up and stared at the newspaper headline.

Boy-Who-Lived Gets
Draco Malfoy Pregnant

Harry’s lips opened and said, ‘buh-bluh-buh-buh …’

Too many competing objections, that was the problem. Every time Harry tried to say ‘But we’re only eleven!’ the objection ‘But men can’t get pregnant!’ demanded first priority and was then run over by ‘But there’s nothing between us, really!’

Then Harry looked down at the can in his hand again.

He was feeling a deep-seated desire to run away screaming at the top of his lungs until he dropped from lack of oxygen, and the only thing stopping him was that he had once read that outright panic was the sign of a truly important scientific problem.

Harry snarled, threw the can violently into a nearby rubbish bin, and stalked back over to the stall. ‘One copy of The Quibbler, please.’ Harry paid over four more Knuts, retrieved another can of Comed-Tea from his pouch, and then stalked over to the picnic area with the blond-haired boy, who was staring at his own can with an expression of frank admiration.

‘I take it back,’ Draco said, ‘that was pretty good.’

‘Hey, Draco, you know what I bet is even better for becoming friends than exchanging secrets? Committing murder.’

‘I have a tutor who says that,’ Draco allowed. He reached inside his robes and scratched himself with an easy, natural motion. ‘Who’ve you got in mind?’

Harry slammed The Quibbler down hard on the picnic table. ‘The guy who came up with this headline.’

Draco groaned. ‘Not a guy. A girl. A ten-year-old girl, can you believe it? She went nuts after her mother died and her father, who owns this newspaper, is convinced that she’s a seer, so when he doesn’t know he asks Luna Lovegood and believes anything she says.’

Not really thinking about it, Harry pulled the ring on his next can of Comed-Tea and prepared to drink. ‘Are you kidding me? That’s even worse than Muggle journalism, which I would have thought was physically impossible.’

Draco snarled. ‘She has some sort of perverse obsession about the Malfoys, too, and her father is politically opposed to us so he prints every word. As soon as I’m old enough I’m going to rape her.’

Green liquid spurted out of Harry’s nostrils, soaking into the scarf still covering that area. Comed-Tea and lungs did not mix, and Harry spent the next few seconds frantically coughing.

Draco looked at him sharply. ‘Something wrong?’

It was at this point that Harry came to the sudden realisation that (a) the sounds coming from the rest of the train platform had turned into more of a blurred white noise at around the same time Draco had reached inside his robes, and (b) when he had discussed committing murder as a bonding method, there had been exactly one person in the conversation who’d thought they were joking.

Right. Because he seemed like such a normal kid. And he is a normal kid, he is just what you’d expect a baseline male child to be like if Darth Vader were his doting father.

‘Yes, well,’ Harry coughed, oh god how was he going to get out of this conversational wedge, ‘I was just surprised at how you were willing to discuss it so openly, you didn’t seem worried about getting caught or anything.’

Draco snorted. ‘Are you joking? Luna Lovegood’s word against mine?’

Holy crap on a holy stick. ‘There’s no such thing as magical truth detection, I take it?’ Or DNA testing … yet.

Draco looked around. His eyes narrowed. ‘That’s right, you don’t know anything. Look, I’ll explain things to you, I mean the way it really works, just like you were already in Slytherin and asked me the same question. But you’ve got to swear not to say anything about it.’

‘I swear,’ Harry said.

‘The courts use Veritaserum, but it’s a joke really, you just get yourself Obliviated before you testify and then claim the other person was Memory-Charmed with a fake memory. Of course if you’re just some normal person, the courts presume in favour of Obliviation, not False Memory Charms. But the court has discretion, and if I’m involved then it impinges on the honour of a Noble House, so it goes to the Wizengamot, where Father has the votes. After I’m found not guilty the Lovegood family has to pay reparations for tarnishing my honour. And they know from the start that’s how it’ll go, so they’ll just keep their mouths shut.’

A cold chill was coming over Harry, a chill that came with instructions to keep his voice and face normal. Note to self: Overthrow government of magical Britain at earliest convenience.

Harry coughed again to clear his throat. ‘Draco, please please please don’t take this the wrong way, my word is my bond, but like you said I could be in Slytherin and I really want to ask for informational purposes, so what would happen theoretically speaking if I did testify that I’d heard you plan it?’

‘Then if I was anyone other than a Malfoy, I’d be in trouble,’ Draco answered smugly. ‘Since I am a Malfoy … Father has the votes. And afterwards he’d crush you … well, I guess not easily, since you are the Boy-Who-Lived, but Father is pretty good at that sort of thing.’ Draco frowned. ‘’Sides, you talked about murdering her, why weren’t you worried about me testifying after she turns up dead?’

How, oh how did my day go this wrong? Harry’s mouth was already moving faster than he could think. ‘That’s when I thought she was older! I don’t know how it works here, but in Muggle Britain the courts would get a lot more upset about someone killing a child –’

‘That makes sense,’ Draco said, still looking a bit suspicious. ‘But anyway, it’s always smarter if it doesn’t go to the Aurors at all. If we’re careful only to do things that Healing Charms can fix, we can just Obliviate her afterwards and then do it all again next week.’ Then the blonde-haired boy giggled, a youthful high-pitched sound. ‘Though just imagine her saying she’d been done by Draco Malfoy and the Boy-Who-Lived, not even Dumbledore would believe her.’

I am going to tear apart your pathetic little magical remnant of the Dark Ages into pieces smaller than its constituent atoms. ‘Actually, can we hold off on that? After I found out that headline came from a girl a year younger than me, I had a different thought for my revenge.’

‘Huh? Do tell,’ Draco said, and started to take another swig of his Comed-Tea.

Harry didn’t know if the enchantment worked more than once per can, but he did know he could avoid the blame, so he was careful to time it exactly right:

‘I was thinking some day I’m going to marry that woman.’

Draco made a horrid ker-splutching sound and leaked green fluid out the corners of his mouth like a broken car radiator. ‘Are you nuts?’

‘Quite the opposite, I’m so sane it burns like ice.’

‘You’ve got weirder taste than a Lestrange,’ Draco said, sounding half-admiring about it. ‘And I suppose you want her all to yourself, huh?’

‘Yep. I can owe you a favour for it –’

Draco waved it off. ‘Nah, this one’s free.’

Harry stared down at the can in his hand, the coldness settling into his blood. Charming, happy, generous with his favours to his friends, Draco wasn’t a psychopath. That was the sad and awful part, knowing human psychology well enough to know that Draco wasn’t a monster. There had been ten thousand societies over the history of the world where this conversation could have happened. No, the world would have been a very different place indeed, if it took an evil mutant to say what Draco had said. It was very simple, very human, it was the default if nothing else intervened. To Draco, his enemies weren’t people.

And in the slowed time of this slowed country, here and now as in the darkness-before-dawn prior to the Age of Reason, the son of a sufficiently powerful noble would simply take for granted that he was above the law, at least when it came to some peasant girl. There were places in Muggle-land where it was still the same way, countries where that sort of nobility still existed and still thought like that, or even grimmer lands where it wasn’t just the nobility. It was like that in every place and time that didn’t descend directly from the Enlightenment. A line of descent, it seemed, which didn’t quite include magical Britain, for all that there had been cross-cultural contamination of things like ring-pull drinks cans.

And if Draco doesn’t change his mind about wanting revenge, and I don’t throw away my own chance at happiness in life to marry some poor crazy girl, then all I’ve just bought is time, and not too much of it …

For one girl. Not for others.

I wonder how difficult it would be to just make a list of all the top blood purists and kill them.

They’d tried exactly that during the French Revolution, more or less – make a list of all the enemies of Progress and remove everything above the neck – and it hadn’t worked out well from what Harry recalled. Maybe he needed to dust off some of those history books his father had bought him, and see if what had gone wrong with the French Revolution was something easy to fix.

Harry gazed up at the sky, and at the pale shape of the Moon, visible this morning through the cloudless air.

So the world is broken and flawed and insane, and cruel and bloody and dark. This is news? You always knew that, anyway …

‘You’re looking all serious,’ Draco said. ‘Let me guess, your Muggle parents told you that this sort of thing was bad.’

Harry nodded, not quite trusting his voice.

‘Well, like Father says, there may be four houses, but in the end everyone belongs to either Slytherin or Hufflepuff. And frankly, you’re not on the Hufflepuff end. If you decide to side with the Malfoys under the table … our power and your reputation … you could get away with things even I can’t do. Want to try it for a while? See what it’s like?’

Aren’t we a clever little serpent. Eleven years old and already coaxing your prey from hiding …

Harry thought, considered, chose his weapon. ‘Draco, you want to explain the whole blood purity thing to me? I’m sort of new.’

A wide smile crossed Draco’s face. ‘You really should meet Father and ask him, you know, he’s our leader.’

‘Give me the thirty-second version.’

‘Okay,’ Draco said. He drew in a deep breath, and his voice grew slightly lower, and took on a cadence. ‘Our powers have grown weaker, generation by generation, as the mudblood taint increases. Where Salazar and Godric and Rowena and Helga once raised Hogwarts by their power, creating the Locket and the Sword and the Diadem and the Cup, no wizard of these faded days has risen to rival them. We are fading, all fading into Muggles as we interbreed with their spawn and allow our Squibs to live. If the taint is not checked, soon our wands will break and all our arts cease, the line of Merlin will end and the blood of Atlantis fail. Our children will be left scratching at the dirt to survive like the mere Muggles, and darkness will cover all the world for ever.’ Draco took another swig from his drinks can, looking satisfied; that seemed to be the whole argument as far as he was concerned.

‘Persuasive,’ Harry said, meaning it descriptively rather than normatively. It was a standard pattern: The Fall from Grace, the need to guard what purity remained against contamination, the past sloping upwards and the future sloping only down. And that pattern also had its counter … ‘I have to correct you on one point of fact, though. Your information about the Muggles is a bit out of date. We aren’t exactly scratching at the dirt any more.’

Draco’s head snapped around. ‘What? What do you mean, we?’

‘We. The scientists. The line of Francis Bacon and the blood of the Enlightenment. Muggles didn’t just sit around crying about not having wands, we have our own powers now, with or without magic. If all your powers fail then we will all have lost something very precious, because your magic is the only hint we have as to how the universe must really work – but you won’t be left scratching at the ground. Your houses will still be cool in summer and warm in winter, there will still be doctors and medicine. Science can keep you alive if magic fails. It’d be a tragedy, but not literally the end of all the light in the world. Just saying.’

Draco had backed up several feet and his face was full of mixed fear and disbelief. ‘What in the name of Merlin are you talking about, Potter?’

‘Hey, I listened to your story, won’t you listen to mine?’ Clumsy, Harry chided himself, but Draco actually did stop backing off and seem to listen.

‘Anyway,’ Harry said, ‘I’m saying that you don’t seem to have been paying much attention to what goes on in the Muggle world.’ Probably because the whole wizarding world seemed to regard the rest of Earth as a slum, deserving around as much news coverage as the Financial Times awarded to the routine agonies of Burundi. ‘All right. Quick check. Have wizards ever been to the Moon? You know, that thing?’ Harry pointed up to that huge and distant globe.

‘What?’ Draco said. It was pretty clear the thought had never occurred to the boy. ‘Go to the – it’s just a –’ His finger pointed at the little pale thingy in the sky. ‘You can’t Apparate to somewhere you’ve never been and how would anyone get to the Moon in the first place?’

‘Hold on,’ Harry said to Draco, ‘I’d like to show you a book I brought with me, I think I remember what box it’s in.’ And Harry stood up and knelt down and yanked out the stairs to the cavern level of his trunk, then tore down the stairs and heaved a box off another box, coming perilously close to treating his books with disrespect, and snatched off the box cover and quickly but carefully pried out a stack of books –

(Harry had inherited the nigh-magical Verres ability to remember where all his books were, even after seeing them just once, which was rather mysterious considering the lack of any genetic connection.)

And Harry raced back up the stairs and shoved the staircase back into the trunk with his heel, and, panting, turned the pages of the book until he found the picture he wanted to show to Draco.

The one with the white, dry, cratered land, and the suited people, and the blue-white globe hanging over it all.

That picture.

The picture, if only one picture in all the world were to survive.

‘That,’ Harry said, his voice trembling because he couldn’t quite keep the pride out, ‘is what the Earth looks like from the Moon.’

Draco slowly leaned over. There was a strange expression on his young face. ‘If that’s a real picture, why isn’t it moving?’

Moving? Oh. ‘Muggles can do moving pictures but they need a bigger box to show it, they can’t fit them onto single book pages yet.’

Draco’s finger moved to one of the suits. ‘What are those?’ His voice starting to waver.

‘Those are human beings. They are wearing suits that cover their whole bodies to give them air, because there is no air on the Moon.’

‘That’s impossible,’ Draco whispered. There was terror in his eyes, and utter confusion. ‘No Muggle could ever do that. How …’

Harry took back the book, flipped the pages until he found what he saw. ‘This is a rocket going up. The fire pushes it higher and higher, until it gets to the Moon.’ Flipped pages again. ‘This is a rocket on the ground. That tiny speck next to it is a person.’ Draco gasped. ‘Going to the Moon cost the equivalent of … probably around a thousand million Galleons.’ Draco choked. ‘And it took the efforts of … probably more people than live in all of magical Britain.’ And when they arrived, they left a plaque that said, We came in peace, for all mankind. Though you’re not yet ready to hear those words, Draco Malfoy …

‘You’re telling the truth,’ Draco said slowly. ‘You wouldn’t fake a whole book just for this – and I can hear it in your voice. But … but …’

‘How, without wands or magic? It’s a long story, Draco. Science doesn’t work by waving wands and chanting spells, it works by knowing how the universe works on such a deep level that you know exactly what to do in order to make the universe do what you want. If magic is like casting Imperio on someone to make them do what you want, then science is like knowing them so well that you can convince them it was their own idea all along. It’s a lot more difficult than waving a wand, but it works when wands fail, just like if the Imperius failed you could still try persuading a person. And Science builds from generation to generation. You have to really know what you’re doing to do science – and when you really understand something, you can explain it to someone else. The greatest scientists of one century ago, the brightest names that are still spoken with reverence, their powers are as nothing to the greatest scientists of today. There is no equivalent in science of your lost arts that raised Hogwarts. In science our powers wax by the year. And we are beginning to understand and unravel the secrets of life and inheritance. We’ll be able to look at the very blood of which you spoke, and see what makes you a wizard, and in one or two more generations, we’ll be able to persuade that blood to make all your children powerful wizards too. So you see, your problem isn’t nearly as bad as it looks, because in a few more decades, science will be able to solve it for you.’

‘But …’ Draco said. His voice was trembling. ‘If Muggles have that kind of power … then … what are we?’

‘No, Draco, that’s not it, don’t you see? Science taps the power of human understanding to look at the world and figure out how it works. It can’t fail without humanity itself failing. Your magic could turn off, and you would hate that, but you would still be you. You would still be alive to regret it. But because science rests upon my human intelligence, it is the power that cannot be removed from me without removing me. Even if the laws of the universe change on me, so that all my knowledge is void, I’ll just figure out the new laws, as has been done before. It’s not a Muggle thing, it’s a human thing, it just refines and trains the power you use every time you look at something you don’t understand and ask “Why?” You’re of Slytherin, Draco, don’t you see the implication?’

Draco looked up from the book to Harry. His face showed dawning understanding. ‘Wizards can learn to use this power.’

Very carefully, now … the bait is set, now the hook … ‘If you can learn to think of yourself as a human instead of a wizard then you can train and refine your powers as a human.’

And if that instruction wasn’t in every science curriculum, Draco didn’t need to know it, did he?

Draco’s eyes were now thoughtful. ‘You’ve … already done this?’

‘To some extent,’ Harry allowed. ‘My training isn’t complete. Not at eleven. But – my father also bought me tutors, you see.’ Sure, they’d been starving grad students, and it had only been because Harry slept on a 26-hour cycle, but leave all that aside for now …

Slowly, Draco nodded. ‘You think you can master both arts, add the powers together, and …’ Draco stared at Harry. ‘Make yourself Lord of the two worlds?’

Harry gave an evil laugh, it just seemed to come naturally at that point. ‘You have to realise, Draco, that the whole world you know, all of magical Britain, is just one square on a much larger game board. The game board that includes places like the Moon, and the stars in the night sky, which are lights just like the Sun only unimaginably far away, and things like galaxies that are vastly huger than the Earth and Sun, things so large that only scientists can see them and you don’t even know they exist. But I really am Ravenclaw, you know, not Slytherin. I don’t want to rule the universe. I just think it could be more sensibly organised.’

There was awe on Draco’s face. ‘Why are you telling me this?’

‘Oh … there aren’t many people who know how to do true science – understanding something for the very first time, even if it confuses the hell out of you. Help would be helpful.’

Draco stared at Harry with his mouth open.

‘But make no mistake, Draco, true science really isn’t like magic, you can’t just do it and walk away unchanged like learning how to say the words of a new spell. The power comes with a cost, a cost so high that most people refuse to pay it.’

Draco nodded at this as though, finally, he’d heard something he could understand. ‘And that cost?’

‘Learning to admit you’re wrong.’

‘Um,’ Draco said after the dramatic pause had stretched on for a while. ‘You going to explain that?’

‘Trying to figure out how something works on that deep level, the first ninety-nine explanations you come up with are wrong. The hundredth is right. So you have to learn how to admit you’re wrong, over and over and over again. It doesn’t sound like much, but it’s so hard that most people can’t do science. Always questioning yourself, always taking another look at things you’ve always taken for granted,’ like having a Snitch in Quidditch, ‘and every time you change your mind, you change yourself. But I’m getting way ahead of myself here. Way ahead of myself. I just want you to know … I’m offering to share some of my knowledge. If you want. There’s just one condition.’

‘Uh huh,’ Draco said. ‘You know, Father says that when someone says that to you, it is never a good sign, ever.’

Harry nodded. ‘Now, don’t mistake me and think that I’m trying to drive a wedge between you and your father. It’s not about that. It’s just about me wanting to deal with someone my own age, rather than having this be between me and Lucius. I think your father would be okay with that too, he knows you have to grow up sometime. But your moves in our game have to be your own. That’s my condition – that I’m dealing with you, Draco, not your father.’

‘I’ve got to go,’ Draco said. He stood up. ‘I’ve got to go off and think about this.’

‘Take your time,’ Harry said.

The sounds of the train platform changed from blurs into murmurs as Draco wandered off.

Harry slowly exhaled the air he’d been holding in without quite realising it, and then looked at the watch on his wrist, a simple mechanical model that his father had bought him in hope it would work in magic’s presence. The second-hand was still ticking, and if the minute hand was right, then it wasn’t quite eleven just yet. He probably ought to get on the train soon and start looking for whatsherface, but it seemed worth taking a few minutes first to do some breathing exercises and see if his blood warmed up again.

But when Harry looked up from his watch, he saw two figures approaching, looking utterly ridiculous with their faces cloaked by winter scarves.

‘Hello, Mr Bronze,’ said one of the masked figures. ‘Can we interest you in joining the Order of Chaos?’

Not too long after that, when all that day’s fuss had finally subsided, Draco was bent over a desk with quill in hand. He had a private room in the Slytherin dungeons, with its own desk and its own fire – sadly not even he rated a connection to the Floo system, but at least Slytherin didn’t buy into that utter nonsense about making everyone sleep in dorms. There weren’t many private rooms, you had to be the very best within the House of the better sort, but that could be taken for granted with the House of Malfoy.

Dear Father, Draco wrote.

And then he stopped.

Ink slowly dripped from his quill, staining the parchment near the words.

Draco wasn’t stupid. He was young, but his tutors had trained him well. Draco knew that Potter probably felt a lot more sympathy towards Dumbledore’s faction than Potter was letting on … though Draco did think Potter could be tempted. But it was crystal clear that Potter was trying to tempt Draco just as Draco was trying to tempt him.

And it was also clear that Potter was brilliant, and a whole lot more than just slightly mad, and playing a vast game that Potter himself mostly didn’t understand, improvised at top speed with the subtlety of a bull in a china shop. But Potter had managed to choose a tactic that Draco couldn’t just walk away from. He had offered Draco a part of his own power, gambling that Draco couldn’t use it without becoming more like him. His father had called this an advanced technique, and had warned Draco that it often didn’t work.

Draco knew he hadn’t understood everything that had happened … but Potter had offered him the chance to play and right now it was his. And if he blurted the whole thing out, it would become Father’s.

In the end it was as simple as that. The lesser techniques require the unawareness of the target, or at least their uncertainty. Flattery has to be plausibly disguised as admiration. (‘You should have been in Slytherin’ is an old classic, highly effective on a certain type of person who isn’t expecting it, and if it works you can repeat it.) But when you find someone’s ultimate lever it doesn’t matter if they know you know. Potter, in his mad rush, had guessed a key to Draco’s soul. And if Draco knew that Potter knew it – even if it had been an obvious sort of guess – that didn’t change anything.

So now, for the first time in his life, he had real secrets to keep. He was playing his own game. There was an obscure pain to it, but he knew that Father would be proud, and that made it all right.

Leaving the ink drippings in place – there was a message there, and one that his father would understand, for they had played the game of subtleties more than once – Draco wrote out the one question that really had gnawed at him about the whole affair, the part that it seemed he ought to understand, but he didn’t, not at all.

Dear Father:

Suppose I told you that I met a student at Hogwarts, not already part of our circle of acquaintances, who called you a flawless instrument of death and said that I was your one weak point. What would you say about him?

It didn’t take long after that for the family owl to bring the reply.

My beloved son:

I would say that you had been so fortunate as to meet someone who enjoys the intimate confidence of our friend and valuable ally, Severus Snape.

Draco stared at the letter for a while, and finally threw it into the fire.

Trigger warnings

By reader request, a list of trigger warnings - parts of the story with potentially traumatic associations for some readers.

Readers wishing to fully brace themselves mentally may click the appropriate links for complete, spoilerized warnings (i.e., deliberately dilute and avert the whole emotional impact).

Discussion (not depiction) of nonconsensual sex.
First-person depiction (experienced by viewpoint character) of strong [bullying].
Psychologically disturbing psychological instability (usually experienced by viewpoint character). Said emotional distress can be highly disturbing for those who have experienced mental illness and/or emotional abuse/neglect, or otherwise doubt (or have previously doubted) their own mental/emotional sanity or stability.... Does not occur in any one specific area, but increases in intensity at least up to Book 3.
Violent character death (very large spoiler).

During book 1 ch. 10, it is revealed that Luna Lovegood has been writing awful headlines about Draco Malfoy, toward whom Harry is currently acting in a friendly manner. Draco - rather to Harry's surprise - announces his intent to rape Luna as soon as he's old enough. Harry inquires further and finds that Draco is certain that the Lovegood family would be incapable of getting a conviction of Draco in the Wizengamot and, knowing this, would not bother prosecuting. Harry quietly resolves to overthrow the wizarding government. Draco seems to think that rape is a fun thing that young Slytherins get to do and invites Harry to join in when they're old enough, reasoning that no one would possibly believe Luna about it. Harry, thinking quickly, asks Draco to hold off on targeting Lovegood because Harry thinks he might marry her someday. Draco agrees.

In book 2 ch. 15, Professor Quirrell says that Harry has been escalating his battles because he is emotionally incapable of accepting the possibility of losing, and that in order to learn how to lose, Harry will be bullied by older Slytherins, without defending himself. Harry agrees because Professor Quirrell says that otherwise he is afraid Harry will hurt someone. Harry is pushed around, pushed to the ground, sat upon, and must repeatedly say that he loses and that the bullies are better than him. After fifteen minutes, while being pushed around in a circle from bully to bully while trying not to fall over, Professor Quirrell ends the lesson and Harry collapses. Afterward Professor Quirrell says that Harry learned the lesson successfully.

In book 8 ch. 14, the troll gets Hermione. Her legs are eaten off. She dies as Harry watches.